<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SChAth/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SChAth/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="ESday008"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="mss">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gädlä Yasay “Vita of Yasay” / Täʾamrä Yasay “Miracles of Yasay”</title>
            <editor key="DN"/>
            <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob Ludolf Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens: Eine
                                multimediale Forschungsumgebung / beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                                    This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                    Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2013-06-07</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository corresp="INS0100DAY"/>
                  <collection>Ethio-SPaRe</collection>
                  <idno>DAY-008</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <rubric>Nomina sacra; name of the protagonist (Yasay, ʾabba Yasay), of his wife (Ṭǝqmala) and of his disciples (Basǝlyos and ʾArkayos); name of the commissioner and of the donor and his relatives in the text and in Additio 1. &#xD;
Six lines divided into 3 groups, alternating with black lines, in the incipit page of the text (fol. 3r); initial lines (2) of some paragraphs in Text I; incipit (2 lines) of each miracle in Text II; the word halleluya  (halleluiah) on fol. 31va. &#xD;
Elements of the punctuation signs; Ethiopic numerals or their elements.</rubric>
                     <incipit>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en"/>
                     </incipit>
                     <explicit>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en"/>
                     </explicit>
                     <note/>
                  </msItem>
                  <!--The data in the items below refers to other items. please remove this items and move the information to the appropriate place.-->
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2">
                     <note>Text I (Gädlä Yasay)</note>
                     <note>- The text, still unpublished, is contained also in Ms.<ref type="mss" corresp="ESday007">DAY-007</ref>.</note>
                     <note>- The name of the first of the two ʾabba Yasay’s disciples mentioned at the end of the Vita is Basǝlyos; in<ref type="mss" corresp="ESday007">DAY-007</ref>it is Bälbǝyos.</note>
                     <note>- On fol. 31vb l.17 the 9th of Mäskäräm is mentioned as the dies natalis of ʾabba Yasay.</note>
                     <note>- On fol. 32rb, the text ends with a subscriptio containing a supplication for the believers, and for the scribe and the commissioner of the Ms.</note>
                     <note/>
                     <note>Text II (Täʾamrä Yasay)</note>
                     <note>- The miracles are three:</note>
                     <note>II-1) ʾAbba Yasay and the angels who descended from the sky through steps of light (fols. 32vb-33va) (ተአምሪሁ፡ ለብፁዕ፡ ወቅዱስ፡ ያሳይ፡ … ወእንዘ፡ ሀሎ፡ ይጼሊ፡ አባ፡ ያሳይ፡ በውስተ፡ ዕፅ፡ ርእየ፡ በላዕሌሁ፡ መላእክተ፡ ሰማይ፡ እንዘ፡ ይወርዱ፡ በሠዋስወ፡ ብርሃን፡...)</note>
                     <note>II-2) ʾAbba Yasay and the beautiful white dove (fols. 33vb-34va) (ተአምሪሁ፡ ለብፁዕ፡ ወቅዱስ፡ አባ፡ ያሳይ፡ … ወአመ፡ ወጽአ፡ በሌሊት፡ ሐዲጎ፡ መንግሥቶ፡ ረከበቶ፡ አሐቲ፡ ርግብ፡ ፀዓዳ፡ ወሰናይ፡…)</note>
                     <note>III-3) ʾAbba Yasay and the righteous ones (ṣadǝqan) who were in the cave near the saint (fols. 34vb-35vb) (ተአምሪሁ፡ ለብፁዕ፡ ወቅዱስ፡ አባ፡ ያሳይ፡ … ወሀለዉ፡ ጻድቃን፡ በውስተ፡ በዓት፡ ዘበጥቃሁ፡ ለብፁዕ፡ አባ፡ ያሳይ፡… ).</note>
                     <note>- Each miracle is numbered and each number is followed by the Amharic suffix ኛ (-ñña) used for the numerals.</note>
                     <note>The number of the first miracle (fol. 32vb) is written within the frame of the text divider (two chains of red and black dots with nine dots asterisks in the middle) which separates Text I from Text II.</note>
                     <note>The numbers for the miracles 2 and 3 are written (by a secondary hand?) above the text.</note>
                     <note>- On fol. 35vb, the text ends with a subscriptio containing an exhortation of the scribe Gäbrä Ḥǝywät to ʾabba Yasay who is asked to give him the blessing; moreover, at the end the scribe reveals his own name.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>Made of <measure unit="leaf">37.0</measure> folios, of which
                                                  <measure unit="leaf" type="blank"/> blank
                                                  1r, 1v, 2r, 2v, 36v, 37v, in
                                                  <measure unit="quire">6.0</measure> quires (A + 5). 
                                                <dimensions type="outer">
                              <height unit="cm">25.6</height>
                              <width unit="cm">17.5</width>
                              <depth unit="cm">4.0</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation/>
                        <collation>
                           <list>
                              <item xml:id="q1">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">2</dim>
                                 <locus from="1r" to="2v"/>A(2/fols. 1r-2v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q2">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="3r" to="10v"/> I(8/fols. 3r-10v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q3">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="11r" to="18v"/> II(8(fols. 11r-18v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q4">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="19r" to="26v"/> III(8/fols. 19r-26v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q5">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">7</dim>
                                 <locus from="27r" to="33v"/> IV(7; s.l.: 3, stub after 5/fols. 27r-33v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q6">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">4</dim>
                                 <locus from="34r" to="37v"/> V(4/fols. 34r-37v).</item>
                           </list>
                        </collation>
                        <condition key="good">Cut repaired in fol. 15.&#xD;
Fol. 37 is of a smaller size (cut at the bottom?).</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="19">
                           <dimensions unit="mm">
                              <height>164</height>
                              <width>134</width>
                              <dim type="intercolumn">15</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="margin">
                              <dim type="top">27</dim>
                              <dim type="bottom">46</dim>
                              <dim type="right">25</dim>
                              <dim type="left">15</dim>
                              <dim type="intercolumn">15</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>All data are for fol. 4r.</note>
                           <ab type="ruling"/>
                           <ab type="pricking">Pricking and ruling are visible. </ab>
                           <ab type="ruling" subtype="pattern">
Ruling pattern: </ab>
                           <ab>
1A-1A-1A1A/0-0/0-0/C. </ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">
Primary pricks are visible. </ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">
Ruling pricks are visible. </ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">
Structural pricks are visible. </ab>
                           <ab type="ruling">
The upper line is written above the ruling. </ab>
                           <ab type="ruling">
The bottom line is written above the ruling.</ab>
                        </layout>
                        <layout/>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><!--ACHTUNG! first HandNote comes from writing system in Ethiospare. the others are one for each CHANGE OF HAND-->
                     <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                        <ab type="script">Mediocre.</ab>
                        <seg type="ink">Black; red (pink).</seg>
                        <persName role="scribe" corresp="PRS00000">Gäbrä Ḥǝywät.</persName>The name of the scribe is mentioned in the subscriptio (s. “other details”) at the end of Text II (fol. 35vb) and with the abbreviated form ገ፡ ሕ፡ ት፡ in the supplication formula on fol. 7ra (ls.12-13)<date>Mid-20th century</date>
                        <list type="abbreviations">
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ለዓ፡ ዓለ፡ አ፡</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ለዓለመ፡ ዓለም፡ አሜን፡ </expan> (fols. 22rb, 33va)</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ለዓ፡ ዓለ፡</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ለዓለመ፡ ዓለም፡ </expan> (fol. 32vb)</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>እ፡</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>እንተ፡ (?) </expan> (fol. 32ra)</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ገ፡ ሕ፡ ት፡</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ገብረ፡ ሕይወት፡ </expan> (fol. 7ra)</item>
                        </list>
                     </handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h2" script="Ethiopic">The handwriting is characterized by thick and broadly spaced letters. <!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h3" script="Ethiopic">
- The word እግዚአብሔር፡ (or እግዚእ፡) is sometimes written with ligature (e.g., fol. 32vb ls.9-10); <!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h4" script="Ethiopic">
- The letter ለ and the letter ሰ are not easily distinguishable as well as the 1th and the 6th order of the letter ሰ.<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <additions><!--THIS element in domlib CONTAINS ESCAPED HTML, thus it is not possible to reliably extract the information about pages. Please watch out.-->
                     <list>
                        <item xml:id="a1">
                           <locus target="#36ra">Fol. 36ra</locus>-b: Donation note.<q xml:lang="gez">Fol. 36ra: ዝመጽሐፍ፡ ዘአቶ፡ ገብሩ፡ ሃይሉ፡ ወስመ፡ ጥምቅቱ፡ ገብረ፡ ጊዮርጊስ፡ ወአጽሐፊሁ፡ አቶ፡ ካህሳይ፡ ሃይሉ፡ ወስመ፡ ጥምቀቱ፡ ወልደ፡ ማርያም፡ ዘወሀቦ፡ ለታቦተ፡ አቡነ፡ ያሳይ፡ ድርባ፡ ከመ፡ ይኩኖ፡ መርሐ፡ ለመንግሥተ፡ ሰማያት፡ ወስመ፡ አቡሁ፡ ወልደ፡ ሩፋኤል፡ ወእሙ፡ ወለተ፡ ኪዳን፡ ወለተ፡ ኪዳን፡ ወለተ፡ ሩፋኤል፡ ወያርፍቆሙ፡ ውስተ፡ ሕጽነ፡ አብርሃም፡ ይስሐቅ፡ ወ[fol. 36rb]ያዕቆብ፡ እስከ፡ ለዓለም። ወለእለ፡ ሀለዉ፡ በሕይወቶሙ፡ ይዕቀቦሙ፡ {እግዚአብሔር፡} በጸሎቱ፡ ለብፁዕ፡ አባ፡ ያሳይ፡ ለፍቁራኒሁ፡ [vac.]፡ ዘሰረቆ፡ ወዘፈሐቆ፡ ለዝንቱ፡ መጽሐፍ፡ በሥ&lt;ል&gt;ጣነ፡ ጴጥሮስ፡ ወጳውሎስ፡ ውጉዛ፡ ለይኩን፡ አሜን፡ ለይኩን፡ ለይኩን። በ፲፱፻፵፱ዓ፡ መጋቢት፲፰ቀ፡ ተጻፈ፡ </q>
                           <q xml:lang="en"/>
                           The note, written in a secondary hand in black and red ink, mentions ʾato Gäbrä Haylu (baptismal name Gäbrä Giyorgis) as the owner of the Ms. and ʾato Kahsay Haylu (baptismal name Wäldä Maryam) as the commissioner and the one who donated it to the church (tabot) of ʾabunä Yasay Dǝrba. Besides them, the names of the Wäldä Maryam’s relatives are mentioned: his father Wäldä Rufaʾel, his mother Wälättä Kidan. At the end it is mentioned the date in which the Ms. was written: 1949 A.M., on the 18th of Mäggabit. In the date, after the abbreviation (ዓ፡) for ዓመት፡, the word ምሕረት፡, designating the Ethiopian year, is missing. On fol. 36rb, the note is interrupted by empty ruled lines (lacuna or left intentionally unfilled?).
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a2">
                           <locus target="#37r">Fol. 37r</locus>: Sälam-hymn for Yasay.<q xml:lang="gez">Fol. 37r: ሰላም፡ ለዝክረ፡ ስምከ፡ ለዓለም፡ ዘይሄሉ። ለነብይ፡ በከመ፡ ባህሉ። ንጉሥ፡ ሃይማኖት፡ ያሳይ፡...</q>
                           <q xml:lang="en"/>
                           The note is written in pink ink. The same hymn is repeated, in pencil and probably by a different hand, at the right side of the Additio.
Crude unreadable notes in pen are below it.
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e1">- It is not clear whether the rubricator was always the scribe himself: the rubrications of the name of the protagonist and parts of the text are carried out by the scribe himself, the rubrications of the names of the donor or the commissioner of the Ms. seem to be written by a secondary hand but with the same ink.&#xD;
- A few times the letters ሠ and ሰ are exchanged (s., e.g, the name of Yasay on fol. 7vb l.5).&#xD;
- On fol. 35vb, the word ሃሌሉያ፡ (“halleluiah”), followed by the words እምቅ፡ ዓ፡ የነብር፡ አምላክ፡ (?), is written in red ink ‒ by the same hand which filled the rubricated spaces in the supplication formulas throughout the Ms. ‒ Within the frame of the text divider (two chains of red and black dots with nine dots asterisks in the middle).&#xD;
- On fol. 35vb, at the bottom of the column, the names of some individuals are written by the same hand and ink as for the words above mentioned (not clear whether as continuation of them), within the frame of the text divider (two chains of red and black dots) which delimits Text II from the following additio (Additio 1, on the next fol.). &#xD;
These individuals are: Gäbrä Giyorgis, his father Wäldä Rufaʾel and his mother Wälättä Kidan (ገብረ፡ ጊዮርጊስ፡ ወአቡሁ፡ ወልደ፡ ሩፋኤል፡ ወእሙ፡ ወለተ፡ ኪዳን፡).&#xD;
These names are mentioned, together or individually, both in the supplication formulas throughout the Ms. (written by the same hand as on fol. 35vb) and in Additio 1. However, they are mentioned in roles which do not coincide:&#xD;
in supplication formula on fol. 7ra (ls. 13-14), Gäbrä Giyorgis is mentioned as the commissioner; in Additio 1 he is mentioned as the owner of the Ms. while Wäldä Maryam occurs as the donor and the commissioner (cp. Additio 1). Again in Additio 1, the names of the individuals mentioned as the Wäldä Maryam’s relatives are the same names mentioned as the Gäbrä Giyorgis’ relatives on fol. 35vb, i.e., Wäldä Rufaʾel and Wälättä Kidan.&#xD;
- The names of Gäbrä Giyorgis or of his relatives (s. above) are written interlineally: e.g., fols. 3ra, 11rb.&#xD;
- Omitted letters or words are written interlineally: e.g., fols. 17ra, 22rb, 33va, 34va.&#xD;
- Erasures marked by thin parallel red lines on fols. 34rb and 35rb.&#xD;
- Crude notes by recent hands, in pen and pencil, in the margins and inside the text throughout the Ms.: e.g., fols. 15v, 30r, 31r, 37r (below Additio 2).</item>
                     </list>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding contemporary="true">
                        <decoNote xml:id="b1">Two wooden boards fully covered with reddish-brown tooled leather. &#xD;
Two pairs of sewing stations.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b2" type="bindingMaterial">
                           <material key="wood"/>
                           <material key="leather"/>
                        </decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b3" type="Endbands"/>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b4" type="Other">Two pairs of chains of endband stitches at the spine cover.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b5">Blind tooled ornament on the reddish-brown leather cover (1 tool was used: fourfold line fillet).</decoNote>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <placeName corresp="INS0100DAY">Dǝrba Däbrä ʾAbunä Yasay  /DAY</placeName>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate notBefore="1956" notAfter="1957">1949 A.M. (= 1956/1957 A.D.)&#xD;
The date is mentioned in Additio 1.</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <listBibl type="catalogue">
                              <bibl/>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <custodialHist>
                        <custEvent type="restorations" subtype="none"/>
                     </custodialHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl/>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="secondary">
                     <bibl>Ms. previously unknown.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Encoded according to TEI P5 Guidelines.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person>
                  <persName role="owner" corresp="PRS0000">The commissioner and donor of the Ms., according to Additio 1, is ʾato Kahsay Haylu, whose baptismal name is Wäldä Maryam; but according to the supplication formula on fol. 7ra (ls.13-14), the commissioner is Gäbrä Giyorgis (the baptismal name Gäbrä Haylu), who is mentioned in Additio 1 as the owner. &#xD;
The name Gäbrä Giyorgis is written in red (by a secondary hand?) in the supplication formulas throughout the Ms., alone or together with the names Wäldä Rufaʾel and Wälättä Kidan. These people are mentioned as Gäbrä Giyorgis’ relatives (the former as his father and the latter as his mother) in a list of names after Text II (s. “Varia”); they also appear   in Additio 1, here as the father and the mother of Kahsay Haylu/Wäldä Maryam.</persName>
                  <!--ACHTUNG! This is actually paragraphic information identifying the donor. 
                                        Person/persName should only contain the person name, not all the paragraph.-->
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName role="scribe" corresp="PRS00000">Gäbrä Ḥǝywät.</persName>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName role="owner" corresp="PRS0000">ʾato Gäbrä Haylu (baptismal name Gäbrä Giyorgis) is the name mentioned as the owner of the Ms. in Additio 1.</persName>
                  <!--ACHTUNG! This is actually paragraphic information identifying the donor. 
                                        Person/persName should only contain the person name, not all the paragraph.-->
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName corresp="PRS00000"/>
                  <!--other-->
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term key="Hagiography"/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Inglese</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez" xml:id="Lan05">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="DN" when="2010-12-16">registered</change>
         <change who="VP" when="2013-06-07">created</change>
         <change who="EG" when="2014-07-25">last edited</change>
         <change who="PL" when="2016-05-10">transformed from mycore to TEI
                            P5</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
