<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SChAth/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SChAth/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="ESgms008"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="mss">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Haymanotä ʾabäw “Faith of the Fathers”</title>
            <editor key="DN"/>
            <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob Ludolf Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens: Eine
                                multimediale Forschungsumgebung / beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                                    This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                    Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2012-10-18</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository corresp="INS0125GMS"/>
                  <collection>Ethio-SPaRe</collection>
                  <idno>GMS-008</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <rubric>Nomina sacra; a few lines on the incipit page, alternating with black lines; two initial lines of each section; elements of punctuation signs; elements of Ethiopic numerals; the words: kǝfl (e.g., fols. 49rc, 48vc, 98rb), fǝkkare (e.g., fols. 98rb, 100ra, 100vc), tǝʿǝzaz (fol. 107rc), qädamay (fol. 107rc), dagǝmay (fol. 107rc).</rubric>
                     <incipit>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en"/>
                     </incipit>
                     <explicit>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en"/>
                     </explicit>
                     <note/>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="coloph1">
                     <colophon>
                        <locus target="108rb"/>Fol. 108rb፡ ዝንቱ፡ መጽሐፍ፡ ዘማርያም፡ ሳኤት፡ ዘተጽሕፈ፡ በዘመነ፡ ዮሐንስ፡ በ፲፻ወ፯፻፺ወ፮፡ ዓመተ፡ ዓለም። በሲመተ፡ ገበዝ፡ ገብረ፡ ድንግል፡ ዘሠረቆ፡ ወዘፈሐቆ፡ ዘሴጦ፡ ወዘተሳየጦ፡ በሥልጣነ፡ ጴጥሮስ፡ ወጳውሎስ፡ ውጉዘ፡ ለይኩን፡ ለዓለመ፡ ዓለም፡ አሜን። <foreign xml:lang="en">Fol. 108rb: This book is of Maryam Saʾet which was written in the year of John, in 1796 year of the world when Gäbrä Dǝngǝl was gäbäz. May the one who stole it and erased it, sold it and bought it, be excommunicated by the authority of Peter and Paul. Forever and ever. Amen.
</foreign>
                        <note>Written possibly in a secondary hand, the colophon mentions the date 1796 year of the world (probably 1803 A.D.).</note>
                     </colophon>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>Made of <measure unit="leaf">108.0</measure> folios, of which
                                                  <measure unit="leaf" type="blank">2.0</measure> blank
                                                  1v, 108v., in
                                                  <measure unit="quire">14.0</measure> quires (A+13). 
                                                <dimensions type="outer">
                              <height unit="cm">37.0</height>
                              <width unit="cm">28.5</width>
                              <depth unit="cm">6.0</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation/>
                        <collation>
                           <list>
                              <item xml:id="q1">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">2</dim>
                                 <locus from="1r" to="2v"/>A(2/fols. 1r-2v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q2">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="3r" to="12v"/> I(10/fols. 3r-12v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q3">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="13r" to="20v"/> II(8/fols. 13r-20v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q4">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="21r" to="28v"/> III(8/fols. 21r-28v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q5">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="29r" to="36v"/> IV(8/fols. 29r-36v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q6">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="37r" to="44v"/> V(8/fols. 37r-44v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q7">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="45r" to="52v"/> VI(8/fols. 45r-52v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q8">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="53r" to="60v"/> VII(8; s.l.: 1, stub after 8; 8, stub after 1/fols. 53r-60v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q9">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="61r" to="68v"/> VIII(8/fols. 61r-68v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q10">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="69r" to="76v"/> IX(8/fols. 69r-76v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q11">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="77r" to="84v"/> X(8/fols. 77r-84v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q12">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="85r" to="92v"/> XI(8/fols. 85r-92v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q13">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="93r" to="100v"/> XII(8/fols. 93r-100v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q14">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="101r" to="108v"/> XIII(8; s.l.: 4, stub after 4; 5, stub after 3/fols. 101r-108v).</item>
                           </list>
                        </collation>
                        <condition key="deficient">Both boards are broken and crudely repaired.&#xD;
A part of the back board is missing.&#xD;
Some fols. are heavily stained with water.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="3" writtenLines="36">
                           <dimensions unit="mm">
                              <height>280</height>
                              <width>245</width>
                              <dim type="intercolumn">15</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="margin">
                              <dim type="top">30</dim>
                              <dim type="bottom">60</dim>
                              <dim type="right">30</dim>
                              <dim type="left">15</dim>
                              <dim type="intercolumn"/>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>All data for fol. 4r.</note>
                           <ab type="ruling"/>
                           <ab type="pricking">Ruling and pricking are partly visible. </ab>
                           <ab type="ruling" subtype="pattern">
Ruling pattern: 1A-1A-1A1A-1A1A/0-0/0-0/C.</ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">
Primary pricks are not visible. </ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">
Ruling pricks are partly visible.</ab>
                           <ab type="ruling">
The upper line is written above the ruling.</ab>
                           <ab type="ruling">
The bottom line is written above the ruling.</ab>
                        </layout>
                        <layout/>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><!--ACHTUNG! first HandNote comes from writing system in Ethiospare. the others are one for each CHANGE OF HAND-->
                     <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                        <ab type="script">Irregular.</ab>
                        <seg type="ink">Black, red (vivid vermilion).</seg>
                        <persName role="scribe" corresp="PRS00000">ʾAsbä Dǝngǝl</persName>The scribe, ʾAsbä Dǝngǝl, is mentioned in the supplication formula in Additio 2.<date>Early 19th century.</date>
                        <list type="abbreviations">
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ክ/ክፍ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ክፍል </expan> (e.g., fols. 48vc, 52ra, 98va).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ተፈ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ተፈሥሒ </expan> (fol. 49va).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ማር</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ማርያም </expan> (fol. 49va).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ዝን</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ዝንቱ </expan> (fol. 78rb).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ቅ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ቅዱስ </expan> (fol. 78rb).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ያዕ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ያዕቆብ </expan> (fol. 78rb).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ይ/ዘ/ዘይ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ይቤ/ዘይቤ </expan> (e.g., fols. 78rb, 99va, 102rc).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ወካ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ወካዕበ </expan> (fol. 78rc).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ጳ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ጳጳስ </expan> (fol. 81ra).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ፍ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ፍካሬ </expan> (e.g., fols. 98va, 100rc, 101rb).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>እ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>እመቦ </expan> (e.g., fols. 99va, 102rc, 102va).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ትእ/ትእዛ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ትእዛዝ </expan> (fol. 107rc).</item>
                           <item>
                              <abbr>ኤ᎓ ቆ</abbr> for
                                                  <expan>ኤጲስ ቆጶስ</expan> (fols. 107vc, 108ra).</item>
                        </list>
                     </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <additions><!--THIS element in domlib CONTAINS ESCAPED HTML, thus it is not possible to reliably extract the information about pages. Please watch out.-->
                     <list>
                        <item xml:id="a1">
                           <locus target="#2v">Fol. 2v</locus>: Scribe’s note on commencing the work.<q xml:lang="gez">Fol. 2v: ናሁ: ወጠንኩ: መጽሐፈ: ሃይማኖተ: አበው: አመ: ፳ለጥር።</q>
                           <q xml:lang="en">Fol. 2v: Behold! I have commenced the book of Haymanotä ʾabäw in the 20th of Ṭǝrr.</q>
                           The date 20 Ṭǝrr is mentioned.
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a2">
                           <locus target="#108ra">Fol. 108ra</locus>-rb: Supplication note for the donors and the scribe.<q xml:lang="gez">Fol. 108ra-rb: ፀሎቶሙ: ወበረከቶሙ: ይዕቀቦ[sic]: ለገብሩ[sic]: ወልደ: ኪሮስ: ጽጌ: መስቀል: ይስሐቅ: ወልደ: ክርስቶስ: ወልደ: ሥላሴ: ስብሐት: ለአብ።  ወምስለ: ዓዕማቲሁ: ወለተ: ጊዮርጊስ: ወለተ: ሐና: ወለተ: ሥላሴ: ወለተ: ዮሐንስ: ርግበ: ሥላሴ: ለዓለመ: ዓለም። ወሊተኒ: ዘጸሐፍኩ: ዛቲ: መጽሐፍ: ሕብዓኒ: እምሐከከ: ሰብእ: ወእመከራሁ: ለሰይጣን: ወሠውረኒ: እምኵሉ: እኩይ: ወፈጽም: ፈቃድየ: ዘእንበለ: ኃጢአት: ባሕቲታ: ወኢትኔጽር: አበሳየ: ወጌጋይየ: ወደምስስ: መጽሐፈ: እዳየ:: ወአንትሙኒ: ካህናት: ውሉደ: ቤተ: ክርስቲያን: ለለአንበብክሙ: ዘንተ: መጽሐፈ: አምሐኩክሙ: ወአማኅፀንክሙ[sic]: በታቦተ: ጽዮን: ቅድስት: ከመ: ኢትርስኡኒ: አቡነ: ዘበሰማያት: ለኃጥእ: ወአባሲ: ሐካይ: ወጊጉይ: ዘማዊ: ወደነዊ[sic]: አስበ: ድንግል: ለዓለመ: ዓለም: አሜን። </q>
                           <q xml:lang="en">Fol. 108ra-rb: May their prayer and blessing protect their servants Wäldä Kiros, Ṣǝgge Mäsqäl, Yǝsḥaq, Wäldä Krǝstos, Wäldä Śǝllase, Sǝbhat Lä-ʾAb; and with their maid servants Wälättä Giyorgis, Wälättä Ḥanna, Wälättä Śǝllase, Wälättä Yoḥannǝs, Rǝgbä Śǝllase, for ever and ever. And as to me who has written this book, hide me from the quarrel of people and the temptation of Satan. Protect me from all evil and may You fulfill my wishes except solely of sin. May You disregard my sin and transgression but abolish the register of my debt. And you priests, children of the church, who read this book, I greet you and entrust you by the tabotä of Holy Sion not to neglect Pater Noster to me, the wicked and sinner, lazy and faulty, adulterer and fornicator ʾAsbä Dǝngǝl, forever and ever. Amen. </q>
                           
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a3">
                           <locus target="#108rc">Fol. 108rc</locus>: Excommunication against those transgressing the church land property (land charter of Śaʾet Maryam) <q xml:lang="gez">Fol. 108rc: ጓል: ሐፄይ: ዓምደ: ጽዮን: ንግሥት: ማርያም: ዘአጽሐፈት: ዘሄዳ: ወዘተዓገላ: ውጉዘ: ይኩን: ከመ: አርዮስ። እመሂ: ሥዩመ: ሀገር: አው: በዓለ: ነጋሪት: ወእመሂ: በዓለ: ገንታ: ለእመ: ተአደውዋ: ወለእመ: ሔድዋ: ወለእመ: ነሥእዋ: ምድራሂ: አው: ንዑሰ: ወዓቢየ: ዘእንበለ: ለሞጣሕት: ወለቀሚስ: ወለመባእ: ወለዕጣን: በሥልጣነ: ጴጥሮስ: ወጳውሎስ። በሥልጣነ: አብ: ወወልድ: ወመንፈስ: ቅዱስ: ውጉዘ: ይኩን። ዘነሥአ: በኃይለ: ንዋያ: ለቤተ: ክርስቲያን: ማርያም: ሣኤት: ዘእንበለ: በቄሰ: ገበዝ: ይስሐቅ: ወኢይቢት: በምድራሂ: ወኢይቅረብ: መኰንን: በነጋሪት: ስዩም: በገንታ: አላ: ይሑር: ይስሐቅ: ውስተ: ቤተ: መኳንንት። ከመ: ኢይምጽእዎ: ውስተ: ቤቱ: ወውስተ: ዓፀዳ: ለማርያም: ሣኤት: ሠሪሮ: በፈረስ: ወበበቅል። ኢይብላዕ: ሣዕራ: ወኢይስተይ: ማያ። ወዘንተ: ቃለ: ዘተዓደወ: ይጥፋእ: እምድር: ዝክሩ: ወትርኀቅ: በረከት: ውስተ: ቤቱ: ወትኩን: መካነ: ብእሲቱ: ወኢይትረሣዕ: በቀለ: ውስተ: ቤተ: እስራኤል: ወይትበቀሎ: እግዚአብሔር: እስከ: ሰብአቱ: ትውልድ። ፪ኤ: ግራ: ማርያም: ታሕት። ፪ኈፃ: ፩ወግር: ማይ: ኑም: ማይ: ዔላ: ጣራ: ጉንድ: ጢሳ: ማአከል: ሞሳልቅ: ግራ: ማርያም: ግራ: ጉንች: ማይ: ሕሙቅ። ዝንቱ: ኵሉ: ዘእንበለ: በቄሰ: ገበዝ: ፈቃድ: ከመ: ኢይሐርስ: ተሐቢሙ: በኃይል: በሥልጣነ: ጴጥሮስ: ወጳውሎስ። ዘ፲ወ፪ሐዋርያት: በአፈ: ፸ወ፪አርድእት። በአፈ: ፫፻ ፲ወ፰ርቱዓነ: ሃይማኖት። ውጉዘ: ለይኩን። </q>
                           <q xml:lang="en">Fol. 108rc: Nǝgǝśt Maryam, the daughter of Emperor ʿAmdä Ṣǝyon, caused it to be written. May the one who robbed it and mistreated it be excommunicated like Arius. Be he an official of a province or holder of nägarit-drum, or a commander of troops, if they surpassed it and if they confiscated it, if they took its land, small or big, except for the purpose of cloak, tunicle, offering and incense, (may be excommunicated) by the authority of Peter and Paul. May the one who abducted the property of Maryam Śaʾet church be excommunicated by the authority of the Father, the Son and the Holy Spirit. Except through (the permission of) qesä gäbäz Yǝsḥaq, a ruler should not stay in its land or should not approach (beating) nägarit-drum, and an official should not accompanied by troops, but rather Yǝsḥaq shall go to the house of dignitaries. So that they do not come to his house and to the territory of Maryam Śaʾet seating on a horse or mule. May not (their burden animals) eat its grass and drink its water. Anyone who breaks this word, may his memory be vanished from the earth, may blessing be away from his house, may his wife be barren. Revenge will not be forgotten in the house of Israel and God will avenge him as far as the seventh generation. Beyond Kǝlʾe Gǝra Maryam, 2 ḫ<hi rend="apices">w</hi>oḍa, 1 wägr, May Num, May ʿEla, Ṭara Gund, Ṭisa Maʾakäl, Mosalǝq, Gǝra Maryam, Gǝra Gunch, May Ḥǝmuq, all these will not be cultivated without the permission of qesä gäbäz, on whom a power is vested by the authority of Peter and Paul. (May the one who breaks this) be excommunicated by the 12 Apostles, by the word of 72 disciples and by the word of the 318 Orthodox. </q>
                           Written in a secondary hand. The land charter is said to have been issued by Nǝgǝśt Maryam, the daughter of King ʿAmdä Ṣǝyon (?).
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e1">- A fingerprint encircled by the word ፊርማየ “my signature”, and a sentence ናይ መጽሐፈ አበው “of the Book of the fathers”: fol. 1r.&#xD;
- An excerpt from the homily of ʾAgnaṭǝyos, and a prayer on the commencement the book: fol. 2r.&#xD;
- Writing exercises in the bottom margins of fols 2v, 3r.&#xD;
- Pen trial in the bottom of fol. 86r.&#xD;
- Parchment cuts crudely repaired: fols. 1, 37, 44, 81, 102, 108.&#xD;
- Spaces left for rubrication: fols. 6rc, 19va, 20ra, 20rb, 20rc.&#xD;
- Immediate corrections indicated by thin lines above and below words: e.g., fols. 33ra, 37vb, 65rc.&#xD;
- Corrections written interlineally: e.g., fols. 43r, 45r, 51r.&#xD;
- Corrections written on the margins: e.g., fols. 79r, 80r, 64r.&#xD;
- Tämälläs-sign: fols. 64rc, 73va, 79rb.&#xD;
- Pen trial in the lower margin of fol. 86r.</item>
                     </list>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding contemporary="true">
                        <decoNote xml:id="b1">Two wooden boards (both are broken and crudely repaired).&#xD;
Two pairs of sewing stations.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b2" type="bindingMaterial">
                           <material key="wood"/>
                        </decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b3" type="Endbands"/>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b4" type="Other">Two rows of small holes are visible on the spine fold of the quires, one close to the head and one close to the tail of the codex.</decoNote>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <placeName corresp="INS0125GMS">SiË&#x81;et QÓ&#x99;ddÓ&#x99;st Maryam / GMS</placeName>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate notBefore="1803" notAfter="1803">The date 1796 year of the world (= 1803 A.D.) is mentioned in the colophon (fol. 108rb).</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <listBibl type="catalogue">
                              <bibl/>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <custodialHist>
                        <custEvent type="restorations" subtype="modern"/>
                     </custodialHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl/>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="secondary">
                     <bibl>The Ms. previously unknown.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Encoded according to TEI P5 Guidelines.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person>
                  <persName role="owner" corresp="PRS0000">Several names are mentioned in the supplication formula in Additio 2: Wäldä Kiros, Ṣǝgge Mäsqäl, Yǝsḥaq, Wäldä Krǝstos, Wäldä Śǝllase, Sǝbhat Lä-ʾAb, Wälättä Giyorgis, Wälättä Ḥanna, Wälättä Śǝllase, Wälättä Yoḥannǝs, Rǝgbä Śǝllase.</persName>
                  <!--ACHTUNG! This is actually paragraphic information identifying the donor. 
                                        Person/persName should only contain the person name, not all the paragraph.-->
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName role="scribe" corresp="PRS00000">ʾAsbä Dǝngǝl</persName>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName corresp="PRS00000"/>
                  <!--other-->
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term key="Theology"/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Inglese</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez" xml:id="Lan05">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="DN" when="2010-12-07">registered</change>
         <change who="AA" when="2012-10-18">created</change>
         <change who="DN" when="2014-11-24">last edited</change>
         <change who="PL" when="2016-05-10">transformed from mycore to TEI
                            P5</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
