<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SChAth/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SChAth/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="ESmkl016"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="mss">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gädlä Kiros “Vita of Kiros” / Mälkǝʾa Kiros “Image of Kiros” (I) / Homily by Rǝtuʿa Haymanot on the Four Living Creatures</title>
            <editor key="DN"/>
            <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob Ludolf Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens: Eine
                                multimediale Forschungsumgebung / beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                                    This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                    Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2011-08-08</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository corresp="INS0123MKL"/>
                  <collection>Ethio-SPaRe</collection>
                  <idno>MKL-016</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <locus from="3r" to="92r">3r-92r</locus>
                     <title type="Complete">I. Gädlä Kiros “Vita of Kiros”</title>
                     <rubric>Nomina sacra; name of the protagonist; name of the commissioner (fols. 3rb, 70vb, 90vb, 99rb); two initial lines in the incipit page of Texts I and III; word sälam in Text II; selected lines in all the texts (27vb, 105ra, 108va, 117vb); elements of the punctuation signs;  elements of Ethiopic numerals.</rubric>
                     <incipit>Fol. 3rab: በስመ፡”… ንቀድም፡ በረድኤተ፡ እግዚእነ ኢየሱስ ክርስቶስ፨ ገድል፡ ወስምዕ፡ ዘቅዱስ፡ ወብፁዕ፡ አባ፡ ኪሮስ መስተጋድል፨ ጸሎቱ፡ ወበረከቱ፡ የሃሉ፡ ምስለ፡ ፍቁሩ ጽጌ ሃይማኖት፡ ለዓለመ፡ዓለም አሜን፡፡ ወነበረ፡ በመንበረ፡ አቡሁ[fol. 3vb]ዮናኒ በምግባራተ፡ አቡሁ፡ ወኢያንተገ፡ እምኔሁ፨ ወነበረ፡ ፷ዓመተ፡ ወወለደ፡ ወልደ፡ ዘስሙ፡ አብያ፨ ወእምዝ አዕረፈ፡ አቡሁ በክብር፨ ወነበረ፡ አብያ፡ ዲበ፡ መንበረ፡ አቡሁ ወኢያንተገ፡ እምኔሁ፡ ወኢአሐተኒ፨ ወሰማ[sic]፡ ለብእሲቱ፡ ኒናሲር፡ ወነበረት፡ መካነ፡ ፴ዓመተ፨ ወእምዝ፡ ጸለዩ፡ ኀበ፡ እግዚአብሔር፡ ወፀንሰት፡ በጊዜ፶፡ ወወለደት፡ መንታ᎒<foreign xml:lang="en">Fol. 5rab: In the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, one God. We shall begin, with the help of our Lord Jesus Christ, the vita and testimony (to the faith) of the holy and blessed father Kiros, an ascetic. May his prayer and blessing be with his beloved Ṣǝge Haymanot, forever and ever, Amen.  And there was on the throne of his father [fol. 3vb]Yonani with the deeds of his father and did not abandon that (duty); and he ruled for 60 years; and he begat a son whose name was ʿAbya. And afterwards his father died in glory and ʿAbya (sat) on the throne of his father and did not abandon that, not even once. And the name of his wife (was) Ninasir and she was infertile for 30 years. And thereafter they prayed to God and she conceived when (she was) forty and shegave birth to twins.</foreign>
                     </incipit>
                     <explicit>Fol. 90vb: ጸሎቱ፡ ወበረከቱ፡ ለአባ፡ ኪሮስ፡ የሀሉ፡ ምስለ፡ ፍቁሩ፡ ጽጌ፡ ሃይማኖት፡ ወምስለ፡ ዓመቱ፡ አመተ፡ ሥላሴ፡ ምስለ፡ አሞየ፡ ወለተ፡ ክርስቶስ፡ ወምስለ፡ አቡየ፡ ቃለ፡ ክርስቶስ፡ ወምስለ፡ ጸሐፊሁ፡ ኃጥእ፡ ዘወልደ፡ ማርያም፡ ዘአጽሐፎ፡ በተአምኖ፡ ወምስለ፡ ኵልነ፡ ሕዝበ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ ለዓለመ፡ ዓለም፡ አሜን፨፨ ወተመጠዉ᎓እምሥጢራተ᎓ ቅድስት[fol. 91vb]:አባ᎓ ሰሞዖን᎓ ወአባ ባውሚን᎓ ወአባ በብኑዳ… ተፈጸመ፡ በዝየ፡ በሰላመ፡ እግዚአብሔር፡ ገድለ፡ አቡነ፡ ብፁዕ፡ ወክቡር፡ ኪሮስ፡ [fol. 92ra]ስብሐት፡ ለእግዚአብሔር፡ አምላክነ፡ ወለእሌነ[sic]፡ ይኩን፡ ሰህሎ[sic]፡ ወምህረቶ፡ ለዓለመ፡ ዓለም፡ አሜን፨፨ ዘጸሐፎ፡ ወለዘአጽሐፎ፡ ለዘእንበቦ፡ ወለዘተርጐሞ፡ ወለዘሰምዓ፡ ቃላቲሁ፡ በዕዝኒ፡ መንፈስ፡ ወበኅሊና፡ ጽሩይ፡ ኅቡረ፡ ይምሐረነ፡ ለዓለመ፡ ዓለም፡ አሜን፡ ወአሜን፡ ለይኩን፡ ለይኩን፨<foreign xml:lang="en">Fol. 90vb: May the prayer and blessing of father Kiros be with his beloved Ṣǝge Haymanot and with his maid ʾAmätä Śǝllase, with my mother Wälättä Krǝstos and with my father Qalä Krǝstos and with the sinful scribe Zä-Wäldä Maryam, who caused it to be written in faith, and with all Christian people, forever and ever, Amen. And they received from the sacraments (?) [fol. 91vb], (namely) ʾabba Sämʿon, ʾabba Bawmin and ʾabba Bäbnuda... Here it is finished, in peace of God, the Vita of our blessed and honoured father Kiros.[fol. 92ra] Glory (be) to Lord our God. And may His grace and His mercy be upon us forever and ever, Amen. (For) the one who wrote it, and for the one who cause it to be written, (and) for the one who read it and for the one who translated it and the one who listened to its words with ears of spirit and with pure mind, may Him have mercy upon all of us, forever and ever, Amen and Amen, so be it, so be it.</foreign>
                     </explicit>
                     <listBibl type="mss">
                        <bibl>VatLib Comb. 205 (19th/20th cent.), fols. 5r-80r: “Atti di Kiros”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(RaiCombAeth 201-02, no. 205);</bibl>
                        <bibl>BerPrKult orient. Oct. 1288 (17th/18th cent.?), fols. 2ra-31ra:</bibl>
                        <bibl>“Vita des seligen und heiligen Abbā Kiros”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(HamSixBerl 135-36, no. 60);</bibl>
                        <bibl>VatLib Comb. 206 (20th cent.), fols. 4r-93r: “Atti di Kiros”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(RaiCombAeth 202-03, no. 206);</bibl>
                        <bibl>BritLib Orient. 701 (18th cent.), fols. 2a-53a: “The Acts of Cyrus”, fol. 53b-54: “Hymn to Kiros”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(WrBriMus 184ab, no. CCLXXVII);</bibl>
                        <bibl>BerPrKult Ṭānāsee 143 – Dāgā Esṭifānos 32 (16th cent.), fols. 1ra-74vb (?): “Vita des seligen Dilāsor, d.h. Abbā Kiros”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(SixTana III, 165-166, no. 32);</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 3554 (16th/17th cent., Church of Masāqo Śellāsē, Ḥarr Ambā, Ankobarr, Shoa), fols. 1r-38v (EMML IX, 37),</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 319 (19th cent., Private library of Mamrē Baqala, district of Gafarsā, Addis Ababa), fols. 1r-50v (EMML II, 21);</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 2107 (19th cent., Church of Miṭāq Takla Hāymānot, Tagulat and Bulgā, Shoa), I fols. 67r-96v: “Gadla Abbā Kiros”; II fol. 96r-98v: Mälkǝʾa Kiros(EMML VI, 199);</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 2137 (19th cent., Church of Miṭāq Takla Hāymānot, Tagulat and Bulgā, Shoa), fols. 1r-32v (EMML VI, 248);</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 3418 (19th/20th cent., Church of Karrayyo Takla Hāymānot, Gubbālāfto, Yağğu, Wallo), I fols. 51r-65v: “Combat of Abbā Kiros”; II fol. 65v: “Sälam” to the saint (EMML VIII, 252);</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 4683 (19th cent., Private library of Qēs Bakwra, Dabra Berhān, Shoa), fols. 1r-38r (EMML X, 266).</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <note>
                        <p>Marrassini (2004:79-81) refers to this version of the Vita of Kiros as the text of “type 1”, most commonly spread and contained in many Mss. It is different from the Vita of “type 2” which is attested in a few Mss. only (translated and published: B. Turaev, “Kopto-efiopskoe skazanie o prepodobnom Kire”, <i>Zapiski vosto</i>
                           <i>čnago otdelenija I</i>
                           <i>.</i>
                           <i>R</i>
                           <i>.</i>
                           <i>Arhe­ologi</i>
                           <i>českago Obščestva 15, 1903, 1–1</i>4). </p> In addition, Marrassini (2004:83) distinguishes two kinds of type 1 Vita of Kiros: “long” and “short”.The incipit of<ref type="mss" corresp="ESmkl013">MKL-013</ref>is even shorter in comparison to the “short” type of Vita 1, and to the incipit of<ref type="mss" corresp="ESdmd013">DMD-013</ref>.  <p>The explicit of<ref type="mss" corresp="ESmkl013">MKL-013</ref>is nearly identical to that of Ms. Comb. 205 and the last part of the explicit (beginning from: ወተመጠዉ᎓ ምሥጢረ᎓ ቅዱሳት) of Ms. Comb. 206.</p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2">
                     <locus from="92v" to="98r">92v-98r</locus>
                     <title type="Complete">II. Mälkǝʾa Kiros “Image of Kiros” (I)</title>
                     <rubric>Nomina sacra; name of the protagonist; name of the commissioner (fols. 3rb, 70vb, 90vb, 99rb); two initial lines in the incipit page of Texts I and III; word sälam in Text II; selected lines in all the texts (27vb, 105ra, 108va, 117vb); elements of the punctuation signs;  elements of Ethiopic numerals.</rubric>
                     <incipit>Fol. 92vab: ሰላም፡ ለዝክረ፡ ስምከ፡ ኀበ፡ አምደ፡ ወርቅ፡ ዘተጽሕፈ፨ ምስለ፡ ኄራን፡ አበው፡ እንዘ፡ ይከውን፡ ሱቱፈ፨ ጻድቅ፡ ኪሮስ፡ እንዘ፡ ታገኒ፡ አእላፈ፨ አባ፡ ሀበኒ፡ ለወልድከ፡ ውስተ፡ ሰማያት፡ ምዕራፈ፨ ወዘመላእክት፡ አስኬማ፡ ወዓጽፈ፨<foreign xml:lang="en">Fol. 92vab:Salutation to the memorial of your name which is written on the golden column, While it is associated with the good fathers.  O, righteous Kiros, while you are accepting thousands,  (O) Father give me, your son, a repose in the heaven, and the monastic garb and vestment of the angels!</foreign>
                     </incipit>
                     <explicit>Fol. 98vab: እም፡ አመ፡ ንእሰየ፡ አባ፡ እስመ፡ ኪያረሰይኩ፨ ጻድቅ፡ ኪሮስ፡ ለሕይወትየ፡ በሰዓተ፡ ሰርኩ፨ አድኅኒ፡ ወባልሐኒ፡ በጽንዓ፡ እዴከ፡ ዝኩ፨ ቅድመ፡ ይንሥአኒ፡ ለዓለም፡ መልአኩ፨፨ አምላከ፡ ቅዱስ፡ ኪሮስ፡ አድኅነኒ፡ ለገብርከ፡ ጽጌ፡ ሐይማኖት፨<foreign xml:lang="en">Fol. 98vab: (???)  O righteous Kiros, in the hour of my life’s twilight,  Save me and rescue me with your firm hand.  Before the angel (of death) will take me forever.  O God of Saint Kiros, save your servant Ṣǝge Haymanot!</foreign>
                     </explicit>
                     <listBibl type="mss">
                        <bibl>BritLib Orient. 590 (18th cent.), “Hymn to Cyrus (Kīrōs)” WrBriMus 132-133 no. 196</bibl>
                        <bibl>BritLib Orient. 701 (18th cent.), “Hymn to Cyrus (Kīrōs)” WrBriMus 184 no. 277</bibl>
                        <bibl>BritLib Orient. 573 (17th cent.), “Hymn to Cyrus (Kīrōs)”; WrBriMus 126-128 no. 190/48</bibl>
                        <bibl>BritLib Orient. 577 (18th cent. 1721-1730), “Hymn to Cyrus (Kīrōs)” WrBriMus 128-129 no. 191/12</bibl>
                        <bibl>BritLib Orient. 535 (17th cent.), “Hymn to Cyrus (Kīrōs)” WrBriMus 73-75 no. 113/2</bibl>
                        <bibl>Éthiopien 350 (18th cent.) fols. 24vo-27vo: Malkeʽe à Kiros (GrébGriaule II, 58-61, esp. 59, Griaule 46)</bibl>
                        <bibl>Éthiopien 313 (17th cent.) fols. 107ro-113ro, 119vo, 121ro-122ro: Malkeʽe à Kiros (GrébGriaule I, 30-36, esp. 33, Griaule 9)</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <note/>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i3">
                     <locus from="99r" to="126va">99r-126va</locus>
                     <title type="Complete">III. Dǝrsan zä-ʾarbaʿtu ʾǝnsǝsa “Homily on the Four Living Creatures”</title>
                     <rubric>Nomina sacra; name of the protagonist; name of the commissioner (fols. 3rb, 70vb, 90vb, 99rb); two initial lines in the incipit page of Texts I and III; word sälam in Text II; selected lines in all the texts (27vb, 105ra, 108va, 117vb); elements of the punctuation signs;  elements of Ethiopic numerals.</rubric>
                     <incipit>Fol. 99r: በስመ፡”… ድርሳን፡ ዘ፬እንስሳ፡ ክቡራን፡ ዘደረሰ፡ ርቱዓ፡ ሃይማኖት፡ በእንተ፡ ኵሎሙ፡ ነገደ፡ መላእክት፡ ሕያዋነ፡ ሕይወት፡ እለ፡ ተፈጥሩ፡ እምነፋስ፡ ወእሳት፨<foreign xml:lang="en">Fol. 99r: In the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, one God. Homily on the honoured four living creatures written by Rǝtuʿa Haymanot, concerning all orders of angels, the living beings, which were created from air and fire.</foreign>
                     </incipit>
                     <explicit>Fol. 125va: በከመ፡ ነፍስ፡ ውስተ፡ ሥጋነ፡ ከማሁ፡ ሀልዎቱ፨ በአፈ፡ኵሎሙ፡ ሕያዋን፡ ሎቱ፡ ስብሐት፡ ለዓለመ፡ ዓለም፨ አሜን፨ ጸሎቶሙ፡ ወሥዕለቶሙ፡ ወትንብልና፡ ሣህሎሙ፡ ወበረከተ፡ አምላኮሙ፡ የሀሉ[fol. 126ra]፡ ምስለ፡ ፍቁሮሙ፡ ጽጌ፡ ሃይማኖት፡ ለዓለመ ዓለም፨ አሜን፨፨ለዘጸሐፎ፤ ወለዘአጽሐፎ፡ ለዘአንበቦ፡ ወለዘሰምዖ፡ በጥቡዕ፡ ልብ፡ በዕዝነ፡መንፈስ፨ ኅቡረ፡ ይምሐረነ፡ እግዚአብሔር፡ በትንብልናሆሙ፡ ለኪሩባውያን፡ አፍራስ፨ ወበጸሎታ፡ ለእግዚእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ አራቂተ፡ ኵሉ፡ እምባዕሰ፨ ለዓለመ፡ ዓለም፡ አሜን፡ ወአሜን፡ ለይኩን፡ ለይኩን፨ ፨<foreign xml:lang="en">Fol. 125va: As the soul (is) in our body so (there is) existence. In the mouth of all the living ones, glory to Him forever and ever. Amen. May their prayer and their supplication and intercession of their mercy and blessing of their God be with their [fol. 126ra] beloved Ṣǝge Haymanot, forever and ever. Amen. For the one who wrote it, and for the one who caused it be written, (and) for the one who read it and for the one who listened to it with an eager heart and ears of the spirit. May God have mercy upon all of us, for the sake of intercession of the cherubic horses. And for the sake of the prayer of Our Lady Mary, intermediary for all (who is) in conflict. Forever and ever, Amen and Amen, so be it, so be it.</foreign>
                     </explicit>
                     <listBibl type="mss">
                        <bibl>BritLib Orient. 786 (early 19th cent.), fol. 160b, “On the Four Beasts”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(WrBriMus 232a, no. 343/17) (Within the compendium of Homilies by Rǝtuʿa Haymanot);</bibl>
                        <bibl>BerPrKult Ṭānāsee 142 – Dāgā Esṭifānos 31 (15th cent.?), fols. 119rb-124vb</bibl>
                        <bibl>(SixTana III 162, no. 31) (Within the compendium of Homilies by Rǝtuʿa Haymanot);</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 2375 (18th cent.), fols. 122r-127v, “On the angels”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(EMML VI, 457) (Within the compendium of Homilies by Rǝtuʿa Haymanot);</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 2584 (18th cent., Church of Masḉā Māryām, Harr Ambā, Showa), fols. 110b-117a, “On the angels”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(EMML VII, 38) (Within the compendium of Homilies by Rǝtuʿa Haymanot).</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 3516 (19th cent.), fol. 3r, “On the angels”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(EMML IX, 13) (With “Dǝrsanä Mikaʾel” and other texts);</bibl>
                        <bibl>EMML no. 4800 (18th cent., Church of Däse Mädḫane ʿAläm, Däse, Wällo), fol. 92v-98v, “Homily by Rǝtuʿa Haymanot Yohannes on the form [mälkǝʾ] of God and on the Four Living Creatures and all the angels”</bibl>
                        <bibl>(EMML X, 318) (With “Dǝrsanä Mikaʾel” and other texts).</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <note>
                        <p>The church possesses the tabot of the Four Living Creatures. Perhaps the text was copied and included into the Ms. on the occasion of introduction of the (new) tabot into the church.</p> 
                        <p>The present Homily is in fact a part of a homiliary entitled Dǝrsan zä-ʾarbaʿtu ʾǝnsǝsa or Dǝrsanä ʾarbaʿtu ʾǝnsǝsa, being in the portion read on 8 Ḫǝdar, the feast of the Four Living Creatures (cp. Ms.<ref type="mss" corresp="ESrqm001">RQM-001</ref>). This can possibly explain inclusion of the words  "zä-ʾarbaʿtu ʾǝnsǝsa" into the incipit; however the Homily itself rather deals with Angels than with the Four Living Creatures (hence the title "On the Angels" in EMML 2584 and elsewhere). In the catalogues, unless the incipit is provided, the Homily is not always identifiable. Cp. also such Mss. as: BN d'Abbadie 54 (15th cent.), fol. 66r five leaves, “Homélie de Jean (Chrysostome), évêque de Constantinople, sur les Quatre animaux célestes” (CRAbb 181, no. 169/3) (Appended to the “Vita of ʾabba Nob”); BN d'Abbadie 80 (15th/16th cent.), fol. 133r five leaves, “Sur les quatre bêtes de l’Apocalypse” (CRAbb 155, no. 133) (Within the compendium of homilies by Rǝtuʿa Haymanot); BN d'Abbadie 92 (15th/16th cent.), fol. 67r  five leaves, “Traité sur les quatre bêtes (de l’Apocalypse) “Homélie de Jean, patriarche de Constantinople, sur les quatre bêtes de l’Apocalypse” (CRAbb 150, no. 129/5) (Appended to the Mäṣḥafä Ḫǝdar); BN 123 (18th/19th cent.), fol. 140r 22 leaves, “Homélie de Jean Chrysostome sur les quatre animaux célestes” (CRAbb 186, no. 175/8) (Appended to the “Vita of ʾAbib”). </p> 
                        <p>The text is probably different from the Homily in honor of the Four Living Creatures in the collection "Homilies in Honor of Angels", EMML nos. 1835 (5) and 1841 (5).</p> 
                        <p/>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>Made of <measure unit="leaf">128.0</measure> folios, of which
                                                  <measure unit="leaf" type="blank"/> blank
                                                  2v, 127v, 128rv, in
                                                  <measure unit="quire">14.0</measure> quires (A+13). 
                                                <dimensions type="outer">
                              <height unit="cm">11.5</height>
                              <width unit="cm">10.0</width>
                              <depth unit="cm">6.0</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation/>
                        <collation>
                           <list>
                              <item xml:id="q1">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">2</dim>
                                 <locus from="1r" to="2v"/>&lt;A(2/fols. 1r-2v)&gt; </item>
                              <item xml:id="q2">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="3r" to="12v"/> I(10/fols. 3r-12v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q3">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="13r" to="22v"/> II(10/fols. 13r-22v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q4">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="23r" to="32v"/> III(10/fols. 23r-32v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q5">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="33r" to="42v"/> IV(10/fols. 33r-42v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q6">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="43r" to="52v"/> V(10/fols. 43r-52v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q7">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="53r" to="62v"/> VI(10/fols. 53r-62v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q8">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="63r" to="72v"/> VII(10/fols. 63r-72v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q9">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="73r" to="82v"/> VIII(10/fols. 73r-82v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q10">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="83r" to="92v"/> IX (10/fols. 83r-92v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q11">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="93r" to="100v"/> &lt;X(8/fols. 93r-100v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q12">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="101r" to="108v"/> XI(8/fols. 101r-108v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q13">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="109r" to="117v"/> XII(8/fols. 109r-117v) </item>
                              <item xml:id="q14">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus target="10"/>
                                 <locus from="118r" to="128v"/> XIII(10/fols. 118r-128v)&gt;.&#xD;
&#xD;
Perhaps the codex was originally composed of quires I-IX (Texts I-II); quires A and X-XIII (Text III) were added to it later, but still during the life time of Ṣǝge Haymanot, the original commissioner of the Ms.</item>
                           </list>
                        </collation>
                        <condition key="good">Originally, one pair of sewing stations was employed for holding together all quires of the Ms. Probably in the modern time, an (unskilled) binder loosened the first three quires and bound them again with nylon threads (?), using two holes in the centre fold of the quires, originally meant for tiedowns of the endbands, as the sewing stations. In the same way, he unsuccessfully tried to resew quires X-XIII.&#xD;
Holes are carefully amended on fols. 67, 86, 95.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="14">
                           <dimensions unit="mm">
                              <height>72</height>
                              <width>74</width>
                              <dim type="intercolumn">10</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="margin">
                              <dim type="top">80</dim>
                              <dim type="bottom">32</dim>
                              <dim type="right">13</dim>
                              <dim type="left">10</dim>
                              <dim type="intercolumn">10</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note/>
                           <ab type="ruling"/>
                           <ab type="pricking">Ruling and pricking are mostly visible.</ab>
                           <ab type="ruling" subtype="pattern">
Ruling pattern: 1A-1A-1A1A/0-0/0-0/C.</ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">
Primary pricks are visible.</ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">
Ruling pricks are visible.</ab>
                           <ab type="ruling">
The upper line is written above the ruling.</ab>
                           <ab type="ruling">
The bottom line is written above the ruling.</ab>
                        </layout>
                        <layout>
                           <ab type="punctuation" subtype="Executed">regularly;</ab>
                           <ab type="punctuation" subtype="Usage">not always logical;</ab>
                           <ab type="punctuation">
                              <list>
                                 <item xml:id="div1">
Dividers:</item>
                                 <item xml:id="div2">
I. Colon;</item>
                                 <item xml:id="div3">
colon of two black dots and three red dashes (in-between, above, below) (e.g., 44ra, 55va, 59va);</item>
                                 <item xml:id="div4">
colon with dashes above and below (esp. in the text by hand b, e.g., fols. 99rab,102vb, 104ra, 104vab, 107rab,109ra, 111rab, 111vab, 113vb, 114rb);</item>
                                 <item xml:id="div5">
three dot vertical colon (e.g., fols. 4ra, 6rab, 10va, 16vb, 38vb, 66va);</item>
                                 <item xml:id="div6">
II. Nine dot asterisk (used throughout the Ms.);</item>
                                 <item xml:id="div7">
two nine dot asterisks (fol. 92ra, 98rb).</item>
                                 <item xml:id="div8">
III. A chain of three nine dot asterisks connected by means of two black lines and one red line (fol. 91vb);</item>
                                 <item xml:id="div9">
three nine dot asterisks between two chains of black and red dots (fols. 92ra, 126va). </item>
                                 <item xml:id="div10">
a chain of black and red dots (fols. 98rb).   </item>
                                 <item xml:id="div11">
two nine dot asterisks connected by means of two black lines with one thick red line in between (fol. 117vb, 126ra).</item>
                              </list>
                           </ab>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><!--ACHTUNG! first HandNote comes from writing system in Ethiospare. the others are one for each CHANGE OF HAND-->
                     <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                        <ab type="script">Hand a: mediocre; hand b: mediocre</ab>
                        <seg type="ink">Black, red</seg>
                        <persName role="scribe" corresp="PRS00000">Zä-Wäldä Maryam</persName>Zä-Wäldä Maryam is the scribe of Texts I and II. His name is written in the concluding supplication on fol. 91ra.<date>First half of the 18th century</date>
                     </handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h2" script="Ethiopic">Hand a: quires I-IX (Zä-Wäldä Maryam): a bit less careful, somewhat deteriorating to the end of the Ms.<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h3" script="Ethiopic">
Hand b: quires A, X-XIII (looking similar to hand a; it can not be excluded that the scribe was the same person).<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <additions><!--THIS element in domlib CONTAINS ESCAPED HTML, thus it is not possible to reliably extract the information about pages. Please watch out.-->
                     <list>
                        <item xml:id="a1">
                           <locus target="#1va">Fol. 1va</locus>: Mǝlṭan-antiphon for the Righteous.   <q xml:lang="gez">Fol. 1va-b: ምልጣን፡ ዘጻድቃን <b>× </b>ምቶሙሰ፡[sic] ለጻድቃን፡ ሕይወቶሙ፡ ውእቱ፡ እስመ፡ ለጻድቅ፡ ይትሌዓል፡ ቀርኑ፡ በክብር <b>×</b> ጻድቃን፡ እለ፡ አስመርዎ፡ ለእግዚኦሙ፡ ምድረ፡ ብርህተ፡ ወጽዕዱተ፡ ይወርሱ <b>×</b>
                           </q>
                           <q xml:lang="en">Fol.1vab: Antiphon for the Righteous.  The death of the righteous is their life.  Since " the horh of a righteous shall be exalted with honour” (cp. Ps. 112:9). God has delight in the righteous,  They will inherit the earth of light and whiteness (Mt. 5:5).</q>
                           
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a2">
                           <locus target="#98va">Fol. 98va</locus>: Mǝlṭan-antiphon for Kiros.   <q xml:lang="gez">Fol. 98va: ምልጣን፡፡ አባ፡ አቡነ፡ አቡነ፡ ወመምህርነ፡ እምአዕላፍ፡ ኅሩይ፤ ሐውጽ፡ እምሰማይ፡ ብርሃንከ፡ ከመ፡ ንርአይ፡ አማን፡ አቡነ፡ ኪሮስ፡ ፀሕይ፡፡</q>
                           <q xml:lang="en">Fol.: 98va: ʾAbba, our father, our father and our teacher,  Chosen from thousands.  Visit (us) from the heaven  So that we might see your light, (Since) verily, our father Kiros (is) the sun.</q>
                           The antiphon for the day (8 Ḫǝdar) is taken from Dǝggwa (cp., e.g., DZ-009, fol. 20va, Zä-ṣadǝqan "Of the Righteous Ones").
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e1">- Numerous corrections written interlineally: e.g., fols. 21vab, 28rab, 48rb, 68vb.&#xD;
- Numerous erasures: e.g., fols. 48va, 49ra, 53ra.&#xD;
- Writing exercises: fol. 1r.</item>
                     </list>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding contemporary="partly">
                        <decoNote xml:id="b1">Two wooden boards covered with reddish-brown tooled leather.&#xD;
One pair of sewing stations.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b2" type="bindingMaterial">
                           <material key="leather"/>
                           <material key="wood"/>
                        </decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b3" type="Endbands"/>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b4" type="Other">Two pairs of chains of endband stitches at the spine cover.</decoNote>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <placeName corresp="INS0123MKL">Läqay Kidanä Mǝḥrät / MKL</placeName>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate notBefore="1700" notAfter="1750">The Ms. was written by Zä-Wäldä Maryam who was active in the first half of the 18th cent. (s. the colophon of Ms. QSM-007 fol. 217rb.)</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <listBibl type="catalogue">
                              <bibl/>
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <custodialHist>
                        <custEvent type="restorations" subtype="modern"/>
                     </custodialHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates>
                     <bibl/>
                  </surrogates>
                  <listBibl type="secondary">
                     <bibl>Ms. previously unknown.</bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Encoded according to TEI P5 Guidelines.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person>
                  <persName role="owner" corresp="PRS0000">Ṣǝge Haymanot is mentioned on fols. 90vb and 126ra. Other members of his family: his father Qalä Krǝstos, his mother Wälättä Krǝstos and his sister ʾAmätä Śǝllase are mentioned on fols. 90vb-91ra.&#xD;
The same family donated Ms. MKL-010.</persName>
                  <!--ACHTUNG! This is actually paragraphic information identifying the donor. 
                                        Person/persName should only contain the person name, not all the paragraph.-->
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName role="scribe" corresp="PRS00000">Zä-Wäldä Maryam</persName>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName corresp="PRS00000"/>
                  <!--other-->
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term key="Hagiography"/>
               <term key="Homily"/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Inglese</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez" xml:id="Lan05">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="DN" when="2011-08-08">created</change>
         <change who="DN" when="2015-03-08">last edited</change>
         <change who="PL" when="2016-05-10">transformed from mycore to TEI
                            P5</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
