<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP00943">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Mekele Mikael 166</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Mekele Mikael </repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/943/">Mekele Mikael 166</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Qerǝllos, ቄርሎስ:, Theological and Christological Works of Cyril of Alexandria and other church fathers, cf. EMML 4448.Ff. i r(ecto)-v(recto): Excerpt from the Synaxarium on the life of Cyril. F<locus target="#1r"/>–46v: On the Orthodox Faith (De recta fide), Bä’ntä Haymanot Rǝt‘ǝt, addressed to Emperor Theodosius. Bernd Manuel Weischer, Qerellos I (= Afrikanische Forschungen 7) Hamburg 1973. F<locus target="#47r"/>–xxx: That Christ is One, Kama aḥadu Krestos, by Cyril of Alexandria. Bernd Manuel Weischer, Qerellos III: Der Dialog “Dass Christus einer ist” des Kyrillos von Alexandrien (Äthiopistiche Forschungen, Vol. 2) Wiesbaden 1977. F<locus target="#71v"/>-73r: Homily by Theodotus of Ancyra, Weicher,  ibid. 122–33 F<locus target="#73r"/>-73v: Homily by Severus of Synnada, Weischer,  ibid. 62–7. F<locus target="#73v"/>–74v: Homily by Acacius of Melitene, Weischer,  ibid. 68–81. F<locus target="#74v"/>-75v: Homily by Juvenalius of Jerusalem, Weischer,  ibid. 82–7. F<locus target="#75v"/>-76v: Homily by Cyril of Alexandria, Weicher,  ibid. 88–99. F<locus target="#76v"/>-77r: Homily by Rheginus of Constantinople, Weicher,  ibid. 100–7. F<locus target="#77r"/>-78r: Homily by Cyril of Alexandria, Weicher,  ibid. 108–17. F<locus target="#78rv"/>: Homily by Eusiebius of Heraclea, Weicher,  ibid. 117–21. F<locus target="#78v"/>-79v: Homily by Theodotus of Ancyra, Weicher,  ibid. 122–33. F<locus target="#79v"/>: Homily by Firmus of Caesarea, Weicher,  ibid. 134–137. F<locus target="#79v"/>-80r: Epistle of the Synod of Ephesus to John of Antioch, Weicher, ibid. 138–141. F<locus target="#80r"/>: Homily by Cyril of Alexandria, Weicher, ibid. 142–145. F<locus target="#80r"/>-81r: Epistle of John of Antioch to Cyril of Alexandria, Weicher,  ibid. 146–153. F<locus target="#81r"/>-82v: Epistle of Cyril of Alexandria to John of Antioch, Weicher,  ibid. 153–169. F<locus target="#82v"/>-84v: Homily by Epiphanius of Cyprus. Bernd Manuel Weischer, Qerellos IV 2: Traktate des Epiphanius von Zypern und des Proklos von Kyzikos. AF 6 (Wiesbaden, 1979) 24–47.  F<locus target="#84v"/>-85r: Homily by Epiphanius of Cyprus on the Trinity, Weicher, ibid. 52–58. F<locus target="#85r"/>-87r: Homily by Proclus of Cyzicus, Weicher, ibid. 64–87. F<locus target="#87r"/>-90v: Homily by Severianus of Gabala. Bernd Manuel Weischer, Qerellos IV 3: Traktate des Severianos Von Gabala, Gregorios Thaumaturgus und Kyrillos von Alexandrien. AF 7 (Wiesbaden, 1980) 22–67. F<locus target="#90v"/>-91r: The Faith of Gregory Thaumaturgus, Weischer, ibid. 70–77. F<locus target="#91r"/>-92v: The first homily of Cyril of Alexandria on Melchisedec, Weischer, ibid. 82–97.  F<locus target="#92v"/>-94r: The second homily of Cyril of Alexandria on Melchisedec, Weischer, ibid. 98–117. F<locus target="#94rv"/>: Homily by a Sage on Melchisedec. Bernd Manuel Weischer, “Die äthiopischen Psalmen- und Qerlosfragmente in Evevan/Armenien,” Oreiens Christianus 53 (1969) 142–143. F<locus target="#94v"/>: On the 318 Orthodox Fathers, Weischer, ibid. 143–144. F<locus target="#94v"/>-95r: On the Nativity and Life of Our Lord, Weischer, ibid. 144–145. F<locus target="#95rv"/>: Confession of faith, Weischer, ibid, 146. F<locus target="#95v"/>-96r: Closing prayer, mentioning the owner, but erased. Closing scribal note mentioning the day the book was started (the 12th night of Ṭərr) and completed on a Friday in Mäggabit.</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf">v + 96</measure>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height>260</height>
                              <width>240</width>
                              <depth>60</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate when="1750">seventeenth century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
