<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP00339">
   <teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Weiner Codex 149</title>
            <editor key="ABe"></editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Weiner</repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/339/">Weiner Codex 149</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Four Gospels of Empress Zäwditu; </summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1"><locus from="1r" to="51r"/><title type="complete" ref="LIT1558Matthew"/>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <incipit xml:lang="gez">ብሥራተ: አብ: ትሩፍ: ማቴዎስ: ሐዋርያ: ፩እም፲ወ፪ቱ: ሐዋርያት: በረከተ: አምላኩ: ውድስት። ወሀብተ: ጸሎቱ: ውክፍት: ተሀሉ: ምስለ: ንግሥትነ: አስካለ: ማርያም: ወምስለ: ፍቁራ: ወራሴ: መንግሥት: ኃይለ: ሥላሴ: ለዓለመ: ዓለም: አሜን።</incipit>
                <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.1"><locus from="51r" to="51r"/>
                <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                <title>Conclusion (<foreign xml:lang="gez">መልዓ</foreign>:) of the Gospel of Matthew</title>
                <incipit xml:lang="gez">መልዓ; ብሥራተ: ማቴዎስ: ሐዋርያ: ወኮነ: ጸሐፎ: በምድረ: ፍልስጥዔም: በአስተሐምሞ: ቅዱስ: እብራይስጣዊ: እምድኅረ: ዕርገቱ: ለእግዚእነ: ኢየሱስ ክርስቶስ: በአጶርግዮ: ለኀበ: ሰማይ: በሰማኒቱ: ዓመታት: በቀዳሚሁ: አም: ዘእምቀላውዴዎስ: ቄሣር: ንጉሠ: ሮም: ወስብሐት: ለእግዚአብሔር: ለዓለመ: ዓለም። አሜን።</incipit>
                <note>Translation: This concludes the gospel of Mathew, the Disciple. He wrote in the land of Palestine with holy care in Hebrew eight years after the ascencion of Our Lord Jesus Christ in flesh into heaven, and the first year of Caesar Claudius, King of Rome. And glory to God forever and ever. Amen</note>
                </msItem>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2"><locus from="52r" to="84r"/><title type="complete" ref="LIT1882MarkGo"/>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <incipit xml:lang="gez">ብሥራተ: አብ: ሐዋርያ: ማርሪ(?): ማርቆስ: ወንጌላዊ: ፩ደ: እም፸: ወ፪ አርድዕት: በረከቱ: ወአስተብ[ቍ]ዖቱ: ተሀሉ: ምስለ:....</incipit>
                <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.1"><locus from="84r" to="84r"/>
                <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                <title>Conclusion of the Gospel of Mark</title>
                <incipit xml:lang="gez">መልዓ ጽሕፈተ: ብስራቱ: ለማርቆስ: ፩እም፸ወ፪: አርድእት: ወኮነ: ጸሐፎ: በልሳነ: ሮሜ: ዘአፍርንጊ: እምድኅረ: ዕርገቱ: ለእግዚእነ: በሥጋ። ውስተ ሰማይ: በ፲ወ፩: ዓመት: በራብዒት: ዓመቱ: ለቀላውዴዎስ: ቄሣር: ንጉሠ: ሮም: ወስብሐት: ለእግዚአብሔር: ለዓለመ: ዓለም: አሜን።</incipit>
                <note>Translation: This concludes the writing of the Gospel of Mark, one of the Seventy Two disciples. He wrote in the language of Rome [Latin] of France, eleven years after the ascencion of our Lord in the flesh into heaven, in the fourth year of Ceasar Claudius, King of Rome. And Glory to God forever and ever. Amen</note>
              </msItem>
            </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i3"><locus from="85r" to="148r"/><title type="complete" ref="LIT1812GospelLuke"/>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <incipit xml:lang="gez">ብስራተ: ሉቃስ: ረድእ: ፩እም፸ወ፪: አርድእት: ጸሎቱ: ወበረከቱ: የሃሉ: ምስለ: ንግሥትነ: አስካለ: ማርያም: ለዓ: ዓለም:..</incipit>
                  <note>See below for the conclusion</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i4"><locus from="149r" to="201r"/><title type="complete" ref="LIT1693John"/>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <incipit xml:lang="gez">ብስራተ: አብ: ትሩፍ: ረድእ: ተናጋሪ: በመለኮት: ዮሐንስ: ወልደ: ዘብዴዎስ: ፍቁረ: እግዚእነ: ኢየሱስ: ክርስቶስ: ጸሎቱ: ወበረከቱ: የሃሉ: ምስለ: ንግሥትነ። ። ። አስካለ: ማርያም: ወምስለ: እግዚእነ: ኃይለ: ሥላሴ: ለዓ: ዓለ:</incipit>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i4.1"><locus from="200v" to="200v"/>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <title>Conclusion of the Gospel of John</title>
                  <incipit xml:lang="gez">መልዓ: ጽሕፈተ: ብስራቱ: ለዮሐንስ: ሐዋርያ: ፩:እም፲ወ፪: ሐዋርያት: ዘጸሐፎ: በዮናኒ: ለሰብአ: ሀገረ: ኤፌሶን: እምድኅረ: ዕርገቱ: ለኢየሱስ: ክርስቶስ: በሥጋ: ውስተ: ሰማይ: በ፴ዓመት: ወበ፰: ዓመተ: መንግሥቱ: ለኔሮን: ንጉሠ: ሮም: ወስብሐት: ለእግዚአብሔር: ለዓለመ: ዓለም: አሜን።</incipit>
                  <note>Translation: This concludes the gospel of John, the Disciple, one of of the Twelve, which he wrote in Greek to the people of the city of Ephesus, after the ascencion of Our Lord Jesus Christ, in the flesh, into heaven, in the thirty-eighth year of the reign of Nero, King of Rome. And glory to God forever and ever. Amen</note>
                  </msItem>
                </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf">i + 201</measure>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height>140</height>
                              <width>92</width>
                              <depth>45</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                  <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                  <seg type="rubrication">
                  <foreign xml:lang="gez">ማርያም፡</foreign>
                  <foreign xml:lang="gez">ኢየሱስ፡</foreign>
                  </seg>
                  <desc>The words Mary and Jesus are rubricated</desc>
                  </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                  <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d1"><locus target="#iv(erso)"/><desc><ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1025NativityJesus"/></desc></decoNote>
                  <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d2"><locus target="#51v"/><desc> The Praise of the <ref type="authFile" corresp ="AT1047Apostles"/></desc></decoNote>
                  <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d3"><locus target="#84v"/><desc><ref type="authFile" corresp ="AT1035HolyMan"/> <persName ref="PRS10691Zechari"/>, Father of <persName ref="PRS3725Elizabet"/></desc></decoNote>
                  <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d4"><locus target="#148v"/><desc><ref type="authFile" corresp ="AT1035HolyMan"/> Portrait of Saint <persName ref="PRS5695John"/> and his vision of <persName ref="PRS5684JesusCh"/>, the Logos</desc></decoNote>
                  <decoNote type="frame" xml:id="d5">
                  Decorative designs:
                  <locus target="#13r"/> (lines of black dots); multiple full stops used as section dividers throughout
                  </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <list>
                    <item xml:id="e1">
                    <locus target="#ir(ecto) #201v"/>
                    <desc>
                    blank
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e2">
                    <locus target="#84r"> f. 84r, column two, lower</locus>
                    <desc>
                    Two seals, illigible
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a1">
                    <locus target="#148r"/>
                    <desc type="GuestText">
                    Conclusion of the <title type="complete" ref="LIT1812GospelLuke"/> and Colophon:
                    Text: <foreign xml:lang="gez">መልዓ: ጽሕፈተ: ብስራት: ለሉቃስ: ፩እም፸ወ፪: አርድእት፡ ዘጸሐፈ: በልሳነ: ዮናኒ: እምድኅረ: ዕርገቱ: ለእግዚእነ: ኢየሱስ: ክርስቶስ: ወበዓመተ: መንግሥቱ: ለቀላውዴዎስ: በ፲ወ፩: ወስብሐት: ለእግዚአብሔር: ለዓለመ: ዓለም: አሜን። ዝንቱ: መጽሐፍ: ዘንግሥተ: ነገሥታት: ዘውዲቱ: ዘስመ: ጥምቀታ: አስካለ: ማርያም: ዘወሀበቶ: ለገሊላ: ቅዱስ: ገብርኤል: ዘሀገረ: ቶበር: ከመ: ይኩና: ለሥርየተ: ኃጢአት: ወመርሐ: ለመንግሥተ: ሰማያት: በጸሎቱ: ለቅዱስ: ገብርኤል: ሊቀ: መላእክት: ወበስእለታ: ለእግዝእትነ: ማርያም: ሰአሊተ: ምሕረት: ለዓለመ: ዓለም: አሜን።</foreign>
                    Translation: This concludes the gospel of Luke, of the Seventy Two, which he wrote in Greek after the ascencion of Our Lord Jesus Christ, and in the eleventh year of the reign of Claudius. Glory to God forever and ever. Amen. This book belongs to Queen of Queens, Zäwditu, whose baptismal name is Askalä Maryam. She gave it to Saint Gabriel church of Gälila, of the city of Tobär, to acquire forgiveness of sins (for her) and to be a guide to the kingdom of heaven through the prayer of Saint Gabriel, the archangel, with the intercession of Our Lady Mary, the Intercessor of Mercy, forever and ever, Amen.”
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e3">
                    <locus target="#199r"/>
                    <desc>
                    A seal, reading around the outside, “Aläqa [parish administrator] Wolde Täklä Haymanot of Däbrä Libanos.” On the horizontal and vertical cross pieces in the center it reads, “According to Your Mercy (horizontal), O our Lord (vertical).” This is an allusion to the liturgical phrase, “According to your mercy, O our Lord; and not according to our transgressions.” See the Book of <title type="complete" ref="LIT1960Mashaf"/>, in the Anapora of the Apostles: <foreign xml:lang="gez">መጽሐፈ፡ ቅዳሴ። በግዕዝና፡ በአማርኛ።</foreign> = Mäṣḥäfä Qəddase. Bä-Gə‘əzənna bä-Amarəñña (Addis Ababa: Täsfa, 1951 EC) 49, no. 62
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a2">
                    <locus target="#201r"/>
                    <desc>
                    Colophon:
                    Text: <foreign xml:lang="gez">ዝንቱ: መጽሐፍ: ዘንግሥተ: ነገሥታት: ዘውዲቱ: ዘስመ: ጥምቀታ: አስካለ: ማርያም: ወለቱ: ለዳግማዊ: ምኒልክ: ንጉሠ: ነገሥት: ዘኢትዮጵያ: ወተጽሕፎቱሰ: በ፲ወ፱፻፲ወ፩: ዓመተ: ምሕረት: እምአመ: አዕረፈ: ዳግማዊ: ምኒልክ: ንጉሠ: ነገሥት: በ፲ወ፬: ዓመት: ወእምአመ: ነግሠት: ንግሥተ፡ ነገሥታት፡ ዘውዲቱ: በ፲ወ፩ ዓመት እንዘ: እግዚእነ: ልዑል: ተፈሪ: መኰንን: ዘስመ: ጥምቀቱ: ኃይለ: ሥላሴ: ወራሴ: መንግሥት: ወእንዘ: ጳጳስነ: ማቴዎስ: ርቱዓ: ሃይማኖት: ወእንዘ: መምህርነ: እጨጌ: ገብረ: መንፈስ: ቅዱስ: ዘነበረ: በመንበረ: ተክለ: ሃይማኖት: ብርሃነ: ዓለም: ወዘአጽሐፎ: መልአከ: ሰላም: ወልደ: መስቀል: ዘውእቱ: ጸሐፌ: ትእዛዝ: ወስመ: ጸሐፊሁ: ገብረ: ማርያም: ወስብሐት: ለእግዚአብሔር: ለዘአብጽሐነ: እስከ: ዛቲ: ሰዓት: ወለወላዲቱ: ቅድስት: ማርያም: ወላዕሌነ: ይኩን: ሣህል: ወምሕረት: ለዓለመ: ዓለም: አሜን። ።</foreign>
                    Translation: “This book belongs to Queen of Queens, Zäwditu, whose baptismal name is Askalä Maryam, daughter of Menelik II, King of Kings of Ethiopia. It is written on 1911 E.C. (= 1918/19) fourteen years after the death of Menelik II, King of Kings, and in the 11th year of the reign of queen of queens, Zäwditu, when our Lord, Tafari Makonnen, whose baptismal name is Ḫaylä Śǝllase, was regent of the throne, when Matewos, the Orthodox, was our bishop [1843–1926] and when our teacher Eččäge Gäbrä Mänfäs Qǝddus sits on the throne of Täklä Hayamont, Light of the World; commissioned by Mälǝ’akä Sälam Wäldä Mäsqäl, who is Minister of Pen; the name of the scribe is Gäbrä Maryam. Glory to God, to the one who brought us to this hour and to his Mother, Saint Mary. Let forgiveness and mercy be upon us for ever and ever, Amen.
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e4">
                    <locus target="#201r"/>
                    <desc>
                    Two seals. The smaller of the two on the left reads around the circumference: “Mälǝ’akä Sälam, Woldä Mäsqäl who is Minister of Pen,” and underneath it reads, “Let the Hearer Hear,” an allusion to the comment made by the reader just after the conclusion of the reading the <title type="complete" ref="LIT1882MarkGo"/>. The larger of the two, on the right, reads, “Conquering Lion of the Tribe of Judah, Queen of Queens of Ethiopia, Zäwditu, daughter of Mǝnilǝk.”
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e5">
                    <locus target="#52 #149"/>
                    <desc>
                    blue yarn is sewn into the top edge to mark content as navigation system
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e6">
                    <desc>
                    Numbered quires: quires 10–18 and 20
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e7">
                    <locus target="#7v #15r #18r #20r #29v"/>
                    <desc>
                    (etc.) words of text are written interlinearly
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                  </list>
                </additions>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate when="1918">1911 E.C. (= 1918/19 C.E., f. 201r)</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                     href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
                                    <change when="2019-10-03" who="ABe">Added items</change>
                                    <change when="2020-01-16" who="ABe">Added items</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
