<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP00154">
   <teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Weiner Codex 49</title>
            <editor key="JS"/>
            <editor key="RL"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Weiner</repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/154/">Weiner Codex 49</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Vision of John, Son of Thunder, on the Dual Virginity of Mary; Forty-Nine Miracles of Mary, ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡, Eight Miracles of Jesus, ተአምረ፡ ኢየሱስ፡</summary>
                     <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1"><locus from="1r" to="5r"/><textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <title>Vision of John, Son of Thunder, on the Dual Virginity of Mary. For a critical edition and English translation, see Getatchew Haile</title>
                  <incipit xml:lang="gez">
                    በስመ፡ አብ፡ ወወልድ፡... ዝንቱ፡ መጽሐፍ፡ ዘይትነበብ፡ እምቅድመ፡ ያንብቡ፡ ተአምሪሃ፡ ለእግዝእትነ፡ ቅድስት፡ ድንግል፡ በክልኤ፡ ማርያም፡ ዘተናገረ፡ ፩፡ ኃጥእ፡ በዘይተ፡ ፍቅራ፡ ለማርያም፡ ውጉዕ፡ ረዓየ፡ ተአምር፡ ዮሐንስ፡ ወልደ፡ ነጐድጓድ፡ ዘርእየ፡ ተአምሪሃ፡ ለማርያም፡ ዘርእየ፡ ተአምረ፡ ዐቢየ፡...
                  </incipit>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2"><locus from="5r" to="46v"/><textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang><title type="complete" ref="LIT2384Taamme"/>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.1"><locus from="5r" to="8r"/><title>Introductory Rite from Mu‘älläqa.</title></msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2"><locus from="8r" to="46v"/><title>Forty-Nine Miracles of Mary</title>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.1"><locus from="8r" to="8v"/><title>How Joachim and Hannah were praying and she conceived the Virgin Mary; how the blind daughter of Arǝsaban was healed when she touched the womb of Hannah; and how the Jews tried to stone Joachim and Hannah and how the archangel Gabriel protected them and led them to Mount Lebanon.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.2"><locus from="8v" to="9r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary descended from the seed of the fathers of the Old Testament; how Joachim saw a white bird coming from the seventh heaven; how Hannah dreamed of a dove descending on her head; and how the Virgin Mary was conceived on the seventh of Näḥase.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.3"><locus from="9r" to="9v"/><title>How God commanded Saint Gabriel to go to the Virgin Mary, descendant of David; how God commanded him to go in peace; and how Gabriel came to Mary and greeted her on Sunday in the third hour when she was spinning silk for the Temple (cf. Princeton MS 37, ff. 67r–68v; Princeton MS 41, ff. 15v–17r). </title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.4"><locus from="9v" to="10r"/><title>How Hanna, the mother of the Virgin Mary, went to the funeral of Samrǝs, son of Ṭaliq, in Jericho and how, when she was weeping and holding his body, he awoke and praised her saying, “Greetings to you, O Mother of the sun of righteousness” (TM61 149–50; MYS 1, ff. 181v–182r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.5"><locus from="10r" to="10v"/><title>The anunciation of the archangel Gabriel to the Virgin Mary. </title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.6"><locus from="10v" to="12r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary was living in the temple; how the archpriest and the Levites cast lots and the lots fell to Joseph and how he took her to his home; how after seven months her pregnancy became known; and how the angel of God told Joseph to keep Mary as his fience; how the Jews gave her testing waters (i.e., “bitter water,” water mixed with dust from the temple floor [Numbers 5:17ff]), which she drank, but nothing happened.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.7"><locus from="12r" to="12v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave birth in Bethlehem of Judea; how she named her son Emmanuel; how the angels praised God saying, “Glory to God in the highest;” how the angel told the shepherds about the birth of Jesus Christ; how the wise men came, enquired about the birth of the king of Israel; and how they found the child, worshipped him and gave him their gifts.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.8"><locus from="12v" to="13v"/><title>How Joseph and Mary circumcised the child and the archangels descended and praised him; how their praise was heard as far as Babylon, Naphtali, Persia and Mount Lebanon; how Herod knew of the birth of the king of Israel and how he became jealous and commanded his army to kill all the children.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.9"><locus from="13v" to="14r"/><title>How Herod commanded his army to find the baby Jesus and his mother Mary; how a hunter in a certain city found Mary and how the hunter’s dogs licked her feet; and how the Virgin Mary blessed the hunter.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.10"><locus from="14r" to="15r"/><title>How the hunter who found the Virgin Mary went to a certain king, Dämatǝyanos, and told him about Mary; how he led the king’s army to her and how he became a pillar of salt; how she sent a message to king Dämatǝyanos; how he came to her and asked her to come to his country; how he interceeded for the man who had turned into a pillar of salt and how he became alive again.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.11"><locus from="15r" to="16r"/><title>How the archangel Gabriel told Mary to go to Bethlehem, then Egypt, according to prophecy; and how the Virgin Mary blessed King Dämatǝyanos and his country.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.12"><locus from="16r" to="17v"/><title>How the angel of God came to Joseph in a dream and told him to take the child and his mother to Egypt; how Herod surrounded Bethlehem and killed the children; how the archangel Gabriel led Mary to Mount Lebanon and how she lived there for three months; how the angel took her soul to heaven; and how she saw many righteous kings and saints there who praised her (a portion of this story is covered by the added illumination on f. 16v)</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.13"><locus from="17v" to="18v"/><title>How the angel of God told the wise men about the birth of Jesus Christ; how they asked Herod about the birth of a king; how they found the child and how the angel of God commanded them to return by a different route without telling Herod; how Herod killed the children of Bethlehem; how the Virgin Mary went to the Sea of Tiberias to King Kefaz; how Kefaz hid Mary and her child; how Herod found out about this and sent a message to King Kefaz and how the angel of God told Mary to go to Mount Lebanon again </title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.14"><locus from="18v" to="19v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary arrived at the place called Dirdi, meaning “City of Peace;” how she healed many sick people there; how the people of that city became jealous and asked her to go someplace else; how the cloud took her to the desert of Sinai when Elsabet has just died; how she mourned because of the death of Elsabet; how Saint Michael and Saint Gabriel buried Elsabet; and how the Virgin Mary tried to take Saint John with her, but he declined saying that it was better to be left in the desert.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.15"><locus from="19v" to="20r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary lived in the desert of Edom; how Joseph asked the Virgin Mary to go further to avoid the army of Herod; how they arrived in the country of Disran, near to the Sea of Gehon; how King Nǝrsǝm asked Saint Mary to stay in his country; how the people were afraid of the other king [Herod]; and how the Virgin Mary blessed them and prayed for them. </title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.16"><locus from="20r" to="21v"/><title>How, when fleeing to Egypt, the Virgin Mary asked water of a wealthy woman whose name was Tǝ‘ǝman; how the woman insulted her; how the servant of this woman, named Kotiba, threw the infant Jesus to the ground; how the wealthy woman descended to Sheol and how her family turned into wild animals (MYS 1, ff. 144r–145r) (a portion of this story is covered by the added illumination on f. 21r)</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.17"><locus from="21v" to="22r"/><title>How the angel of God told Joseph to take the child with his mother and return to the land of Israel; how the Virgin Mary praised God when she came into the land of Israel; how she healed many sick people in the city of Dirdis in Gaza; and how she passed through the city of Gaza where the land is cursed and finally arrived in her home land.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.18"><locus from="22v" to="23r"/><title>How the people of the land of lower Galilee welcomed the Virgin Mary; how she lived there for forty-nine [months]; how she healed many people; and how she declined to receive gifts from them.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.19"><locus from="180r" to="180v"/><title>Ff. 180rv: How the Virgin Mary kept the container of oil suspended in the air after its attachments had broken (Princeton 41, ff. 135r–136v; MYS 1, ff. 180rv).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.20"><locus from="23r" to="23v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary removed a Monastery in Greece near to the Sea of Jericho from the site on which it had been built in the desert to the side of a running stream; and how the removal was effected by night whilst the monks were sleeping (Budge, XIII; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 62rv; MYS 1, ff. 12rv).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.21"><locus from="23v" to="24r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary lived for seven months in Ethiopia; how the Lord blessed the land of Ethiopia and gave it to her as an inheritance. </title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.22"><locus from="24r" to="26r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary accepted the Book of Miracles compiled by Saint Däqsǝyos and how she punished a bishop who usurped the garment and chair of Däqsǝyos (Budge, I; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 30r–32r; MYS 1, ff. 5r–6r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.23"><locus from="26r" to="27r"/><title>[A variant version of] How the Virgin Mary accepted the Book of Miracles compiled by Saint Däqsǝyos and how she punished a bishop who usurped the garment and chair of Däqsǝyos (Budge, I; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 30r–32r; MYS 1, ff. 5r–6r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.24"><locus from="27r" to="27v"/><title>How a certain man wished to build a martyrium to the Virgin Mary but lacked the necessary money and how she showed him in a dream where a pot of gold coins was to be found (Budge, LXXXVIII; MYS 1, ff. 160v–161r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.25"><locus from="27v" to="28r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary spoke from her picture to a devout worshipper and said to him, “Blessed art thou among men” (Budge, II; Princeton 20, ff. 41v–42r; Princeton 23, ff. 28v–29v; Princeton 41, ff. 54v; Princeton 43, ff. 8rv; Princeton 46, ff. 10v–11r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.26"><locus from="28r" to="28v"/><title>How an aged Jew of Akhmim, who had spent his whole life in ministering in a church of the Virgin Mary, fell down one day during the service and broke his back, and how the Virgin Mary touched his backbone and made it whole, and made him to stand by her on the right-hand side of the altar (Budge, III; MYS 1, ff. 6v–7r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.27"><locus from="28v" to="29v"/><title>How the scribe Damianus used to write the name of the Virgin Mary in gold and colored paints, and how the Virgin appeared to him when dying, and took his soul to Paradise and showed him his name inscribed upon a pillar of gold (Budge, IV; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 55v–56r; MYS 1, ff. 7rv).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.28"><locus from="29v" to="30r"/><title>How Abbas, Bishop of Rome, cut off his hand which had been kissed by a woman when he was celebrating the Eucharist, and how the Virgin Mary rejoined it to his arm (Budge, V; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 55rv; MYS 1, ff. 7v–8r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.29"><locus from="30r" to="31r"/><title>How Isaac, monk and verger, heaped ascetic labors upon himself, and for seven years devoted his nights to prayers to the Virgin whilst the brethren were asleep, and how the Virgin Mary appeared to him and promised to take him to herself after three days (Budge, VI; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 56r–57r; MYS 1, ff. 8rv).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.30"><locus from="31r" to="31v"/><title>How a certain God-fearing man took his two elder daughters and went to church, leaving in his house Mary, his youngest daughter, in spite of her protests and wish to go in order to receive the Sacrament; and how the Virgin Mary appeared from out of her picture to the child, and told her that she would take her to herself in Paradise after three days; and how a godly man saw the child three days later, clad in purple and following the Virgin up into heaven (Budge, VII; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 57rv; MYS 1, ff. 8v–9r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.31"><locus from="31v" to="32v"/><title>How a certain painter was decorating a church with pictures of the blessed in and his friends in hell; how the Devil overturned the scaffolding, and how the painter was caught by the arm by the Virgin Mary as he fell, and how she lowered him little by little uninjured to the ground (Budge, VIII; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 57v–58v; MYS 1, ff. 9r–10r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.32"><locus from="32v" to="33r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary carried a sick monk from the Monastery of the Pilgrims to Palestine, and showed him Jerusalem and Bethlehem, and bathed him in the waters of Jordan (Budge, IX; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 58v–59r; MYS 1, f. 10r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.33"><locus from="33r" to="34r"/><title>How a certain youth called Zacharias, in other manuscripts, a native of Rome [Constantinople, in other mss] crowned the head of a picture of the Virgin daily with fifty roses, and how when the season of roses was past he recited fifty Aves before it, and how the Virgin Mary appeared to him in the desert, and how the thieves who were waiting to attack him repented and become monks when they saw the roses that dropped from his mouth when he addressed her (Budge, X; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 59r–60v; MYS 1, ff. 10r–11r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.34"><locus from="34r" to="34v"/><title>How two women called Juliana and Barbara, went on a pilgrimage to Jerusalem, were attached by robbers who stole their provisions; and how, when the thieves tried to eat them, the Virgin Mary turned the bread into stones upon which the thieves broke their teeth; and how the thieves repented and restored twofold what they had stolen from the women, when the Virgin Mary had healed their wounded mouths and mended their broken teeth (Budge, XI; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 60v–61r; MYS 1, ff. 11rv).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.35"><locus from="34v" to="35v"/><title>On the Assumption of Mary; How Jesus Christ took the body of the Virgin Mary to heaven (TM61 30–2; MYS 1, ff. 61v–63r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.36"><locus from="35v" to="36r"/><title>How three Arabs set sail for Rif, and were overtaken by a storm which sank their boat and hurled them into the water; how two of them appealed to the Virgin Mary for help, and were saved by her, whilst the third, who jeered at their prayers and called upon Muhammad the Prophet, was swallowed up by a crocodile; and how the men who were saved paid their vow and sent a camel-load of dates to the Monastery of Kalman, where there was a church dedicated to the Virgin Mary (Budge, XII; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 61r–62r; MYS 1, ff. 11v–12r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.37"><locus from="36r" to="38r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary commanded [Budge says “taught”] the Syrian potter [Ephrem] to learn by heart and to recite the weekly service of her Book of Praise (Budge, XXXV; Princeton 8, ff. 30r–33v; Princeton 41, ff. 77r–79r; Princeton 43, ff. 40r–43r; Princeton 46, ff. 47r–48v; Princeton 47, ff. 103v–106v).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.38"><locus from="38r" to="36v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary removed a Monastery in Greece from the site on which it had been built in the desert to the side of a running stream; and how the removal was effected by night whilst the monks were sleeping (Budge, XIII; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 62rv; MYS 1, ff. 12rv).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.39"><locus from="38v" to="39v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary anointed the eyes of John Bakansi, a blind priest of the Church of Saint Mercurius in Cairo, with milk from her breasts and restored his sight when he was one hundred years old (Budge, XIV; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 62v–63v; MYS 1, ff. 12v–13r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.40"><locus from="39v" to="40r"/><title>How a merchant from the Island of Colossae was shot in the eye by the arrow of a pirate in the Mediterranean; how his friends made an image in wax of the wounded man with an arrow fixed in one eye and took it to a church of the Virgin Mary; and how she withdrew the arrow from the eye of the figure, whereupon the eye of the Greek was healed (Budge, XV; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 63v–64r; MYS 1, ff. 13rv).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.41"><locus from="40r" to="40v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary restored the sight of Elizabeth, a blind girl of Badraman, by breathing upon her eyes and sprinkling them with milk from her breasts, incomplete at the end (Budge, XVI; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 64v–65v; MYS 1, ff. 13v–14v).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.42"><locus from="41r"/><title>How the Virgin delivered from devils the soul of a scribe who was engaged in writing a copy of the Book of her Miracles. This scribe had a brother who had sinned, but not knowing him they seized the innocent man and tried to carry him off to hell, incomplete at the beginning (Budge, XVIII; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 66v–67v; MYS 1, f. 15r). </title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.43"><locus from="41r" to="41v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary delivered from prison a certain man called “George the New” who had been condemned to suffer by the judges, and how she healed the wound in his head which had been inflicted by those who beat him (Budge, XIX; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 67v–68r; MYS 1, ff. 15rv).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.44"><locus from="41v" to="42r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the robber’s soul from judgment because he drank from water that sprang from her feet (Princeton 20, ff. 5rv; MYS 1, ff. 146rv).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.45"><locus from="42r" to="43r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary interceded on behalf of a robber who was killed by another robber while he was washing from water which ran from the feet of Mary; and also how she interceded on behalf of the daughter of the murdered robber who killed the robber who had killed her father.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.46"><locus from="43r" to="44v"/><title>How a certain woman whose husband had left her for another woman begged the Virgin Mary to kill the other woman; and how the Virgin Mary brought the other woman, who was devoted in worship of the Virgin, to repentance (TM61 256–8; MYS 1, ff. 131rv and ff. 192r–193r). </title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.47"><locus from="44v" to="45r"/><title>How Jesus asked Mary about her five lamentations (TM61 161–2; Princeton 46, f. 102v; Princeton 47, ff. 102v–103v; MYS 1, f. 107r).</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.48"><locus from="45r" to="45v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Yoḥannǝs Käma when he had remained in his vow of chastity even after he had married a woman; how she blessed him and gave him 100 dinars which had the sign of the cross on them and told him to put them in the offering box at the church to be a blessing to the people of that church.</title></msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2.49"><locus from="45v" to="46v"/><title>Miracle of Mary (How the son of the Muslim king of Egypt spit on the Icon of Mary and saw a vision of judgment; Princeton 46, ff. 114r–115r).</title></msItem>

                  </msItem>

                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i3"><locus from="47r" to="55v"/><textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang><title type="complete" ref="LIT2382Taamme"/><note>(beginning at: <locus target="#47r #48r #48v #51v #52r #52v #54r #55r"/>)</note></msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf">56</measure>
                           <measure unit="quire">7</measure>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height>320</height>
                              <width>250</width>
                              <depth>45</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation>
                          <signatures>Quires 2-3 numbered</signatures>
                          <note>Quire descriptions: quires 1–6 balanced; quire 7 adjusted balanced.</note>
                          <note>A partial sheet of parchment has been wrapped on the outside of the quires and under the covers. The parchment has been prepared with lines to receive text. In the front, this spine cover extends between 3 and 5 cm from the gutter. There is no writing on either side. The back spine cover extends between 5 and 6 cm from the gutter. There is some writing on the recto side.</note>
                          <list>
                              <item xml:id="q1" n="1">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus from="1" to="10"/>
                              Quire 1
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q2" n="2">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus from="11" to="20"/>
                              Quire 2
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q3" n="3">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus from="21" to="30"/>
                              Quire 3
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q4" n="4">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                                 <locus from="31" to="40"/>
                              Quire 4
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q5" n="5">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">6</dim>
                                 <locus from="41" to="46"/>
                                 <note>An uneven stub of parchment (which, in this case, we define as a reinforcement strip) is visible between <locus target="#46 #47"/>. It is 1–2 cm wide at the top of the codex and disappears about two-thirds of the way down the gutter. The other edge of this stub is visible between <locus target="#40 #41"/> though it is broken off at the gutter.</note>
                              Quire 5
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q6" n="6">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">6</dim>
                                 <locus from="47" to="52"/>
                              Quire 6
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q7" n="7">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">4</dim>
                                 <locus from="53" to="56"/>
                                 <note>Stubs appear between <locus target="#52 #53"/> and between <locus target="#55 #56"/>.</note>
                              Quire 7:
                              1, stub after 3
                              4, stub before 1
                            </item>
                          </list>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                       <layout>
                           <dimensions type="margin" unit="mm">
                              <dim type="top">38</dim>
                              <dim type="bottom">60</dim>
                              <dim type="right">28</dim>
                              <dim type="left">17</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                       </layout>
                       <layout columns="3" writtenLines="25">
                           <locus from="1r" to="55v"/>
                       </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                  <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                  <seg type="rubrication">
                  <foreign xml:lang="gez">ማርያም፡</foreign>
                  </seg>
                  </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d01"><locus target="#16v"/><desc><ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1031VirginAndChild"></ref></desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d02"><locus target="#21r"/><desc><ref type ="authFile" corresp="AT1002Annunciation"/></desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d03"><locus target="#50r"/><desc><ref type="authFile" corresp ="AT1041HolyMen"/>, four saints</desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d04"><locus target="#55v"/><desc>Talismanic symbol</desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="frame" xml:id="d05">
                      Decorative designs:
                      <locus target="#1r #5r"/> (fine, elaborate and colorful haräg);
                      <locus target="#4v"/> (multiple full stops);
                      <locus target="#47r"/> (crude haräg)
                    </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                    <list>
                      <item xml:id="a01">
                      <desc type="ScribalSignature">
                      <locus target="#52v"/> The scribe’s name is: Zena Gäbrǝ’el
                      </desc>
                      </item>
                      <item xml:id="e01">
                      <desc>
                      Numbered quires: quires 2–3
                      </desc>
                      </item>
                      <item xml:id="e02">
                      <desc>
                      words of text are written interlinearly (<locus target="#5v #6r #6v #15v #40r"/>, etc.);
                      and lines of text are written interlinearly (<locus target="#41v #44r"/>);
                      and in the upper margin with a symbol (┴) marking the location where the text is to be inserted (<locus target="#52r"/>, line 22);
                      text has been removed (e.g., <locus target="#5v #37v"/>)
                      </desc>
                      </item>
                    </list>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                    <binding xml:id="binding" contemporary="true">
                        <decoNote xml:id="b1">Parchment, 320 x 250 x 45 mm, four Coptic chain stitches attached with bridle attachments to rough-hewn boards of the traditional wood.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b2" type="bindingMaterial">
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                           <material key="wood"/>
                        </decoNote>
                    </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate notBefore="1800" notAfter="1899">nineteenth century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                     href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
         <change when="2018-07-15" who="JS">Added quire desc, binding desc, margin dim, columns/lines, dating info</change>
         <change when="2019-09-24" who="RL">Added ms item details, miniatures, notes and varia</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
