<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="mss" xml:lang="en" xml:id="EMIP00261">
   <teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Weiner Codex 84</title>
            <editor key="JS"/>
            <editor key="ABe"></editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Weiner</repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno n="130" facs="EMIP/Codices/261/">Weiner Codex 84</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Thirty-Two Miracles of Mary, ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                    <locus from="1r" to="56r" facs="003"/>
                    <title type="complete" ref="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.1">
                    <locus from="1r" to="4r" facs="003"/>
                    <title>Extended version of Introductory Rite from Mu‘allaqa</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2">
                    <locus from="5r" to="56r" facs="007"/>
                    <title type="complete" ref="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                    <note>Thirty-Three Miracles of Mary (rebound in disorder)</note>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.1">
                    <locus from="5r" facs="007"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary accepted the Book of Miracles compiled by Saint Däqsǝyos and how she punished a bishop who usurped the garment and chair of Däqsǝyos</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.2">
                    <locus from="7r" facs="009"/>
                    <title>How a certain righteous governor was falsely accused, and the authorities attempted to injure him, but the Virgin Mary prevented the injury and also sustained his life when they attempted to hang him</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.3">
                    <locus from="9r" facs="011"/>
                    <title>How, because of his devotion to her, the Virgin Mary saved the soul of a wicked monastic leader from hell when he died; and how he appeared to his disciple in a dream and told him how the Virgin Mary saved him from damnation</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.4">
                    <locus from="10r" facs="012"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary saved from a sinking ship a certain devoted person who cried out to Mary, who then came and covered him with her wings (other accounts say garment)</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.5">
                    <locus from="12v" facs="015"/>
                    <title>How the painted figures of the Virgin Mary and Christ on an icon bled when a Jew cast the board into a pit, and how the magistrate had the Jew burnt alive</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.6">
                    <locus from="13v" facs="016"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a monk when he couldn’t walk and his friends carried him to church; how she appeared to him and took him to Paradise; and how a certain monk saw this in his dream</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.7">
                    <locus from="15r" facs="017"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary saved a young widow from the wiles of a certain knight, who forthwith became a monk and retired to the desert</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.8">
                    <locus from="18v" facs="021"/>
                    <title>A story about a bell ringer and faithful priest. The exact identification is not possible due to the disorder of the folios</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.9">
                    <locus from="19r" facs="021"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary revealed to a certain man the truth of the prophecy of Isaiah about the birth of the messiah by a virgin; and how she allowed him to kiss her feet and cheek. Not known in other collections</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.10">
                    <locus from="30r" to="20r" facs="032"/>
                    <title>How the icon of the Virgin Mary helped a young impoverished man and how the church keeper saw this miracle and how he gave his daughter to the young man in marriage. Ending f. 20r, beginning ff. 30rv</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.11">
                    <locus from="21r" facs="023"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary commanded the bishop to bury in the believers’ burial the body of a hanged thief who had been devoted to Mary; and how a tree with healing powers grew up from his grave</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.12">
                    <locus from="23v" facs="026"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary spoke from her picture to a devout worshipper and said to him, “Blessed art thou among men.”</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.13">
                    <locus from="24v" facs="027"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary raised up a dead knight, who had been buried in the cemetery of a convent, to fight against an enemy of the church called Gǝldǝyanos. (continued on ff. 27rv)</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.14">
                    <locus from="26r" facs="028"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain priest inside the church at the time of prayer; How the Abbott of the church had beaten the priest because he had not participated in prayer. Incomplete at the beginning and end</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.15">
                    <locus from="37r" to="28r" facs="039"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary received the gift of a certain woman who was forbidden to fast by her husband, incomplete at the beginning. 15.	Concluded on f. 28r, beginning f. 37r</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.16">
                    <locus from="28r" to="31r" facs="030"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary saved the drunken monk from a lion and a savage dog. Beginning f. 28r, continued 31rv</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.17">
                    <locus from="40v" to="29r" facs="043"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain painter when he fell from his scaffolding, incomplete at the beginning. Concluded on f. 29r, beginning on f. 40v</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.18">
                    <locus from="29v" to="54r" facs="032"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a jeweler to forbid him from making an icon for certain arrogant people; and how she showed an icon of her which had been made by the angels to Abba Basiliyos. Beginning f. 29v; ending ff. 54r–55v</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.19">
                    <locus from="31v" facs="034"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary saved the people on a certain ship on the sea when they were caught in a powerful storm</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.20">
                    <locus from="33v" facs="036"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary healed the sick deacon who recited her sälam song by anointing him with her breast milk</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.21">
                    <locus from="35r" facs="037"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary protected a sinful man from his attackers until he had confessed his sin to the priest; and how she received his soul after he was executed; and how the people saw this and repented of their sins</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.22">
                    <locus from="36r" facs="038"/>
                    <title>How two traveling women [elsewhere called Juliana and Barbara] were attacked by robbers who stole their provisions; and how, when the head of the bandits tried to eat the stolen food, the Virgin Mary turned the bread into stones upon which he broke his teeth; and how the thieves repented from their evil</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.23">
                    <locus from="36v" to="47r" facs="039"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary commanded a deacon to dig up and rebury in consecrated ground the body of an adulterous deacon from the island of Jericho in the city of Gärisat who was killed by the people. Beginning f. 36v, continuing ff. 41rv, and ending 47r</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.24">
                    <locus from="46r" to="38r" facs="048"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary healed a certain sinful woman when she swallowed a scorpion because she was depressed about her sin and how a voice from the icon led her to a certain priest for repentance and healing. Ending f. 38r and beginning 46rv</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.25">
                    <locus from="38v" to="39v" facs="041"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a wise monk who had criticized his fellow monks about the food they were eating and how she chided him, incomplete at the end</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.26">
                    <locus from="52r" to="40r" facs="054"/>
                    <title>How a certain Jew of Constantinople threw into the water [other accounts say to the ground] a picture of the Virgin Mary and when it was restored it exuded oil that healed many, incomplete at the beginning. 26.	Ending f. 40r; beginning 52rv</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.27">
                    <locus from="42r" to="43r" facs="044"/>
                    <title>How a monk from Alexandria [other versions say an aged Jew of Akhmim], who had spent his whole life in ministering in a church of the Virgin Mary, became old and could not walk [other versions say that he fell down one day during the service and broke his back], and how the Virgin Mary touched his backbone and made it whole, and made him to stand by her on the right-hand side of the altar</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.28">
                    <locus from="43r" to="44v" facs="045"/>
                    <title>How a scribe [some versions name him as Damianus] used to write the name of the Virgin Mary in gold and colored paints, and how the Virgin appeared to him when dying, and took his soul to Paradise and showed him his name inscribed upon a pillar of gold</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.29">
                    <locus from="44v" to="46r" facs="047"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to reassure an ascetic woman about the purity of her friends, other ascetic women held with her in prison</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.30">
                    <locus from="47r" to="49v" facs="049"/>
                    <title>How a certain woman prayed to Mary to hold Jesus as the Virgin Mary had held her; how Jesus Christ appeared to the woman as a small child; and how the woman did not recognize him and sent him away</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.31">
                    <locus from="49v" to="51r" facs="052"/>
                    <title>How a certain witch advised a man to bring communion for the purpose of attracting bees; how the man brought the communion elements in his mouth and put them in the beehive; how light shown in the beehive and how the Virgin Mary with her Beloved Son appeared in the beehive; and how the priest and the believers took the beehive to the church, received the communion elements and how they killed the man</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.32">
                    <locus from="51r" to="52r" facs="053"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of a certain rich person who had stolen the land and grain of the people, but was devoted to the Virgin Mary; how the demons tried to take his soul; how the demons and the angels put his deeds in the balances; and how the Virgin Mary interceded to save his soul</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>

                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2.33">
                    <locus from="52r" to="56r" facs="054"/>
                    <title>How the Virgin Mary removed a Monastery [called in some versions the monastery Akona or Sikona] near Jericho from the site on which it had been built in the desert to the side of a running stream; and how the removal was effected by night whilst the monks were sleeping. 52r–53r, ending f. 56r</title>
                    <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝ'ǝz</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                </msItem>
              </msItem>

               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf">ii + 58</measure>
                           <measure unit="quire">Protection sheet + 4</measure>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height>200</height>
                              <width>173</width>
                              <depth>50</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation>
                          <note>Quire descriptions: protection sheet and quires 1 and 4 balanced; quire 2 adjusted balanced; quire 3 unbalanced.</note>
                          <note>
                              <locus from="24" to="58" facs="026"/> have been assembled in no discernable quire pattern utilizing various stab stitches. This makes an accurate map of the codex impossible to determine.</note>
                          <list>
                              <item xml:id="q1" n="a">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">2</dim>
                                 <locus from="i" to="ii" facs="001"/>
                              Protection Sheet
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q2" n="1">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">4</dim>
                                 <locus from="1" to="4" facs="003"/>
                              Quire 1
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q3" n="2">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                                 <locus from="5" to="12" facs="007"/>
                                 <note>
                                    <locus target="#5 #12" facs="007 014"/> are stitched onto the same vellum strap wrapped around the spine of the quire.</note>
                              Quire 2
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q4" n="3">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">7</dim>
                                 <locus from="13" to="19" facs="015"/>
                                 <note>Unbalanced quire (Quire 3) has been repaired.</note>
                              Quire 3:
                              1 added
                            </item>
                              <item xml:id="q5" n="4">
                                 <dim unit="leaf">4</dim>
                                 <locus from="20" to="23" facs="022"/>
                              Quire 4
                            </item>
                          </list>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                       <layout>
                           <dimensions type="margin" unit="mm">
                              <dim type="top">22</dim>
                              <dim type="bottom">39</dim>
                              <dim type="right">32</dim>
                              <dim type="left">10</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                       </layout>
                       <layout columns="2" writtenLines="21">
                           <locus from="1r" to="4r" facs="003"/>
                       </layout>
                       <layout columns="2" writtenLines="16">
                           <locus from="5r" to="58r" facs="007"/>
                       </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                  <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                  <seg type="rubrication">
                  <foreign xml:lang="gez">ማርያም፡</foreign>
                  <foreign xml:lang="gez">ኢየሱስ፡</foreign>
                  </seg>
                  <desc>The words Mary and Jesus are rubricated</desc>
                  </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d1"><locus target="#iir(ecto)" facs="002"/><desc>Ornate <ref type ="authFile" corresp="AT1071Cross"/></desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d2"><locus target="#iiv(erso)" facs="003"/><desc>Three panels: the upper has five people, four arches and a face; the middle has four arches; the lower contains two elephants, two leopards and other animals</desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d3"><locus target="#57r" facs="059"/><desc>The Great Judgment (?)</desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d4"><locus target="#58r" facs="060"/><desc>Crude drawing of two men, a rifle, and a <term key="sword"/></desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="frame" xml:id="d5">
                    Decorative designs:
                    <locus target="#iv(erso) #iir(ecto) #57v #58r" facs="002 060"/> (ḥaräg)
                    </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <list>
                    <item xml:id="a1">
                    <desc>
                    <locus target="#iv(erso) #iir(ecto) #57v #58r" facs="002 060"/>
                    Miracle of Jesus, in a later hand, mentioning Emperor Mǝnilǝk
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a2">
                    <desc>
                    <locus target="#iir(ecto)" facs="002"> f. iir(ecto), col. 2</locus>Reminder to observe the two Sabbaths
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a3">
                    <desc>
                    <locus target="#4r #4v" facs="006 007"/>
                    An attempt to copy a miracle of the Archangel <persName ref="PRS7049Michael"/>, incomplete, in blue ink
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a4">
                    <desc type="OwnershipNote">
                    <locus target="#5r" facs="007"> f. 5r and passim</locus>
                    Name of original owner, <persName ref="PRS4306GabraMa"/>
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a5">
                    <desc>
                    <locus target="#ir(ecto) #58r" facs="001 060"/>
                    The Miracle of Jesus is copied by Affäsä, baptismal name Gäbrä Maryam for the church Däbrä Mika’el; commissioned by Wäldä Maryam during the reign of Mǝnilǝk
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a6">
                    <desc type="OwnershipNote">
                    <locus target="#56r" facs="058"> f. 56r, lines 7 and 8</locus>
                    Note of ownership in a later hand: “This book belongs to [the church of] Qǝddus Mika’el.”
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a7">
                    <desc>
                    <locus target="#56r" facs="058"> f. 56r, bottom</locus>
                    Isolated names in blue ink
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e1">
                    <desc>
                    <locus target="#58v" facs="061"/>
                    pen trials
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e2">
                    <desc>
                    The back cover has a large ornate cross etched into the wood
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e3">
                    <desc>
                    Scribal intervention:
                    words of text are written interlinearly (<locus target="#23r" facs="025"/>)
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                  </list>
                </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                    <binding xml:id="binding" contemporary="false">
                        <decoNote xml:id="b1">Parchment, 200 x 173 x 50 mm, four Coptic chain stitches attached with bridle attachments to rough-hewn boards of the traditional wood, rebound in disorder.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b2" type="bindingMaterial">
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                           <material key="wood"/>
                        </decoNote>
                    </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate notBefore="1600" notAfter="1699">seventeenth century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
         <change when="2018-09-16" who="JS">Added quire desc, binding desc, margin dim, columns/lines, dating info</change>
         <change when="2020-04-18" who="RL">Corrected ǝ character</change>
         <change when="2020-08-10" who="ABe">Added items</change>
         <change when="2020-11-06" who="ABe">Updated facs statements</change>
    </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
