<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP00601">
   <teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Mekane Yesus Seminary 1</title>
            <editor key="ABe"></editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Mekane Yesus Seminary </repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/601/">Mekane Yesus Seminary 1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Miracles of Mary, ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1"><locus from="1r" to="197v"/><title type="complete" ref="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>Three Hundred Seventy One Miracles of Mary, <foreign xml:lang="gez">ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡</foreign>, each with a rhyming summary at the end. There are similarities with Princeton Ethiopic MS 41 which leaves four blank lines at the end of each miracle to be filled in later with the concluding summarizing hymn. The standard works on the miracles of Mary are Cerulli, Maria, and Budge, Mary.</note>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.1"><locus from="1r" to="3v"/><title>Introductory Rite from Mu‗älläqa</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2"><locus from="5r" to="6r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary accepted the Book of Miracles compiled by Saint Däqsǝyos and how she punished a bishop who usurped the garment and chair of Däqsǝyos</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, I; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#30r #30v #31r #31v #32r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.3"><locus from="6r" to="6v"/><title>How Däqsǝyos healed the sick and the demon possessed by means of the covering of the icon</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.4"><locus from="6v" to="7r"/><title>How an aged Jew of Akhmim, who had spent his whole life in ministering in a church of the Virgin Mary, fell down one day during the service and broke his back, and how the Virgin Mary touched his backbone and made it whole, and made him to stand by her on the right-hand side of the altar</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, III)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.5"><locus from="7r" to="7v"/><title>How the scribe Damianus used to write the name of the Virgin Mary in gold and colored paints, and how the Virgin appeared to him when dying, and took his soul to Paradise and showed him his name inscribed upon a pillar of gold</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, IV; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#55v #56r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.6"><locus from="7v" to="8r"/><title>How Abbas, Bishop of Rome, cut off his hand which had been kissed by a woman when he was celebrating the Eucharist, and how the Virgin Mary rejoined it to his arm</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, V; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#55r #55v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.7"><locus from="8r" to="8v"/><title>How Isaac, monk and verger, heaped ascetic labors upon himself, and for seven years devoted his nights to prayers to the Virgin whilst the brethren were asleep, and how the Virgin Mary appeared to him and promised to take him to herself after three days</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, VI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#56r #56v #57r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.8"><locus from="8v" to="9r"/><title>How a certain God-fearing man took his two elder daughters and went to church, leaving in his house Mary, his youngest daughter, in spite of her protests and wish to go in order to receive the Sacrament; and how the Virgin Mary appeared from out of her picture to the child, and told her that she would take her to herself in Paradise after three days; and how a godly man saw the child three days later, clad in purple and following the Virgin up into heaven</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, VII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#57r #57v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.9"><locus from="9r" to="10r"/><title>How a certain painter was decorating a church with pictures of the blessed in and his friends in hell; how the Devil overturned the scaffolding, and how the painter was caught by the arm by the Virgin Mary as he fell, and how she lowered him little by little uninjured to the ground</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, VIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#57v #58r #58v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.10"><locus from="10r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary carried a sick monk from the Monastery of the Pilgrims to Palestine, and showed him Jerusalem and Bethlehem, and bathed him in the waters of Jordan</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, IX; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#58v #59r"/>). Budge has "Monastery of Beggars"</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.11"><locus from="10r" to="11r"/><title>How a certain youth called Zacharias, a native of Constantinople, crowned the head of a picture of the Virgin daily with fifty roses, and how when the season of roses was past he recited fifty Aves before it, and how the Virgin Mary appeared to him in the desert, and how the thieves who were waiting to attack him repented and become monks when they saw the roses that dropped from his mouth when he addressed her</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, X; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#59r #59v #60r #60v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.12"><locus from="11r" to="11v"/><title>How two women called Juliana and Barbara, went on a pilgrimage to Jerusalem, were attached by robbers who stole their provisions; and how, when the thieves tried to eat them, the Virgin Mary turned the bread into stones upon which the thieves broke their teeth; and how the thieves repented and restored twofold what they had stolen from the women, when the Virgin Mary had healed their wounded mouths and mended their broken teeth</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#60v #61r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.13"><locus from="11v" to="12r"/><title>How three Arabs set sail for Rif, and were overtaken by a storm which sank their boat and hurled them into the water; how two of them appealed to the Virgin Mary for help, and were saved by her, whilst the third, who jeered at their prayers and called upon Muhammad the Prophet, was swallowed up by a crocodile; and how the men who were saved paid their vow and sent a camel-load of dates to the Monastery of Kalman, where there was a church dedicated to the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#61r #61v #62r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.14"><locus from="12r" to="12v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary removed the Monastery of Si'ǝqona from the site on which it had been built in the desert to the side of a running stream; and how the removal was effected by night whilst the monks were sleeping</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#62r #62v"/>). Budge has "Monastery of ‗Akona"</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.15"><locus from="12v" to="13r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary anointed the eyes of John Bakansi, a blind priest of the Church of Saint Mercurius in Cairo, with milk from her breasts and restored his sight when he was one hundred years old</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XIV; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#62v #63r #63v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.16"><locus from="13r" to="13v"/><title>How a merchant from the Island of Colossae was shot in the eye by the arrow of a pirate in the Mediterranean; how his friends made an image in wax of the wounded man with an arrow fixed in one eye and took it to a church of the Virgin Mary; and how she withdrew the arrow from the eye of the figure, whereupon the eye of the Greek was healed</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XV; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#63v #64r"/>). Budge has "Greek Merchant" in his table of contents</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.17"><locus from="13v" to="14v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary restored the sight of Elizabeth, a blind girl of Badraman, by breathing upon her eyes and sprinkling them with milk from her breasts</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XVI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#64v #65r #65v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.18"><locus from="14v" to="15r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary arranged marriages for three poor girls,4 called Mary, Martha and Yawahita, with the sons of Tewog, the blacksmith of Makmas</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XVII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#65v #66r #66v"/>). Budge‘s table of contents lists only "two girls" but the account in the body of his work lists "three poor sisters."</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.19"><locus from="15r"/><title>How the Virgin delivered from devils the soul of a scribe who was engaged in writing a copy of the Book of her Miracles. This scribe had a brother who had sinned, but not knowing him they seized the innocent man and tried to carry him off to hell</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XVIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#66v #67r #67v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.20"><locus from="15r" to="15v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary delivered from prison a certain man called "George the New" who had been condemned to suffer by the judges, and how she healed the wound in his head which had been inflicted by those who beat him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XIX; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#67v #68r"/>). Budge has simply "George."</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.21"><locus from="15v" to="16r"/><title>How a cruel sacristan evilly entreated an aged priest called Qäṭir, and thrust him out of the church, and how the Virgin Mary restored the strength of her servant, and caused two men to bastinado the sacristan, whom she smote with paralysis</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XX; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#68r #68v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.22"><locus from="16r" to="16v"/><title>How a certain Qadi caused a Christian dyer called Nazib to be beaten and shut up in prison in order to compel him to embrace Islam, and how, at the intercession of Tag, the Virgin Mary sent to the Kadi St. George of Lydda, who threatened to kill him if he did not release Nazib</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#68v #69r #69v"/>). Budge does not mention Tag</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.23"><locus from="16v" to="17r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary cured a man in his lameness</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#70r #70v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.24"><locus from="17r" to="17v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary cleansed Bishop Mercurius of his leprosy by touching his body with her hand</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#70v #71r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.25"><locus from="17v" to="18r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary used to appear in person in the church at Ḫärtälomä, and how she healed the broken foot of a woman therein</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXIV; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#73v #74r #74v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.26"><locus from="18r" to="19r"/><title>How Sophia, Abbes of Mount Carmel, became with child; how the Virgin Mary caused an angel to deliver her of her child before the arrival of the bishop who came to enquire into the matter; and how the child was reared by the monks and Bishop Severus, whom he succeeded in the episcopate</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXV; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#89r #89v #90r #90v #91r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.27"><locus from="19r" to="19v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Barok, a dissolute man who worshipped her, and took it to Paradise</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXVI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#85v #86r #86v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.28"><locus from="19v" to="20r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Anastasius, a deacon of Rome, who addressed the "Five Gaudes" to her at all times, and took it to Paradise</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXVII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#84 #84v #85r"/>). Budge has Constantinople</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.29"><locus from="20r" to="21r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary helped a pious monk of the Monastery of Abba Samuel of Qälmon to escape from the persecution of the brethren by making a breach in the wall of the church when he smote it with his skull cap</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXVIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#104r #104v #105r #105v #106r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.30"><locus from="21r" to="21v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary delivered from crucifixion the son of a poor widow, who had become a thief and a robber</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXX; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#80r #80v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.31"><locus from="21v" to="22r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary protected a woman, great with child, who was overtaken by an inrush of the sea, and how the woman brought forth her child and escaped from drowning</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#83r #83v #84r"/>). Up to this point, the order and content of the miracles is very close to Budges order and content; after this the relationship breaks down</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.32"><locus from="22r" to="22v"/><title>How a certain rich man hurled a loaf at the head of a beggar and wounded him, and how the Virgin Mary delivered his soul from the devils</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LXXXVI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#71v #72r #72v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.33"><locus from="22v" to="23r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a daughter of a wealthy man from labor pain</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#72v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.34"><locus from="23r" to="23v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed the blind daughter of a woman who, in a dream, threw her daughter into the sea</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#73r #73v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.35"><locus from="23v" to="24r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary raised the dead son of a wealthy man from Cappadocia who refused to bury the son and who took the body to the church and prayed to Mary for his son</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#74v #75r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.36"><locus from="24r"/><title>How a certain woman, living with her mother-in-law, was devoted to an icon of Mary in her house; how her mother-in-law criticized her for her devotion to the icon; how Mary appeared in a dream and told her that she could not stay in the home because of the criticisms of the mother-in-law; and how, when she awoke, the icon was gone</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#75r #75v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.37"><locus from="24r" to="24v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain military officer of the King when he became mentally distressed by anointing his lips with her breast milk</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cp., Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#75r #75v #76r #76v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.38"><locus from="24v" to="25r"/><title>How a certain woman was bereft of her nine children; how the Virgin Mary appeared to her and promised three children who would become priests; how she conceived three children who became priests and presided at her funeral</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#76v #77r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.39"><locus from="25r" to="25v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved Qiras, the bandit who was devoted to Mary, when the people caught him and led him to the gallows; and how he later became a monk</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#80r #80v"/>; cf. Budge, XXXI)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.40"><locus from="25v" to="26r"/><title>How a certain man slew an evil-living deacon and buried him where he fell, and how the Virgin Mary had his body dug up and buried in consecrated ground</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(a version of Budge, CIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#80v #81r #81v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.41"><locus from="26r" to="26v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary cut out and sewed a garment for Philotheus, a bishop of Upper Egypt</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XL; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#81v #82r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.42"><locus from="26v" to="27r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary revealed herself to Bishop Philotheus when he refused to receive the repentance of a man called araqos</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 82r–83r)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.43"><locus from="27r" to="27v"/><title>How Nicodemus, an evil-living Persian knight, became a Christian, but was unable to learn the Lord‘s Prayer, and could only master the Salutation to Mary; and how these words were found written on every leaf of a tree which grew on his grave</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXVIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#85r #85v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.44"><locus from="27v" to="28r"/><title>How a certain bishop removed a priest from his office owing to complaints of his ignorance of the Eucharistic service, and how the Virgin Mary rebuked the bishop</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, CII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#86v #87r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.45"><locus from="28r" to="28v"/><title>How a certain Hebrew man called Alexander was swallowed by a large serpent and cried out to the Virgin Mary; how the serpent spat him out; how he further developed leprosy, cried out to the Virgin Mary again, became a Christian and was healed</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#87v #88r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.46"><locus from="28v" to="29r"/><title>How a certain righteous governor, Armatyas of Ephesus, was falsely accused, and the authorities attempted to behead him, but the Virgin Mary prevented the beheading and also sustained his life when they attempted to hang him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#88v #89r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.47"><locus from="29r"/><title>How a generous, wealthy woman attended prayers with the monks at a monastery and saw the Virgin Mary descending from heaven with a multitude of angels</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#91r #91v #92r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic MS 8, <locus target="#45v #46r #46v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.48"><locus from="29r" to="29v"/><title>How a certain Ishmaelite was converted when he saw oil and milk flowing from the breasts of a picture of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LXI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#92r #92v #93r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.49"><locus from="29v" to="30r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary helped a young, impoverished man and how the church keeper gave his daughter to him [when he saw the icon of the Virgin Mary bow down to him]</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#93r #93v #94r"/>; and Princeton Ethiopic MS 20, <locus target="#25r #72r #72v"/>). Not included in the Budge collection, but the theme of the bowing icon appears in other miracle stories</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.50"><locus from="30r" to="30v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary delivered from the devils the soul of an avaricious farmer who had given alms in her name during his life</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, CIX; Princeton Ethiopic MX 41, <locus target="#94r #94v #95r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.51"><locus from="30v" to="31r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary commanded the bishop to bury in the believers‘ burial the body of a hanged thief who had been devoted to Mary; and how a tree with healing powers grew up from his grave</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.52"><locus from="31r" to="31v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary revealed herself as a woman with wings like an eagle‘s wings to John the Righteous, the priest at Mäqarǝs monastery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#97r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.53"><locus from="31v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain nun and commanded her to continue reciting the Hail Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#96r #96v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.54"><locus from="31v" to="32v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved, by the intercession of Abba Samuel of the monastery of Qälǝmon, a fallen angel who had failed to execute judgment on a city by saving a beautiful young child</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#97v #98r #98v"/>; and Princeton Ethiopic 43, <locus target="#53v #54r #54v #55r #55v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.55"><locus from="32v" to="33r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved Timothy, a drunken monk, from a lion and a savage dog</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXVIII and Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#98v #99r #99v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.56"><locus from="33r" to="33v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved from a sinking ship a certain devoted person who cried out to Mary, who then came and covered him with her garment</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#99v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.57"><locus from="33v" to="34r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a man from France (Färäsawi) when he denied Christ but kept devotion to the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#100v #101r #101v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.58"><locus from="34r" to="34v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to the man from France named Nifon and led him to the monastic life</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#106r #106v #107r #107v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.59"><locus from="34v" to="35r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a monk from the Island Ṭegǝros (Tigris?) when he couldn‘t walk and his friends carried him to church</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#107v #108r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.60"><locus from="35r" to="35v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary took a Shepherd into paradise in seven days</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#108r #108v #109r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.61"><locus from="35v" to="37r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary recovered for a deacon named Mika‘el a ring stolen by a Muslim and swallowed by the fish</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#101v #102r #102v #103r #103v #104r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.62"><locus from="37r" to="41r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary at the intercession of John the priest caused the Khalifah of Athribis to spare her church in that city</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXIV)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.63"><locus from="41r" to="43r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary helped Abba Abraham the Syrian, archbishop of Alexandria, move a mountain when he was challenged by the Jewish advisor of a Muslim King</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. TM89 150–4)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.64"><locus from="43r" to="46r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave to a certain couple a child and how, when he was grown and falsely accused of stealing, the Virgin Mary saved him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.65"><locus from="46r" to="47r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary recovered the scissors of Jacob the Short, a tailor, when Arabs stole it from him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#122r #122v"/>, but 122v has been painted over with an added illumination)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.66"><locus from="47r" to="47v"/><title>How a certain monk converted to Judaism and denied Christ and the Virgin Mary and how a Christian governor put to death the monk</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>This miracle has been considered relevant for the discussion of the origin of the Falasha group in Ethiopia. See, Stephen Kaplan‘s The Monastic Holy Man and the Christianization of Early Solomonic Ethiopia (Weisbaden: Franz Steiner Verlag, 1984) 40, etc.</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.67"><locus from="47v" to="49r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary helped a certain man named Aboli to borrow money from a rich Jew and how the icon of the Virgin Mary testified when the Jew denied receiving the borrowed money</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 261–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.68"><locus from="49r" to="49v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary commanded the demon to serve the monks in the monastery in Egypt</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 46, <locus target="#93v #94r #94v"/>; TM89 165–8)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.69"><locus from="49v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary recovered a silver dish from the river</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 46, <locus target="#94v #95r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.70"><locus from="49v" to="50r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the abbot of Däbrä Qwusqwam from flogging when the Muslim governor tried to plunder the monastery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.71"><locus from="50r" to="51r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a young widow from the wiles of a certain knight, who forthwith became a monk and retired to the desert</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LV)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.72"><locus from="51r" to="51v"/><title>How the icon of the Virgin Mary healed a woman who suffered from hemorrhage</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#132r #132v #133r #133v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.73"><locus from="51v" to="52r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished a Muslim man when he tried to take the clothes of two monks</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.74"><locus from="52r" to="52v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary made the tears of a sinful maiden, when weighed in the scales of Justice, to outweigh her sins; and how Mary commanded Saint Mika‘el to baptize the woman and add her to the virgins of the monastery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. miracle 201 below and Budge, LXXI and TM89 227–31)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.75"><locus from="53r" to="54r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary was born to Joakim and Anna</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#13r #13 #14r #14v"/>; TM89 16–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.76"><locus from="54r" to="54v"/><title>How Saint Gabriel took the body of the Virgin Mary and put it under the tree of life in Paradise, and how 600 Jews who tried to burn the body of the Virgin Mary were baptized when they saw the earth swallow one of their number who had insulted Christ and the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 19–21)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.77"><locus from="54v" to="55v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished the camel caravan leader of Däbrä Mǝṭmaq monastery when he stole property from the monastery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#150r #150v #151r #151v #152r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.78"><locus from="55v" to="56v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished the King of Egypt named al-Sharif when he plundered the monastery of Däbrä Mǝṭmaq and how Christians in Egypt sent a message to Emperor Zärǝ‗a Ya‗ǝqob, king of Ethiopia, about the destruction of Däbrä Mǝṭmaq and how he built a church and named it Däbrä Mǝṭmaq</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 59–64)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.79"><locus from="56v" to="59r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Muslim traders at Däbrä Mǝṭmaq after its destruction and how the Virgin Mary commanded them to tell her miracle and how she led them to Christianity</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 64–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.80"><locus from="59r" to="59v"/><title>How the angel of God cut the hand of Tawǝfanya when he tried to burn the body of Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 21–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.81"><locus from="59v" to="60r"/><title>How Saint John greeted the Virgin Mary when he embalmed her body</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 23–5)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.82"><locus from="60r" to="61r"/><title>How the apostles did not leave the body of Mary for fear of the Jews and how the angel of God encouraged them to claim the body</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 25–30)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.83"><locus from="61r" to="61v"/><title>On the Assumption of Mary; How Jesus Christ took the body of the Virgin Mary to heaven</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 30–2)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.84"><locus from="61v" to="63r"/><title>How the icon of the Virgin Mary came from Jerusalem to the city of Ṣedenya</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 32–7) This miracle is mentioned in the introductory rite of Mu‗alqqa, see Budge xlvii</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.85"><locus from="63r" to="63v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave birth to Jesus Christ and how the wise men came to present their gifts</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 39–41)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.86"><locus from="63v" to="64r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave birth while she was with Joseph in Bethlehem for the census</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 41–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.87"><locus from="64r" to="66r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary received the covenant of mercy from her son; and how the Virgin Mary saved the soul of the cannibal of Kemer, who had killed and eaten his wife and two children and a large number of men and women</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXIX; TM89 43–52) In this manuscript and in TM the miracles are combined in one account; in Budge the miracle of the cannibal of Kemer is a separate miracle</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.88"><locus from="66r" to="66v"/><title>How, when the Virgin Mary was weaving silk and gold in the temple, God sent Gabriel to announce the birth of Jesus Christ</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 52–4)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.89"><locus from="66v" to="67r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary conceived Jesus Christ on Maggabit 29</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 54–5)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.90"><locus from="67r" to="69v"/><title>How Jesus predicted to his mother the Virgin Mary that a church (Däbrä Mǝṭmaq) would be constructed in Egypt where they had stayed and how the Virgin Mary appeared to the people of Egypt</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 46, <locus target="#80r #80v #81r #81v #82r #82v #83r #83v #84r"/>; TM89 69–80)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.91"><locus from="69v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to the apostles with Jesus Christ</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 84–5)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.92"><locus from="69v" to="70v"/><title>How, when the people of Damot worked on the day of Mary‘s festival, the Virgin Mary uprooted a tree that they worshipped, and how when the people tried to cut up the tree, the Virgin Mary raised the tree upright again and how Zärǝ‗a Ya‗ǝqob, king of Ethiopia built a church at that place</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(See <locus target="#89r #89v #90r #90v"/> in this manuscript; TM89 88–94)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.93"><locus from="71r"/><title>How Joachim and Hanna presented the Virgin Mary to the temple</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#14v #15r #15v"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 47, <locus target="#13r #13v #14r #14v #15r"/>; and cf. TM89 18–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.94"><locus from="71r" to="72r"/><title>How Saint Gabriel announced the birth of Jesus Christ to Mary as she was spinning silk for the temple; how Joseph received the Virgin Mary in order to protect her; and how she gave water in her shoe to a thirsty dog</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(regarding the annunciation, cf. Princeton Ethiopic 37, <locus target="#67r #67v #68r #68v"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#15v #16r #16v #17r"/>; regarding water for a thirsty dog, cf., Princeton Ethiopic 20, <locus target="#83r #83v #84r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 47, <locus target="#92v #93r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 55, <locus target="#150r #150v #151r #151v #152r"/>; Budge, XXXIII; and TM89 217–18)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.95"><locus from="72r"/><title>How Abba Samu‘el levitated from the ground and spewed fire from his mouth and was not touched by the rain when he read the praises of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 43, <locus target="#52v #53r #53v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.96"><locus from="72r" to="72v"/><title>How Zechariah, the prophet, saw a vision of Zion and seven lamp stands which symbolized Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.97"><locus from="72v" to="73r"/><title>[The beginning of the Zion Cycle:] How Moses received Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—with the ten commandments on Mount Sinai</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>The following cycle of miracles, which we call "The Zion Cycle," continues in nineteen sections through <locus target="#78r"/>. In the upper corners of <locus target="#72r #72v #73r"/> is written the word "Zion." The cycle is narrated, ostensibly, by Ezra (see, miracles 114 and 115 on <locus target="#78r"/>). This cycle is known in no other copy of the Miracles of Mary with which we are familiar</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.98"><locus from="73r"/><title>How, after the death of Moses, Joshua received Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—; and how he parted the Jordan River, circled Jericho and stopped the movement of the sun with it, and how he built a home for Zion, the tablet, in Jericho; and how it was there throughout the period of the Judges</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.99"><locus from="73r" to="73v"/><title>How David received with praise Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—and how he put it in the temple until Solomon became King, and how Menelik the son of Solomon and the Queen of the South took it to Aksum; and how, when he was pursued by the army of Solomon, escaped when the Red Sea opened before him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.100"><locus from="73v"/><title>How the army of Solomon became sad when they realized that Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary— was beyond their power to regain, how Menelik, also called Ǝbnä Ḫakim, came to Aksum with his army, how they built a temple and put Zion, the tablet, there, and how they celebrate her festival every year on Ḫǝdar 21</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.101"><locus from="73v" to="74r"/><title>How Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—parted the Jordan River</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.102"><locus from="74r" to="74v"/><title>About the glory of Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—and how it protected the people of Israel and later saints?</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.103"><locus from="74v"/><title>How the Philistines took Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—and killed Eli‘s sons Afǝnin and Finǝḥäs</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.104"><locus from="74v" to="75r"/><title>How Eli died when he heard the news of the death of his sons and the capture of Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary; and how Zion, the tablet, punished the Philistines and their idols</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.105"><locus from="75r"/><title>How the Philistines discussed in what manner they had to return Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.106"><locus from="75r" to="75v"/><title>How the Philistines sent toward the territory of Israel, with gold, Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.107"><locus from="75v"/><title>How Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—punished the house of Samis, and how Zion dwelt in the house of Aminidab</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.108"><locus from="75v" to="76r"/><title>How King David brought Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—from the house of Aminidab and how Zion punished Ǝoza, and how David put Zion in the house of Abidara, and how, after three months, he brought Zion to his city and placed it in the tabernacle, and how Melǝkol, daughter of Saul, despised David for his dancing</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.109"><locus from="76r" to="76v"/><title>How David tried to build a temple for Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—and how God told him that his son, Solomon, would build the temple, and how David brought material for the temple from Tyre, and how Solomon built the temple</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.110"><locus from="76v" to="77r"/><title>How the various parts and accoutrements of the temple built by Solomon symbolized Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—, the prophets and the apostles</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.111"><locus from="77r"/><title>How Kiram, king of Tyre, helped Solomon to build the temple, and how Solomon put Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—in the holy of holies, and how he blessed the temple, and how God made a covenant with Solomon</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.112"><locus from="77r" to="77v"/><title>How, in Babylon, Ezra saw a vision about Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.113"><locus from="77v"/><title>How Ezra saw that Zion, the tablet—which is a symbol of the Virgin Mary—was glorified by angels and archangels praising Zion</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.114"><locus from="78r"/><title>How the spirit of the Virgin Mary‘s Son prepared the author (Ezra) to praise her</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.115"><locus from="78r"/><title>[Conclusion to the Zion Cycle:] How the spirit of the Virgin Mary‘s Son commanded the author (Ezra) to read out to others the praise of the Virgin</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.116"><locus from="78r" to="79r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary revived the child Saint Fiqǝṭor when the wife of Emperor Diocletian killed him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.117"><locus from="79r" to="79v"/><title>How a Muslim girl converted to Christianity and became a martyr after she recovered a lost belonging by the power of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 46, <locus target="#88v #89r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.118"><locus from="79v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a cup full of the water of life and joy to an Ethiopian pilgrim who was going to Jerusalem</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.119"><locus from="79v" to="80r"/><title>How Jesus Christ cast out a demon from wild animals when the holy family was in Egypt; and how He healed sick people when the holy family was at the place called Qwusqwam</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.120"><locus from="80r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary asked her Son to bless the place called Qwusqwam</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.121"><locus from="80r" to="80v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary asked her son to bless the people who visit the place called Qwusqwam</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.122"><locus from="80v" to="81r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Säräbamon, the Martyr</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.123"><locus from="81r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a garment to Saint Nicolaus who had given his possessions to the poor</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see similar themes in Budge, XL, and Princeton Ethiopic 8, <locus target="#13v #14r #14v #15r #15v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.124"><locus from="81r" to="81v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished a certain woman with leprosy when the woman killed her sister in order to take her husband; and how the earth swallowed her; and how Basil told this story</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.125"><locus from="81v"/><title>How Jesus commanded John, the disciple, to take, by fiery chariots, the body of Saint Mary to paradise under the tree of life</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.126"><locus from="81v" to="82r"/><title>How Matthew, the priest, fled to the monastery to avoid becoming archbishop; how the abbot of the monastery of Saint Anthony sent him back to become archbishop; and how he cut out his own tongue; and how the Virgin Mary appeared to him with instructions for the healing of his tongue by reading her homilies</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 46, <locus target="#138v #139r #139v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.127"><locus from="82r" to="82v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary cut off the hands and feet of a certain man when he insulted her and refused to listen to her pleas</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.128"><locus from="82v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary was revealed to a certain lady from a noble family of Rome when that lady tried to enter the Church of the Holy Sepulcher in Jerusalem; and how the Virgin Mary led her to repentance</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.129"><locus from="82v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary turned the water into sweet, white bread to feed the priests who burned incense to her icon</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.130"><locus from="82v" to="83r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to reassure an ascetic woman about the purity of her friends, other ascetic women in the monastery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 8, <locus target="#19v #20r #20v #21r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 20, <locus target="#5v #6r #31r #75r #75v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.131"><locus from="83r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary raised the saints who died at the monastery of Scete (Asqeṭǝs)</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cp. Budge, XCI; Princeton Ethiopic 20, <locus target="#1r #1v #66r #66v"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#155v #156r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.132"><locus from="83r" to="83v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to the abbot of Scete (Asqeṭǝs) when he was afraid of demons</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.133"><locus from="83v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary anointed the woman of Qwusqwam and how she described to Anthony of Qwusqwam the future glory of that place</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 20, <locus target="#85v #86r #86v"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 46, <locus target="#49v #50r #50v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.134"><locus from="83v" to="84r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary blessed the Monastery of Qwusqwam with its people and animals and how she anointed them again</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see 133 above and the cross references there)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.135"><locus from="84r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Timothy, archbishop of Alexandria, and how she commanded him to build the church</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 46, <locus target="#51v #52r #52v #53r #53v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.136"><locus from="84r" to="84v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain Muslim man, how she rebuked him when he insulted Christians, how he converted to Christianity, how she commanded him to be a witness and how he was martyred for his faith</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#143r #143v #144r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.137"><locus from="84v" to="85r"/><title>How the archangel Gabriel appeared to the Virgin Mary at Bethlehem and told her about her assumption to heaven</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.138"><locus from="85r"/><title>How, because of his devotion, the Virgin Mary saved a bandit leader when the other bandits tried to kill him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.139"><locus from="85r" to="85v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a priest named Yoḥannəs as a woman with wings like a bird</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#97r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 43, <locus target="#13r #13v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.140"><locus from="85v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed the sick deacon who recited her sälam song by anointing him with her breast milk</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 8, <locus target="#2r #2v #3r #3v #4r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#75r #75v #76r #76v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.141"><locus from="85v" to="86r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain bandit from hanging because he always recited her sälam song and how he became a pious monk</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 8, <locus target="#4r #4v #5r #5v #6r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 20, <locus target="#65r #65v #66r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#95r #95v #96r"/>; cp. Budge, XXX)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.142"><locus from="86r" to="86v"/><title>How a certain man slew an evil-living deacon and buried him where he fell and how the Virgin Mary had his body dug up and buried in consecrated ground</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, CIII; Princeton Ethiopic 8, <locus target="#9r #9v #10r #10v"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#80v #81r #81v"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 43, <locus target="#25r #25v #26r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 46, <locus target="#128r #128v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.143"><locus from="86v"/><title>How [Nicodemus,] an evil-living [Persian] knight, became a Christian, but was unable to learn the Lord‘s Prayer, and could only master the Salutation to Mary; and how these words were found written on every leaf of a tree which grew on his grave</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXVIII, Princeton Ethiopic 8, <locus target="#10v #11r #11v #12r #12v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.144"><locus from="86v" to="87r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a garment to a certain bishop and how she commanded him to receive a person who wanted to repent before him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XL and CII; Princeton Ethiopic 8, <locus target="#13v #14r #14v #15r #15v"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#81v #82r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 43, <locus target="#49v #50r #50v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.145"><locus from="87r" to="87v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared a certain deacon who was sick and how she took him into paradise</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton Ethiopic 8, <locus target="#14v #15r #15v #16r #16v #17r #17v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.146"><locus from="87v"/><title>How the scribe [Damianus] used to write the name of the Virgin Mary in gold and colored paints, and how the Virgin appeared to him when dying, and took his soul to Paradise and showed him his name inscribed upon a pillar of gold</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, IV; Princeton Ethiopic 20, <locus target="#43r #43v #44r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#55v #56r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 46, <locus target="#11v #12r #12v"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 47, <locus target="#22r #22v #23r #23v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.147"><locus from="87v" to="88r"/><title>How a certain Ishmaelite was converted when he saw oil and milk flowing from the breasts of a picture of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LXI, Princeton Ethiopic 20, <locus target="#73r #73v"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 41, <locus target="#92r #92v #93r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic 43, <locus target="#17r #17v #18r #18v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.148"><locus from="88r" to="88v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary, in Bethlehem, blessed a certain government official and how she healed his son</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.149"><locus from="88v" to="89r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary raised up a dead knight who had been buried in the cemetery of a convent, to fight an enemy of the church called Golǝyad (Goliath), and how the knight fought against him and slew him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LX; Princeton Ethiopic 20, <locus target="#73v #74r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.150"><locus from="89r" to="90v"/><title>How, when the people of Damot worked on the day of Mary‘s festival, the Virgin Mary uprooted a tree that they worshipped, and how when the people tried to cut up the tree, the Virgin Mary raised the tree upright again and how Zärǝ‗a Ya‗ǝqob, king of Ethiopia built a church at that place</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(See <locus target="#69v #70r #70v"/> in this manuscript, and TM89 88–94)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.151"><locus from="90v" to="91v"/><title>How the light descended into the Emperor‘s city when the Emperor killed a certain group of monks who refused to bow down for Mary and the cross</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 94–8)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.152"><locus from="91v" to="92v"/><title>How the light remained in the Emperor‘s city until a monk appointed by the Emperor arrived</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 98–101) These two miracles are understood to be in reference to the Estifanosite movement. See Getatchew, Däqiqa Ǝsṭifanos Bäḥǝg Amlak, Collegeville, MN, 1996; The Gǝ‗ǝz Acts of Abba Ǝsṭifanos of Gwǝndagwǝnde, CSCO 619/620; SA 110/111 (2006); "Religious Controversies and the growth of Ethiopic Literature in the Fourteenth and Fifteenth centuries," Orient Christianus 65 (1981) 102–136; ―The Cause of the Ǝsṭifanosites: A Fundamentalist Sect in the Church of Ethiopia‖ Paideuma 29 (1983) 93–119</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.153"><locus from="92v" to="93r"/><title>How a light descended upon the Ethiopian traveler during the Easter celebration in Jerusalem when the other communities rejected him and cast him out of the Church of the Holy Sepulcher because he was black</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 101–4)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.154"><locus from="93r" to="93v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished a wealthy man when he insulted a priest who only knew how to recite the Anaphora of Our Lady</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 104–6; cp. Budge, CII)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.155"><locus from="93v" to="94v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary warned the people of a certain city when they put their wealth inside the church, and how she burned down the church with lightning, while protecting the priests as they celebrated the Mass</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 106–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.156"><locus from="94v" to="95r"/><title>How Our Lord descended from Heaven and how He honored the Virgin Mary before the Apostles</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 109–110)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.157"><locus from="95r" to="95v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished those who denied the doctrine of the millennial feast of Mount Zion during the reign of Zärǝ‗a Ya‗ǝqob</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 110–4)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.158"><locus from="95v" to="97r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary helped the priest of a certain church when a Muslim warrior tried to burn down the church</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 114–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.159"><locus from="97r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary performed a miracle through the icon of the city of Ṣedenǝya when a certain merchants tried to cut a piece from the icon and blood flowed out</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM 89, 119–20)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.160"><locus from="97r" to="97v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a harlot from stoning by the people of a certain city</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM 89 121)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.161"><locus from="97v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary provided food for a monastery when a young helper of the monks he prayed to her</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM 89 122)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.162"><locus from="97v" to="98r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary protected a monk from the temptations of the devil</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 122–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.163"><locus from="98r" to="98v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished a certain man when he attacked a priest and a deacon from the monastery of Fiqǝṭor</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 124–6; cp. Princeton 41, <locus target="#136v #137r #137v #138r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.164"><locus from="98v" to="99r"/><title>How our Lord Jesus Christ appeared with His Mother and Saints Michael and Gabriel to a certain man named Pifamon during his martyrdom</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 126–8; Princeton 43, <locus target="#55v #56r #56v #57r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.165"><locus from="99r" to="100r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain woman named Tekǝla, sister of Abba Asi</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM 89, 128–32)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.166"><locus from="100r" to="100v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared in Däbrä Qwusqwam when Bishop Gabriel stayed there and died during the celebration of the passion week</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 132–4)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.167"><locus from="100v" to="101r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished a certain Muslim when he attacked the abbot of Däbrä Qwusqwam and when Qozǝmos Yoḥannǝs prayed</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 134–6)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.168"><locus from="101r" to="101v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain deacon Yoḥannǝs as a pillar of light</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 136–9; Princeton 20, <locus target="#68r #68v #69r #69v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#153r #153v #154r"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#86v #87r #87v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.169"><locus from="101v" to="102r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary brought water to the well of the monastery of Däbrä Mǝṭmaq</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 139–141; Princeton 20, <locus target="#66r #66v #67r #67v #68r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#154r #154v #155r #155v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.170"><locus from="102r" to="102v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a prince‘s son named Bätergela Maryam</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 141–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.171"><locus from="102v" to="103r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary prayed to God that He would reveal his Trinity to a certain man named eṭros</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 143–5; Princeton 46, <locus target="#104v #105r #105v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.172"><locus from="103r" to="104r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain man called Silan to warn him about the money he had lent to Filipos and how she led him to righteous life</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 145–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.173"><locus from="104r" to="105v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Abraham, Archbishop of Alexandria when he was challenged by a Jew and Muslims to move a mountain, how she led them to Simon, the shoemaker, and how he moved the mountain</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 150–4)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.174"><locus from="105v" to="106v"/><title>How a certain woman named Sophia received a candle in her dream when her husband forbade her to go to the church, and how she found the candle in her hand when she awoke</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 154–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.175"><locus from="106v" to="107r"/><title>How when bishop Nestorius commanded the people to spit on the menstrual blood of a woman in the church, John Chrysostom kissed her instead and the icon in the church called him ―golden mouth‖</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 159–161)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.176"><locus from="107r"/><title>How Jesus asked Mary about her five lamentations</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 161–2; Princeton 46, <locus target="#102v"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#102v #103r #103v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.177"><locus from="107r" to="108r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished a certain Jew when he challenged a monk who converted from Judaism</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 162–5; cp. Princeton 46, <locus target="#152v #153r #153v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.178"><locus from="108r" to="108v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary commanded the devil to be a servant for the monastery; and how the pagans converted to Christianity when they saw the devil acting as servant for the monastery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 165–8)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.179"><locus from="108v" to="109v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain deacon when he went to a certain woman to give her holy communion and when the priest who loved money refused to go</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 168–71)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.180"><locus from="109v" to="110v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed a certain monk when he was bitten by a snake and how he and his friends served the Virgin Mary until they died in martyrdom</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 171–5)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.181"><locus from="110v" to="111r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary took a certain abbot with her into heaven when the people accused him and how she punished them like Dothan and Abiram (i.e., the earth swallowed them)</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 176–7)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.182"><locus from="111r" to="111v"/><title>How a certain harlot swore falsely about her pregnancy by the name of saint Mary at which moment the harlot delivered two cows horns and two sheep horns from her womb and how she lost her mind and died</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 176–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.183"><locus from="111v" to="113r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain monk named Giyorgis and how she gave to him the cup of knowledge when he was rejected by his teacher due to a lack of money</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 179–83)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.184"><locus from="113r" to="113v"/><title>How the Ark of the Virgin Mary performed a set of miracles in the palace of a certain king: the ark came out of the box without aid, it turned the tents of the king from white to black and it punished wicked priests</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 183–6)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.185"><locus from="113v" to="114v"/><title>How a certain priest was carried away by the angel of God out of the gate of the Virgin Mary church when he was sleeping and had a nocturnal emission</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 186–8)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.186"><locus from="114v" to="115r"/><title>How the angel of God punished a certain man with hemorrhage when he entered into the Virgin Mary Church after he had committed adultery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 189–90)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.187"><locus from="115r"/><title>How the ark of the Virgin Mary fell into the hands of an army of unbelievers and how the Virgin Mary punished a certain man when he sat down on the ark by cutting him into two pieces</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 190–1)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.188"><locus from="115r" to="116r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to those who were trying to steal the holy articles from the church; how she punished the thieves when they did not listen; how she appeared to the governor of that land and how she led him to the thieves; and how the thieves were thrown into prison</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 191–4)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.189"><locus from="116r" to="116v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain man named Alexander the Jew after he was swallowed by a serpent for three days and three nights and how she led him to the Jordan River to wash him and heal him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 194–6; Princeton 41, <locus target="#87v #88r"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#23v #24r #24v #25r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.190"><locus from="116v" to="117v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary enabled a man to slay a serpent nearly one hundred feet in length and thirty-three feet in diameter, how the man took from the brain of the serpent a pearl of great price, which he placed in a martyrium of Mary that he built at Sidon</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LIII; TM89 196–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.191"><locus from="117v" to="118r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain monk after had become depressed concerning a nocturnal emission and how she comforted him and gave him a sign of assurance in his hand</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 199–202)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.192"><locus from="118r" to="119r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a child to a certain couple and how they turned aside from their promise to raise him for the service of God; how he became very sick on his wedding day and the Virgin Mary appeared to him, comforted him and sent him to a monastery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 202–5)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.193"><locus from="119r" to="120r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain priest; how she commanded him to go to Gäbrä Krestos [known as Alexis in the West], son of Theodotius, king of Constantinople; when Gäbrä Krestos lived among the beggars for fifteen years</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 205–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.194"><locus from="120r" to="120v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain Jew when his father threw him into the fire because of his conversion to Christianity</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LIX; TM89 209–11; Princeton 20, <locus target="#37r #37v #38r #38v #39r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.195"><locus from="120v" to="121r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain priest to go to Abǝdäl Mäsih [Arabic form of Gäbrä Krestos], son of the king of Constantinople; and how she commanded the priest to bring him back to the church to live there</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 211–3; see miracle 193 above and the references there)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.196"><locus from="121r"/><title>How the icon of the Virgin Mary appeared in a beehive when a certain beekeeper, commanded by a sorcerer to multiply his beehive, brought the elements from holy communion to put in his beehive</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, CVII; TM89 215–7)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.197"><locus from="121r" to="122v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished a certain young man when he revealed the whereabouts of the hiding place of the Holy Family in Egypt; and how she heard the prayer of the governor of that land who interceded for the young man</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 218–22)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.198"><locus from="122v" to="123r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave water to a thirsty dog with her shoe</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXIII; TM89 217–8; Strelcyn 32.16. 32; Princeton 20, <locus target="#83r #83v #84r"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#92v #93r"/>; Princeton 56, <locus target="#150r #150v #151r #151v #152r #152v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.199"><locus from="123r" to="123v"/><title>How, when she was fleeing from Herod, the Virgin Mary visited a certain king when he sent a message to her to bless him and his people</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 222–5; Princeton 41, <locus target="#44v #45r #45v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.200"><locus from="123v" to="124r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave birth to Jesus while she was in Judea; how the midwife Salome burned her hand when she touched the body of the Virgin; and how her hand healed when she touched the body of the infant Jesus</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 225–7; cp. the miracle associated with Salome glorifying Jesus at his birth, Princeton 23, <locus target="#36r #36v #37r #37v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#179r #179v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#57v #58r"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#20r #20v #21r #21v #22r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.201"><locus from="124r" to="125r"/><title>How a certain woman promised herself to live as a virgin for Saint Mary; how she committed adultery with many men, how she repented on her deathbed; how her tears and her sin were put on a scale and the tears outweighed the sin; how the Virgin Mary commanded Saint Michael to baptize her and put her with other virgins</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 227–31; cf. Budge, LXXI and miracle 74 above)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.202"><locus from="125r" to="125v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary helped two monks when they prayed on behalf of a certain man who had lost his mind when he made a covenant with Satan to protect his cattle</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 231–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.203"><locus from="125v" to="126r"/><title>How a certain rich man called Paqlima hurled a loaf at the head of a beggar and wounded him, and how the Virgin Mary delivered his soul from demons</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LXXXVI; TM89 233–4; Princeton 20, <locus target="#54r #54v #55r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.204"><locus from="126r" to="126v"/><title>How a certain Jew of Constantinople threw into the water [to the ground a picture of the Virgin Mary and when it was restored it exuded oil that healed many</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LXV; cp. Budge, LXI and LXVIII; TM89 237–8; Princeton 20, <locus target="#78r #78v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.205"><locus from="126v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary protected an adulterous deacon from his attackers until he had confessed his sin to the priest; and how she directed the bishop to bury his body among the faithful</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 238–9; cp. Budge, CIII, "How the Virgin Mary commanded a deacon to dig up and rebury in consecrated ground the body of an adulterous deacon from the island of Jericho in the city of Gärisat who was killed by the people;" cp. also Princeton 8, <locus target="#9r #9v #10r #10v"/>; Princeton 40, <locus target="#80v #81r #81v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#25r #25v #26r"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#128r #128v"/>, which all follow Budge, CIII)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.206"><locus from="126v" to="127r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary carried a sick monk from the Monastery of the Pilgrims [Budge, has "Beggars"] to Palestine, and showed him Jerusalem and Bethlehem, and bathed him in the waters of the Jordan</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, IX; TM89 239–40; Princeton 20, <locus target="#47r #47v #48r"/>; Princeton 23, <locus target="#29v #30r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#58v #59r"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#30r #30v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#15v #16r"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#35v #36r #36v #37r #37v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.207"><locus from="127r" to="127v"/><title>How Sybil the prophetess saw a vision of the Virgin Mary holding her child within a circle around the sun and revealed this vision to a king who refused to be worshipped</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 241–2; Princeton 8, <locus target="#6r #6v #7r #7v #8r #8v"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#39r #39v #40r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#37v #38r #38v #39r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.208"><locus from="127v" to="128v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the servant of a certain king when a co-worker accused him falsely; and how she caused the co-worker to be executed instead of the innocent man</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 243–7)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.209"><locus from="128v" to="129r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed a certain man named Ṭiras who had became a deaf mute</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 247–8)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.210"><locus from="129r"/><title>How a monk [named in this manuscript Gärdan] who had defiled himself mutilated himself and died under the influence of Satan; how Satan tried to carry off his soul to Sheol; and how the Virgin Mary obtained forgiveness for him, and restored life to his body</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, CI; TM89 248–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.211"><locus from="129r" to="130r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain woman from a knight who wanted to marry her and how she became a nun; how the knight repented from his sins and how, when he died, a tree sprang from him tomb; and how the icon of the Virgin was on every leaf of the tree</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 250–3; compare Budge, XXXVIII and Princeton 8, <locus target="#10v #11r #11v #12r #12v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#85r #85v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#22v #23r #23v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.212"><locus from="130v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a young Jew of Tyre from the fiery furnace into which his father had cast him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XLIV; TM89 209–11; compare with Budge, LIX; Princeton 20, <locus target="#37r #37v #38r #38v #39r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.213"><locus from="130v" to="131r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary protected a woman, great with child, who was overtaken by an inrush of the sea, and how the woman brought forth her child and escaped from drowning</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXII; TM89 255–6; Princeton 20, <locus target="#82v #83r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#83r #83v #84r"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#31v #32r #32v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.214"><locus from="131r" to="131v"/><title>How a certain woman whose husband had left her for another woman begged the Virgin Mary to kill the other woman; and how the Virgin Mary brought the other woman, who was devoted in worship of the Virgin, to repentance</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 256–8)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.215"><locus from="131v" to="132r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary delivered a thief, the son of a poor widow</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXX; TM89 259–260; Princeton 47, <locus target="#88v #89r #89v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.216"><locus from="132r" to="133r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary became a guarantor on a loan from a certain Jew to a certain knight; how she delivered the money when the knight prayed to the Virgin Mary; and how the icon of the Virgin Mary testified when the Jew denied having received his money</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XLVII; TM89 261–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.217"><locus from="133r" to="133v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to the son of a king and asked him to remain celibate; how his father, the king, wanted him to marry a woman; and how the son died on his wedding day; and how the Virgin Mary received his soul and took it to heaven</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 264–7)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.218"><locus from="133v" to="134v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain king when he repented of his sin and how she told him that God received his repentance</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 267–71)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.219"><locus from="134v" to="135r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain priest named Askänafǝr who was sad over his lack of church education and how she told him that she found him more blessed than educated ones</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 271–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.220"><locus from="135r" to="135v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain pilgrim when he was travelling to Jerusalem; how she showed him a river of milk when he was exhausted from the heat of the sun; and how he arrived in Jerusalem in peace</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 273–4)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.221"><locus from="135v" to="136r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished a certain treasurer of the church who disobeyed the monks and the bishop and how he died</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 274–6)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.222"><locus from="136r" to="136v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain monk when a demon tried to drown him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 276–8; cf. Budge, LXIX and Princeton, 20, <locus target="#27r #27v #28r #28v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.223"><locus from="136v" to="137r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain blind teacher when his students pushed him from a cliff and how she punished those students</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 278–81)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.224"><locus from="137v" to="138r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary with her mother, Anna, and Elsabet, mother of John the Baptist, appeared to Tawkǝlǝya and how the Virgin Mary told her of her martyrdom along with her husband, Yosǝṭos, and her son, Aboli</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 281–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.225"><locus from="138r" to="139r"/><title>How King Marqos became the king of Rome and was pressed to marry, how he left his palace and went to church to pray before the Icon of Mary and how he entered the monastery of Tormaq</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 284–7; Princeton 8, <locus target="#34r #34v #35r #35v"/>). The scribe has marked with red and black dotted lines a section on <locus target="#138v"> f. 138v, columns 1 and 2</locus>, which were copied erroneously</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.226"><locus from="139r" to="143v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Archbishop Tewofǝlos of Alexandria and told him about the events surrounding Jesus‘ birth and the flight of the Holy Family into Egypt</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM 89 287–303; Princeton 41, <locus target="#21r #21v #22r #22v #23r #23v #24r #24v #25r #25v #26r #26v #27r #27v #28r #28v #29r #29v #30r"/> and <locus target="#113r #113v #114r #114v #115r #115v"/>; cf. Princeton 41, <locus target="#146r #146v #147r #147v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.227"><locus from="143v" to="144r"/><title>How King Herod ordered the murder of the children [of Bethlehem]; how the angel of God appeared to Joseph to take the holy family to Egypt; and how the Sycamore tree opened itself and hid the holy family when they were threatened by bandits</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 41, ff. 39v–42v)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.228"><locus from="144r" to="145r"/><title>How, when fleeing to Egypt, the Virgin Mary asked water of a wealthy woman; how the woman insulted her; how the servant of this woman threw the infant Jesus to the ground; how the wealthy woman descended to Sheol and how her family turned into wild animals</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. the next miracle)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.229"><locus from="145r" to="145v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary cursed the people of a certain city in Egypt, while the Holy Family was there, when they treated her with disdain and how the city was swallowed by the ground</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 41, <locus target="#42v #43r #43v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.230"><locus from="145v" to="146r"/><title>How, when the holy family fled to Egypt; how Jesus brought forth water from under the feet of the Virgin Mary; and how the Virgin Mary healed the daughter of bandits</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 41, <locus target="#45v #46r #46v #47r #47v #48r"/>, How the Holy Family visited Egypt and blessed Asqeṭəs and how Jesus caused water to well up from the ground using Joseph‘s rod)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.231"><locus from="146r" to="146v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the robber‘s soul from judgment because he drank from water that sprang from her feet</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 20, <locus target="#5r #5v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.232"><locus from="146v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed a certain man who had been sick for forty-seven years</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.233"><locus from="147r" to="147v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed a certain man with a foot of stone</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXII (has lame foot); Princeton 20, <locus target="#63r #63v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#70r #70v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#24r #24v"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#67v #68r #68v #69r #69v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.234"><locus from="147v" to="148r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a Jeweler to forbid him from making an icon for certain arrogant people; and how she showed an icon of her which had been made by the angels to Abba Basiliyos</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 46, <locus target="#55v #56r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.235"><locus from="148r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the drunken monk from a lion</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(See Budge, XXXVII and XLVIII which include an incident with a savage dog as well; Princeton 8, <locus target="#21r #21v #22r"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#9r #9v"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#87r #87v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#98v #99r #99v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#15v #16r #16v #17r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.236"><locus from="148r" to="148v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary helped a sick monk, who had left the monastery without the permission of the abbot, to repent and to receive holy communion before he died</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 20, <locus target="#89r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.237"><locus from="148v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a wise monk who had criticized his fellow monks about the fish they were eating and how she chided him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.238"><locus from="148v" to="149r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary received the gift of a certain woman who was forbidden to fast by her husband</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Budge, XCIX; Princeton 20, <locus target="#6r #6v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#58r #58v #59r #59v #60r #60v #61r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.239"><locus from="149r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary rescued from the clutches of the Devil the soul of a libertine monk who was crossing a stream one night to visit a paramour</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LXIX; Princeton 20, <locus target="#27r #27v #28r #28v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.240"><locus from="149r" to="149v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain sick man and commanded him to stay at the gate of the church during her fasting season and how she healed him on the feast day of her assumption to heaven</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.241"><locus from="149v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary made a stream to reverse its course and water to run uphill in order to assist a poor man</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXVI; Princeton 41, <locus target="#54r"/>; Princeton 8, <locus target="#43r #43v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.242"><locus from="149v" to="150r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary commanded [Budge says "taught"] the Syrian potter [Ephrem] to learn by heart and to recite the weekly service of her Book of Praise</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXV; Princeton 8, <locus target="#30r #30v #31r #31v #32r #32v #33r #33v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#77r #77v #78r #78v #79r"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#40r #40v #41r #41v #42r #42v #43r"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#47r #47v #48r #48v"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#103v #104r #104v #105r #105v #106r #106v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.243"><locus from="150r" to="151r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the cupbearer of a king who was accused by his fellow and how the accuser received the judgment which was planned for the cupbearer</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 40, <locus target="#163r #163v #164r"/>; cf. miracle 208 above)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.244"><locus from="151r" to="151v"/><title>How the Afrənəgawi [European man] took the gate lock from the Church of Bethlehem and how the Virgin Mary revealed her power when the Afärəngi was strangled by it</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 41, <locus target="#141r #141v #142r #142v #143r #143v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245"><locus from="151v" to="154r"/><title>The Cycle of the Vision of John, Son of Thunder</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.1"><locus from="151v" to="152r"/><title>how the Virgin Mary appeared as a lady with twelve stars in her crown</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.2"><locus from="152r"/><title>how the Virgin Mary was glorified by all creation</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.3"><locus from="152r" to="152v"/><title>how the glory of the Virgin Mary was preordained before the creation of heaven and earth</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.4"><locus from="152v"/><title>how the Virgin Mary appeared when the whole world was in darkness</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.6"><locus from="152v" to="153r"/><title>how the Virgin Mary was given great wings</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.7"><locus from="153r"/><title>how the Virgin Mary is pure in her mind and in her body</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.8"><locus from="153r" to="153v"/><title>how the Virgin Mary is a perpetual virgin</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.9"><locus from="153v"/><title>how King Solomon prophesied about her virginity</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.10"><locus from="153v"/><title>how the apostles taught their synod about the virginity of Saint Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.245.11"><locus from="153v" to="154r"/><title>how the Virgin Mary is praised by all creation</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
              </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.246"><locus from="154r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary made a garment for a devoted bishop and how, when the bishop refused to accept the repentance of a sinner, she revealed herself to the sinner and told him to go tell the bishop that he was wearing her garment</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Budge, XL; Princeton 8, <locus target="#13v #14r #14v #15r #15v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.247"><locus from="154r" to="154v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain wealthy man as great bird on a pillar of light</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 46, <locus target="#41r #41v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.248"><locus from="154v" to="155r"/><title>How Saint Paul saw the glory of the Virgin Mary when he went to the third heaven</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.249"><locus from="155r" to="155v"/><title>How the angels appeared to Abba Mardäri and how they praised the Virgin Mary with him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.250"><locus from="155v" to="156r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Abba Bǝḥor, disciple of Amoni</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 46, <locus target="#42v #43r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.251"><locus from="156r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Säwla, wife of Giyorgis, the new martyr after he had endured his martyrdom</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.252"><locus from="156r" to="156v"/><title>How the holy family stayed in a place near to the Jordan River and how Jesus and his mother, the Virgin Mary, blessed that place</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.253"><locus from="156v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary revealed a vision of the departed saints of the monastery of Asqeṭǝs to the monks who were praying there</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 41, <locus target="#155v #156r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.254"><locus from="156v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a devoted monk from the deceptions of Satan</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.255"><locus from="156v" to="157r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain priest from Satan‘s temptation</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.256"><locus from="157r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved from a lion a certain laundryman of a king</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.257"><locus from="157r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a garment to a devoted monk</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XC; cf. Budge, XL; Princeton 47, <locus target="#93r #93v #94r"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#84r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.258"><locus from="157r" to="157v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a male child to a certain barren woman and how on his wedding day he refused to sleep with his bride; how the Virgin Mary anointed him with fragrance and he went to his bride</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.259"><locus from="157v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain governor when the king wrongly accused him and tried to kill him with the sword</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 20, <locus target="#31 #32r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#88v #89r"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#20v #21r #21v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.260"><locus from="157v" to="158r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary protected a certain virgin when a nobleman took her by force to be his wife</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.261"><locus from="158r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a fisherman when a great sea serpent swallowed him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. TM 89 194)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.262"><locus from="158r" to="158v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary took to safety the Abbott of the monastery when the monks wrongly accused him of adultery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.263"><locus from="158v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary interceded on behalf of a certain sinner when God ordered the angels to put his soul in hell; and how the tears of the Virgin Mary washed the sin away</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.264"><locus from="158v" to="159r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary sent priests to a certain man when he prayed to receive holy communion</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.265"><locus from="159r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the drunken monk from a lion and a savage dog</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 235 above; Budge, XXXVII and XLVIIIl; cf. Princeton 8, <locus target="#21r #21v #22r"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#9r #9v"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#87r #87v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#98v #99r #99v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#15v #16r #16v #17r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.266"><locus from="159r" to="159v"/><title>How the painted figures of the Virgin Mary and Christ on an icon bled when a Jew cast the board into a pit, and how the magistrate had the Jew burnt alive</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LXVIII; Princeton 20, <locus target="#29v #30r #30v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.267"><locus from="159v"/><title>How a certain woman consigned to the Devil the son whom, against her desire, she conceived on Good Friday, and how the Virgin Mary rescued the young man from the clutches of the Devil</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XLIX which has the day of conception as Easter Eve; Princeton 20, <locus target="#35v #36r #36v #37r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.268"><locus from="159v" to="160r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave food to a certain poor beggar to be able to share with a guest</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.269"><locus from="160r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed the son of a certain Roman governor while she was at Bethlehem and how she blessed him and his family and how he returned to Rome in peace</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.270"><locus from="160r" to="160v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary, with other apostles, appeared to John Chrysostom and encouraged him in the exercise of the office of the keys</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.271"><locus from="160v"/><title>How the angels protected the house of the Virgin Mary in Bethlehem when the Jews tried to burn it down</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 46, <locus target="#53v #54r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.272"><locus from="160v" to="161r"/><title>How a certain man wished to build a martyrium to the Virgin Mary but lacked the necessary money and how she showed him in a dream where a pot of gold coins was to be found</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LXXXVIII)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.273"><locus from="161r"/><title>How the icon of the Virgin Mary wept for the sins of this world and how the icon spoke to a child to hide this from anyone and how the child followed the Blessed Virgin in a holy life of celibacy</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XCII)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.274"><locus from="161r"/><title>How a certain man used to put fifty roses on the icon of the Virgin Mary and how, when roses were out of season he would recite fifty Hail Mary‘s instead; and how fifty roses sprang from his grave three months after he died with their roots springing from his heart</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Budge, X and Princeton 8, <locus target="#39r #39v #40r #40v #41r"/>; Princeton 23, <locus target="#31r #31v #32r #32v #33r #33v #34r #34v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#59r #59v #60r #60v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#30v #31r #31v #32r #32v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#16r #16v #17r"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#39r #39v #40r #40v #41r #41v #42r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.275"><locus from="161r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary, because of his devotion, protected a thief who was stealing from the church</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.276"><locus from="161r" to="161v"/><title>How the icon of the Virgin Mary spoke to a certain woman whose mother-in-law was opposed to her devotion to the icon of the Virgin and how the icon disappeared because of the mother-in-law‘s objection</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 20, <locus target="#52v #53r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#75r #75v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.277"><locus from="161v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary made a stream to reverse its course and water to run uphill in order to assist a poor man</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 241 above; Budge, XXXVI; Princeton 41, <locus target="#54r"/>; Princeton 8, <locus target="#43r #43v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.278"><locus from="161v"/><title>How Jesus Christ appeared with his Mother to the apostles; how he appointed Peter to be the father of the people of Israel</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 109–10)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.279"><locus from="161v" to="162v"/><title>How a certain Ethiopian monk named Qälemǝnṭos went to lower Egypt to a city called Säbǝṭ in order to make a pilgrimage to Jerusalem; how he stayed in the house of the mother of Yoḥannǝs, a lady who was known for her love of pilgrims; how her house was filled with light when he was reading from the miracles of Mary and how the lady decided to follow the monk to Jerusalem</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 41, <locus target="#139r #139v #140r #140v #141r"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#129v #130r #130v #131r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.280"><locus from="162v"/><title>How a certain lady of Roman nobility tried to enter into the tomb of Jesus Christ in Jerusalem; how she was forbidden to enter because of her unbelief and how she came to faith, received holy communion and entered into the tomb to receive a blessing</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Budge, XXXIX; Princeton 43, <locus target="#57r #57v #58r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.281"><locus from="162v" to="163r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary and her son, Jesus Christ, with the Apostles and archangels, blessed a certain church near to the Jordon River</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 252 above)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.282"><locus from="163r"/><title>How the Holy Spirit taught about the honor of the day Sunday and how Jesus Christ appeared in honor of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 46, <locus target="#54r #54v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.283"><locus from="163r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a garment to a devoted monk</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(See miracles 41 and 257 above; Budge, XC; cf. Budge, XL; Princeton 20, <locus target="#84r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#81v #82r"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#93r #93v #94r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.284"><locus from="163r" to="163v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain wealthy lady from Syria from the pain of childbirth</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 23, <locus target="#34v #35r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#72v"/> which identifies the woman as from Caesarea)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.285"><locus from="163v"/><title>How the Church of the Virgin Mary in Jerusalem at the gate of Mount Olives will serve as a ship [like the ark of Noah] at the time of the second coming of Jesus Christ</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.286"><locus from="163v" to="164r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a drunken monk named Matewos from a lion and a savage dog</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracles 55 and 235 above; and Budge, XXXVII and XLVIII; Princeton 8, <locus target="#21r #21v #22r"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#9r #9v"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#87r #87v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#98v #99r #99v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#15v #16r #16v #17r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.287"><locus from="164r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary punished Nǝsṭur [Nestorius] who had insulted her</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.288"><locus from="164r" to="164v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the people on a certain ship on the sea when they were caught in a powerful storm</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 20, <locus target="#57v #58r #58v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.289"><locus from="164v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a wealthy woman at a monastery while the monks were in prayer</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 8, <locus target="#45v #46r #46v"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#25v #26r #26v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.290"><locus from="164v" to="165r"/><title>How a certain Roman prefect was prevented by a Ram from entering the Tomb of our Lord, and how he was not able to go in until he had become a follower of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXIX; Princeton 43, <locus target="#57r #57v #58r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.291"><locus from="165r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Abba Bärsuma as a white dove</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.292"><locus from="165r" to="165v"/><title>How Jesus Christ carried the body of the Virgin Mary to heaven on the day of her assumption and how he gave her a covenant</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Synaxarium entry for the sixteen day of Yäkatit)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.293"><locus from="165v" to="166r"/><title>How Emperor Tiberius sent a letter to our Lord Jesus Christ with the body of his son and how his son was raised from the dead when they put him in the tomb of Jesus and how the Emperor and Empress tried to bring our Lady Mary to the palace in Rome</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. a similar account in Gäbrä Haymamat)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.294"><locus from="166r" to="167r"/><title>How Jesus Christ commanded John to go to Emperor Tiberius; how Tiberius asked John to make an icon like the one he had seen on the day of the crucifixion of Jesus; how John made the icon and when he finished how John kissed the icon for several hours and how the icon called John "my beloved"</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. a similar account in Gäbrä Haymamat)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.295"><locus from="167r"/><title>How Jesus Christ commanded John the Apostle to carry the body of the Virgin Mary in a heavenly chariot and how the angels received the body of Mary with incense and praise</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 46, <locus target="#65r #65v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.296"><locus from="167r" to="167v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary was exalted more than the angels and how the One born from the Virgin Mary saved the world</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 46, <locus target="#64v #65r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.297"><locus from="167v" to="168v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary took the position from a certain abbot who had forbidden the praise of Mary among the monks; and how the Ethiopians and Copts received the light at Jerusalem and they were singing and dancing during the Easter celebration with the line "for us who believe in your resurrection, send us your light"</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. TM89 101–4)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.298"><locus from="168v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary returned a child to a certain woman when the child was taken by a hyena and the mother went to the local church, took an icon of Jesus and said, "I will return your son, when you return my son."</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.299"><locus from="168v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a garment and food to a poor, devoted monk</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracles 41 and 257 above; Budge, XC; cf. Budge, XL; Princeton 20, <locus target="#84r"/>; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, <locus target="#81v #82r"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#93r #93v #94r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.300"><locus from="168v" to="169v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed the hand of Atenatewos, a converted Muslim, who had became a priest, after he cut off his hand because a woman had kissed it during the celebration of the Eucharist</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 319–21; cf., Budge, V; Princeton 41, <locus target="#55r #55v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.301"><locus from="169v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed a certain sinful woman when she swallowed a scorpion because she was depressed about her sin and how a voice from the icon led her to a certain priest for repentance and healing; and how she gave birth to forty scorpions when she had completed her repentance</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 330–2; Princeton 20, <locus target="#57r #57v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.302"><locus from="170r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed a sick deacon by anointing him with her breast milk</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 41, <locus target="#75r #75v #76r #76v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.303"><locus from="170r" to="170v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared at the time of prayer for a certain wealthy woman who was a patron for a certain monastery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 8, <locus target="#45v #46r #46v"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#25v #26r #26v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.304"><locus from="170v"/><title>How, because of his devotion to her, the Virgin Mary saved the soul of a wicked monastic leader from hell when he died; and how he appeared to his disciple in a dream and told him how the Virgin Mary saved him from damnation</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 20, <locus target="#62v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.305"><locus from="170v" to="171r"/><title>How a certain Muslim was converted when he saw oil and Myron exuded from the breast of icon of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 48 above; Budge, 61; Princeton 41, <locus target="#92r #92v #93r"/>; Princeton , <locus target="#17r #17v #18r #18v"/>; cf. Budge, LXV and LXVIII)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.306"><locus from="171r" to="171v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed an elderly priest of Alexandria when he fell and broke his back during the church service because of his old age</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, III, which identifies the man as an elderly Jew of Akəmim; Princeton 20, <locus target="#42r #42v #43r"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#8v #9r #9v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#11r #11v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.307"><locus from="171v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary spoke from her picture to a devout worshipper and said to him, ―Blessed art thou among men‖</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, II; Princeton 20, <locus target="#41v #42r"/>; Princeton 23, <locus target="#28v #29r #29v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#54v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#8r #8v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#10v #11r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.308"><locus from="171v" to="172r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary received the soul of a sick and devout monk who was unable to go to church and how she took his soul to Paradise</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Budge, XXVII; Princeton 20, <locus target="#81r #81v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#84r #84v #85r"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#6v #7r #7v #8r"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#50v #51r #51v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#27v #28r"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#80v #81r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.309"><locus from="172r" to="172v"/><title>How the icon of the Virgin Mary helped a young impoverished man and how the church keeper saw this miracle and how he gave his daughter to the young man in marriage</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 20, <locus target="#25r"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#72r #72v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#93r #93v #94r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.310"><locus from="172v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to reassure an ascetic woman about the purity of her friends, other ascetic women held with her in prison</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 8, <locus target="#19v #20r #20v #21r"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#5v #6r #31r #75r #75v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.311"><locus from="172v" to="173r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary received the gift of gold from a certain woman when the woman was forbidden by her husband to fast</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 238 above and cf. Budge, XCIX; Princeton 20, <locus target="#6r #6v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#58r #58v #59r #59v #60r #60v #61r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.312"><locus from="173r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary delivered from devils the soul of a scribe who was engaged in writing a copy of the Book of her Miracles. This scribe had a brother who had sinned, but not knowing him they seized the innocent man and tried to carry him off to hell</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XVIII; Princeton 20, <locus target="#51v #52r #52v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#66v #67r #67v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#21v #22r"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#58r #58v #59r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.313"><locus from="173r" to="173v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary revealed a vision of the departed saints of the monastery of Asqeṭǝs, among them Abba Mäqars, Abba Yoḥannǝs, Abba Bǝsoy, Abba Muse, Abba Yoḥannǝs Käma, to the monks who were praying there</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 253 above and Princeton 41, <locus target="#155v #156r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.314"><locus from="173v"/><title>How; during the reign of Gabriel the eighty-eighth Archbishop of Alexandria, the Virgin Mary punished a certain man who insulted the icon of the Virgin; and how the icon spoke to the abbot when he interceded for the man</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.315"><locus from="174r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary received the soul of the king of Constantinople who was a devout follower of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.316"><locus from="174r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain nun who died before she finished her penitence and how she appeared to the Abbess and told her how the Virgin Mary saved her</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 20, <locus target="#28r #28v #29r #29v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.317"><locus from="174r" to="174v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the people on a certain ship on the sea when they were caught in a powerful storm and they cried out to her</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 20, <locus target="#57v #58r #58v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.318"><locus from="174v" to="175r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain man from drowning when the ship was sinking</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 41, <locus target="#99v #100r #100v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.319"><locus from="175r"/><title>How the monk Ḫǝrdaw had defiled himself, mutilated himself and died under the influence of Satan; how Satan tried to carry off his soul to Sheol; and how the Virgin Mary obtained forgiveness for him and restored life to his body</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, CI; Princeton 20, <locus target="#40r #40v #41r #41v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.320"><locus from="175r" to="175v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain Jew from the fiery furnace into which his father had cast him</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XLIV; cf. Budge, LIX; and Princeton 20, <locus target="#37r #37v #38r #38v #39r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.321"><locus from="175v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain painter when he fell from his scaffolding</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 20, <locus target="#3v #4r"/>; cf. Budge, VIII; Princeton 20, <locus target="#46r #46v #47r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#57v #58r #58v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#14v #15r #15v #145v #146r"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#32v #33r #33v #34r #34v #35r #35v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.322"><locus from="175v" to="176r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a garment to a certain bishop and how she appeared to a certain man and commanded him to go again to make repentance with the bishop who had previously refused to grant forgiveness</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Budge, XL; Princeton 8, <locus target="#13v #14r #14v #15r #15v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#81v #82r #82v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#49v #50r #50v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.323"><locus from="176r"/><title>How the icon of the Virgin Mary in Jerusalem spoke to the people of Ethiopia when they entered into the place with their shoes still on their feet</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 342–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.324"><locus from="176r" to="176v"/><title>How Jesus Christ took the body of the Virgin Mary to heaven and how the angels praised her and cast upon her the leaves of the tree of life; and how John commanded his secretary Abǝrokos [Prochorus] to write down the account of the assumption of the Virgin on the sixteenth of Näḥase</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 46, <locus target="#65r #65v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.325"><locus from="176v" to="177r"/><title>How the apostles assembled to witness the assumption of the Virgin Mary and how the archangels Gabriel, Michael and Rufael commanded the earth to give up the body of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.326"><locus from="177r" to="177v"/><title>How a certain man named Afǝlaṭon [Plato?] came to see the assumption of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.327"><locus from="177v" to="178r"/><title>How the Holy Spirit commanded Thomas, the apostle, who was in India, to go back to Jerusalem and receive blessing from Saint Mary during her assumption to heaven</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.328"><locus from="178r" to="178v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary prayed to Jesus Christ to send an angel to take her from this world</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.329"><locus from="178v" to="179r"/><title>How the apostles buried the body of the Virgin Mary when she died, part one</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 25–7)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.330"><locus from="179r" to="179v"/><title>How the apostles buried the body of the Virgin Mary when she died, part two</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 27–30)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.331"><locus from="179v" to="180r"/><title>How Saint John greeted the Virgin Mary holding the shroud of the Virgin Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 23–5)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.332"><locus from="180r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain man named Yolǝyo in a dream; how she commanded him to bury the martyrs; how she put the sign of the cross on his hand and how he found it when he awoke</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.333"><locus from="180r" to="180v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary kept the container of oil suspended in the air after its attachments had broken</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 41, <locus target="#135r #135v #136r #136v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.334"><locus from="180v"/><title>How the angel of God transported a certain man eighty cubits outside the church when he had a nocturnal emission</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 185 above, for which this is a longer version, and TM89 186–8)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.335"><locus from="180v" to="181v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Timothy, the archbishop, and how she told him about the holy family and the flight to Egypt</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 321–6; Princeton 46, <locus target="#51v #52r #52v #53r #53v #146r #146v #147r #147v"/>; cf. the appearance to Tewoflos with a similar vision, Princeton 41, <locus target="#21r #21v #22r #22v #23r #23v #24r #24v #25r #25v #26r #26v #27r #27v #28r #28v #29r #29v #30r #113r #113v #114r #114v #115r #115v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.336"><locus from="181v" to="182r"/><title>How Hanna, the mother of the Virgin Mary, went to the funeral of Samǝr, son of Ṭolit, in Jericho and how, when she was weeping and holding his body, he awoke and praised her saying, ―Greetings to you, O Mother of the sun of righteousness‖</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 149–50)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.337"><locus from="182r" to="182v"/><title>How Gregory, the Seer of Mystery (Rä‘aye Ḫǝbu‘at), saw the glory of the Virgin Mary in heaven</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 332–5; Princeton 46, <locus target="#43r #43v #44r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.338"><locus from="182v" to="183v"/><title>How a certain woman, Abrǝsqǝla, and her husband, Särges, consigned to the Devil the son whom, against the woman‘s desire, she conceived on Easter Eve, and how the Virgin Mary rescued the young man from the clutches of the Devil</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 267 above; Budge, XLIX; Princeton 20, <locus target="#35v #36r #36v #37r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.339"><locus from="183v" to="184v"/><title>How a certain man named Ṭǝbrǝyanos became poor and Satan came to him and tempted him to deny Jesus Christ, the Virgin Mary, and the angels and he denied all except the Virgin Mary; and how he repented and appealed to the Virgin Mary and how she obtained forgiveness for him from Jesus Christ</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 339–42; cf. Princeton 20, <locus target="#26r #26v #27r #27v #77r #77v"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#100v #101r #101v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.340"><locus from="184v" to="185r"/><title>How a stone from the mountain of Ṭir served as a ship when the holy family returned from Egypt and the captain of another ship refused to transport them</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(TM89 37–9)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.341"><locus from="185r" to="186r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary raised from the dead a young man who had fallen into a deep pit when he tried to bring water to Däbrä Qwusqwam; how, when he was still lost, his mother prayed to the Virgin Mary during the feast of Däbrä Qwusqwam and how the young man awoke from the dead and came to his mother</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 41, <locus target="#158v #159r #159v #160r #160v #161r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.342"><locus from="186r" to="187r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Ṭimotewos, the Archbishop and son of Deyosəqoros, and how she told him about the meeting with the witch Ṭäludar during the flight of the Holy Family into Egypt</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 46, <locus target="#146r #146v #147r #147v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.343"><locus from="187r" to="188r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Tewoflos the Archbishop of Alexandria and told him about the flight of the Holy Family into Egypt</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf. Princeton 41, <locus target="#21r #21v #22r #22v #23r #23v #24r #24v #25r #25v #26r #26v #27r #27v #28r #28v #29r #29v #30r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.344"><locus from="188r" to="189r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the wife of King Constantine when the brother of the king accused her falsely of adultery when she refused to sleep with him; and how the Virgin Mary gave her the power of healing, and how she led a life of chastity</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.345"><locus from="189r"/><title>How a certain Christian who was the treasurer for a Muslim prince gave all of the food in the treasury to the poor and needy; and how the servants of the prince found nothing in the treasury during a time of drought; and how the Virgin Mary saved the treasurer when he was thrown into prison</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.346"><locus from="189r" to="189v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary, through her icon, told Dänasəyos, the Archbishop of Rome, that King Marqos had entered a monastery</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 8, <locus target="#33v #34r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.347"><locus from="189v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a child to the king of Rome, Mäsfǝyanos, and his wife, Sǝfnǝgǝya</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.348"><locus from="189v" to="190r"/><title>How Nicodemus, an evil-living Persian knight, became a Christian, but was unable to learn the Lord‘s Prayer, and could only master the Salutation to Mary; and how these words were found written on every leaf of a tree which grew on his grave</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, XXXVIII; Princeton 8, <locus target="#10v #11r #11v #12r #12v"/>; Princeton 40, <locus target="#85r #85v"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#22v #23r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.349"><locus from="190r" to="190v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a child to a certain woman named Martha from a royal family in the East; how the Virgin Mary raised the child from the dead when the wife of the Emperor Diocletian threw the child to the floor out of jealousy</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.350"><locus from="190v" to="191v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Tewoflos the Archbishop of Alexandria and told him about the events surrounding Jesus‘ birth and the flight of the Holy Family into Egypt</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(cf., Princeton 41, <locus target="#21r #21v #22r #22v #23r #23v #24r #24v #25r #25v #26r #26v #27r #27v #28r #28v #29r #29v #30r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#110v #111r #111v #112r #112v #113r #113r #113v #114r #114v #115r #115v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.351"><locus from="191v" to="192r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain deacon who loved to sing her praises and how she received his soul into paradise</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 8, <locus target="#14v #15r #15v #16r #16v #17r #17v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.352"><locus from="192r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain man from drowning when the ship was sinking</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 318 above; Princeton 41, <locus target="#99v #100r #100v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.353"><locus from="192r" to="193r"/><title>How a certain woman whose husband had left her for another woman begged the Virgin Mary to kill the other woman; and how the Virgin Mary brought the other woman, who was devoted in worship of the Virgin, to repentance</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 214 above; TM89 256–8)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.354"><locus from="193r"/><title>How Sybil the prophetess saw a vision of the Virgin Mary holding her child within a circle around the sun and revealed this vision to a king who refused to be worshipped</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Princeton 8, <locus target="#6r #6v #7r #7v #8r #8v"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#39r #39v #40r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#37v #38r #38v #39r"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.355"><locus from="193r" to="193v"/><title>How [Abbas,] Bishop of Rome, cut off his hand which had been kissed by a woman when he was celebrating the Eucharist, and how the Virgin Mary rejoined it to his arm</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(incomplete at the end; cf. Budge, V and Va; Princeton 41, <locus target="#55r #55v"/>; Princeton 46, <locus target="#11v #12r #12v"/>; Princeton 47, <locus target="#23v #24r #24v #25r #25v"/>; and fused with the story of); How the Virgin Mary appeared to reassure an ascetic woman about the purity of her friends, other ascetic women held with her in prison (incomplete at the beginning, see miracle 310 above; cf. Princeton 8, <locus target="#19v #20r #20v #21r"/>; Princeton 20, <locus target="#5v #6r #31r #75r #75v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.356"><locus from="193v" to="194r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of a certain woman who died without repentance and how this woman appeared at the church of her friend and told her how the Virgin Mary had saved her because of the blessing of the feast day in that church</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 316 above and Princeton 20, <locus target="#28r #28v #29r #29v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.357"><locus from="194r" to="194v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary helped two brothers when they prayed on behalf of a certain man who had lost his mind when he made a covenant with Satan to protect his cattle</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 202 above; TM89 231–3)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.358"><locus from="194v" to="195r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary raised up a dead knight, who had been buried in the cemetery of a convent, to fight against an enemy of the church called Gǝlǝyanos</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(Budge, LX; Princeton 20, <locus target="#73v #74r #74v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.359"><locus from="195r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary sent priests to a certain man when he prayed to receive holy communion</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 264 above)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.360"><locus from="195r" to="195v"/><title>How one of Herod‘s soldiers saved the Christ child and the Virgin Mary from the slaughter of the innocents</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.361"><locus from="195v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of a man who had committed great sin but who had also built a martyrium; and how the Virgin Mary asked her Son to show mercy on this man</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.362"><locus from="195v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary took a certain abbot with her into heaven when the people accused him and how she punished them</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(a variation of miracle 181 above; TM89 176–7)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.363"><locus from="195v" to="196r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary healed a man who had spent all of his money on medicine but who, at the end, prayed to the Virgin Mary for healing</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.364"><locus from="196r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary provided for a poor family the meal for the feast of Saint Mary</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.365"><locus from="196r" to="196v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary helped a hunter to catch a wild animal with the face of a dog and how she commanded him to eat the flesh of that animal</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.366"><locus from="196v"/><title>How the icon of the Virgin Mary wept for the sins of this world and how the icon spoke to a child to hide this from anyone and how the child followed the Blessed Virgin in a holy life of celibacy</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 273 above; Budge, XCII)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.367"><locus from="196v"/><title>How a certain man wished to build a martyrium to the Virgin Mary but lacked the necessary money and how she showed him in a dream where a pot of gold coins was to be found</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 272 above; Budge, LXXXVIII)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.368"><locus from="196v" to="197r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain governor when the king wrongly accused him and tried to kill him with the sword; and how the Virgin Mary appeared to the king and said, "Don‘t harm my servant"</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 259 above; cf. Princeton 20, <locus target="#31 #32r"/>; Princeton 41, <locus target="#88v #89r"/>; Princeton 43, <locus target="#20v #21r #21v"/>)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.369"><locus from="197r"/><title>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain sick man and commanded him to go into the church on the sixteenth of Näḥase (the feast day of her assumption); and how he was healed on that day</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 240 above)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.370"><locus from="197r" to="197v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary gave a male child to a certain barren woman and how on his wedding day he refused to sleep with his bride; how the Virgin Mary anointed him with fragrance and he went to his bride</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  <note>(see miracle 258 above)</note>
                </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.371"><locus from="197v"/><title>How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of the monk who had no other good works beside observing the fast of Mary which is known as the Assumption</title>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gə‘əz</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf">v + 199</measure>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height>415</height>
                              <width>342</width>
                              <depth>102</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                  <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                  <seg type="rubrication">
                  <foreign xml:lang="gez">ማርያም፡</foreign>
                  </seg>
                  <desc>The word Mary is rubricated</desc>
                  </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d1"><locus target="#iiiv(erso)"/><desc><ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1035HolyMan"/>,<persName ref="PRS4585Georgeo"/> and the <term key="dragon"/></desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d2"><locus target="#ivr(ecto)"/><desc><ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1031VirginAndChild"/></desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d3"><locus target="#viv(erso)"/><desc> How the <ref type="authFile" corresp ="AT1099StMary"/> was crowned by the Trinity</desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d4"><locus target="#4v"/><desc> How the <ref type="authFile" corresp ="AT1099StMary"/> gave garment and chair to Saint Hildefonsus (Däqsǝyos), Bishop of Toledo</desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d5"><locus target="#58v"/><desc> The Assumption of the <ref type="authFile" corresp ="AT1099StMary"/> and how she gave Saint <persName ref="PRS9496Thomas"/> her handkerchief (cf. the four miracles beginning on <locus target="#59r"/> which recount the death and assumption of the Virgin Mary)</desc></decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="frame" xml:id="d6">
                    Decorative designs:
                    <locus target="#1r #5r"/> (ornate and colorful ḫaräg);
                    <locus target="#2r #138v #154r"/> (a line of alternating red and black dots);
                    multiple full stops are used as section dividers throughout (e.g., <locus target="#2r #5r #7r"/>);
                    <locus target="#43r"/> (a line of black dots)
                    </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                  <list>
                    <item xml:id="e1">
                    <locus target="#iir(ecto) #iiv(erso) #iiir(ecto) #iiiv(erso) #ivr(ecto) #ivv(erso) #vr(ecto) #vv(erso) #vir(ecto) #4r #58r #198r #198v"/>
                    <desc>
                    blank
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e2">
                    <locus target="#i #199"/>
                    <desc>
                    are pasted beneath the tooled leather
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a1">
                    <locus target="#197v"/>
                    <desc>
                    Scribal prayer: "Oh our lady, may your prayer and blessing be with your servant—and the scribe Abunä Gäbrä Qiros—forever and ever, amen.""
                  </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e3">
                    <locus target="#1v #6r #26r #30r #41r"/>
                    <desc>
                    (etc.) words of text are written interlinearly
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e4">
                    <locus target="#176v"/>
                    <desc>
                    lines of text are written interlinearly
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e5">
                    <locus target="#31v"> f. 31v, col. 3, line 9</locus>
                    <desc>
                    lines of text are written in the upper margin with a symbol (+) marking the location where the text is to be inserted
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e6">
                    <locus target="#44v #51v #79v"/>
                    <desc>
                    text has been removed
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="e7">
                    <locus target="#144r"> f. 144r, col. 3, lines 16–17</locus>
                    <desc>
                    two lines of text have been crossed out to correct homeoteleuton (see lines 11–12)
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="a2">
                    <locus target="#43r"> f. 43r, col. 2</locus>
                    <desc>
                    contains the beginning of the miracle know as "How the Virgin Mary call John, the priest, 'Golden Mouth' after he kissed the woman with an issue of menstrual blood who had been challenged by Nestorius." Cf. TM89 159–61. But, the scribe stopped, put removal dots above and below the account, and someone has made ink lines through the text
                    </desc>
                    </item>
                  </list>
                </additions>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate when="1950">twentieth  century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                     href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italian</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
                                    <change when="2020-02-21" who="ABe">Added items</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
