<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="mss" xml:lang="en" xml:id="PRet01198"><teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/"><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="t1">Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 56: A Book of Magical Prayers With Talismanic Drawings</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority><publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher><pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace><availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"><p>This file is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p><p>Transformed with permission to create a stub record from https://findingaids.princeton.edu/collections/C0776/cPRet01198.xml . See https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/1181.</p></licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc xml:id="ms"><msIdentifier><repository ref="INS0486Princeton_University_Library"/><idno>Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 56: A Book of Magical Prayers With Talismanic Drawings</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary><p>Illustration: Fol. 3v: A drawing in purple ink of Jesus and another figure in a reed boat addressing a now feint figure outside a house ( ?). The text above the drawing, also in purple ink, is now only partly legible and seems to mention an individual called Berhanä Mäsqäl. </p><p>  Illustrations: Fol. 4r: A collection of talismanic drawings. </p><p>  Illustrations: Fols. 5v-6v: [mostly in red] A collection of talismanic drawings, followed by a prayer for the "drowning" of demons. </p><p>  Illustrations: Fols. 7rv: Two grid charts, the second of which is titled "My Lord Jesus Christ, with this chart save me from mäqurañña [possibly meaning here 'demonic possession']. </p><p>  Illustrations: Fols. 8r-9r: [in red] Further grid charts followed by a prayer for binding demons, barya, zar, etc., with talismanic drawings and figures. </p><p>  Illustration: Fols. 32v: Three grid charts entitled "for Monday" , "for Wednesday," and "for Thursday," respectively. </p><p>  Illustration: Fol. 33r: A crude drawing of a bird and talismanic letters [harägwi fidäl, lit. "knotted letters"]. </p><p>  Illustration: Fols. 33v-34r: A drawing of a supplicant with accompanying servant being led by the Virgin Mary towards the figure of Christ in majesty [f.34r]. The supplicant may be a priest as evidenced by his turban and the prayer stick carried by his servant. The text reads "how — (name erased) made supplication through Our Lady Mary and with his [sic] beloved Saviour of the World." </p><p> Illustration: Fol. 35r: Virgin and Child.</p><p>  This is a high-quality magical prayer book made in the first half of the nineteenth century likely for a member of the nobility. As expected, there is no formal indication of date. The several hands are all a 19th century räqiq hand, of varying quality, certain features of which might suggest a date earlier rather than a later in the century, and the costume worn by the figure of the supplicant in the drawing on fol. 33v resembles that worn by the nobility up to the 1850s. </p><p>  There are numerous talismanic drawings and the quality of many of them shows greater finesse than is usual in magical manuscripts of this sort. This type of manuscript, intended for practical use by a däbtära as a source book for the composition of amulet scrolls or kitab, would normally be copied by the original owner himself, but as is the case here could also be passed on to others. </p><p>  The text comprises a collection of prayers for various purposes. In the present manuscript these are predominantly prayers against drowning (s'älot bä'entä mäst'em) and prayers to counteract spells (mäftehé seray), though there is also a version of the well known magical prayer known as the Säyfä Esat or Sword of Fire. The accompanying diagrams are intended as prophylactic designs for incorporation in amulets, and the charts or tables either as devices for divination or schematic representations of protective processes. The prayer texts themselves typically comprise lists of magical names (asmat) for the summoning of power or the protection and shielding of the individual from demonic forces. </p><p>  The name of the original owner and probable scribe has been erased throughout, though the first element of his name, Wäldä..., is still occasionally visible.</p><p>In red, with a small haräg at the beginning and a talismanic figure in the form of an eight-pointed star with serpents' head arms at the end.</p><p>Incorporating 5 talismanic drawings or charts, one [f.10v] of nine squares with a face in the centre square and cherubim in each of the four corner squares, another [f.12v] in grid form possibly representing the "net of Solomon" for trapping spirits. The motif of alternating faces in a grid-pattern design also appears in the drawing at the end of the group of prayers [f.13v].</p><p>Incorporating another grid-like talismanic drawing [f.18r] and two smaller designs.</p><p>Incorporating 5 small talismanic drawings.</p><p>Incorporating talismanic drawings and grid-patterns.</p><p>Incorporating talismanic drawings and grid-patterns.</p><!--BIBLIOGRAPHY--></summary><msItem xml:id="ms_i1"><locus>Located on folio 1r-3v.</locus><title>A Composite Text Beginning in Abrupto With an Extract from the Gospel Text Recounting Jesus' Recruiting of the Apostle Andrew, Followed by a Magical Prayer or Prayers Invoking the Same Apostle</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1830">early 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i2"><locus>Located on folio 4v-5r.</locus><title>A Prayer for the Binding of Demons, Barya and Zar</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1830">early 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i3"><locus>Located on folio 9v-13v.</locus><title>Series of Prayers for the Undoing of Spells or Charms</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1830">early 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i4"><locus>Located on folio 14r-17r.</locus><title>Series of Prayers for the Undoing of Spells</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1830">early 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i5"><locus>Located on folio 17r-20r.</locus><title>Series of Prayers for "Drowning" [of Demons]</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1830">early 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i6"><locus>Located on folio 20r.</locus><title>Series of Prayers for the Undoing of Spells</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1830">early 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i7"><locus>Located on folio 20r-29v.</locus><title>Series of Prayers for the Undoing of Spells</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1830">early 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i8"><locus>Located on folio 29v-32v.</locus><title>An Extensive Prayer Without a Title But Also for Release from Spells and Charms</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1830">early 19th century</date></msItem></msContents><physDesc><objectDesc form="Codex"><supportDesc><support><p/></support></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc><history><origin><origDate>early 19th century</origDate></origin></history></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml"><xi:fallback><p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p></xi:fallback></xi:include></encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language><language ident="gez"/></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="PL" when="2016-11-17">Created XML record from https://findingaids.princeton.edu/collections/C0776/cPRet01198.xml . See https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/1181.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/"><body><ab/></body></text></TEI>