<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="mss" xml:lang="en" xml:id="PRet00164"><teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/"><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="t1">Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 20: Miracles of Mary (Tä'amrä Maryam), Book of Baptism (Mäsəhafä Təmqät)</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority><publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher><pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace><availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"><p>This file is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p><p>Transformed with permission to create a stub record from https://findingaids.princeton.edu/collections/C0776/cPRet00164.xml . See https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/1181.</p></licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc xml:id="ms"><msIdentifier><repository ref="INS0486Princeton_University_Library"/><idno>Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 20: Miracles of Mary (Tä'amrä Maryam), Book of Baptism (Mäsəhafä Təmqät)</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary><p>Fol. 21v: Pen trial in crude hand with black ink and pencil scrawl. </p><p>  Fols. 91v: The scribe's name is mentioned in the original manuscript but someone has erased it. </p><p>  Fols. 91v-92r: In another, later hand, is a note of the gift of the manuscript to a church (whose name has been erased). </p><p> Fols. 92r: Ge'ez alphabet.</p><p>  Fols. 92v: Pen and pencil scrawls. Also throughout. </p><p>  Two manuscripts have been bound together, one is older than the other. They are in different hands. The first manuscript is the Book of Baptism, Miracles of St Michael, Miracles of Jesus, and Miracles of Mary. After fol. 22r are only Miracles of Mary. </p><p> No miniatures.</p><p> Gift of John Mason.</p><p> Original owner: Kəflä Mika'e.</p><p>  Loose slip of paper noting cataloging information about the manuscript and a photocopy of part of a letter from John Mason, the purchaser, re. cataloging by Isaac Welde-Iesus in Kenya, dated to 1986.</p><p>The owner's name is not mentioned in this one of the two texts.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared with saints Abba Mäqars, Abba Yohannəs Abba Bəsoy, Abba Musse, Abba Yohannəs at the monastry of Asqetəs.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary healed a woman at Bethlehem.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary left her handprint in the icon of the Virgin Mary when a certain priest burned incense and bowed to her icon and how she brought holy water inside the church and how Elarəya, daughter of King Zänun, left for the monastic life at Asqetəs (repeated later).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved the painter when he fell down from his scaffolding (different version of Budge, Mary, 8).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to King Anorewos and how she led him to the ascetic life.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved the robber's soul from judgment because he drank from water that sprang from her feet.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain ascetic woman to reassure her about the purity of her friends, other ascetics in the monastery (similar to twenty-second miracle later in this manuscript).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary rebuked a woman when she gave up fasting at her husband's command (incomplete at the end) (Budge, Mary, 99).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved a drunken monk from a lion (Budge, Mary, 48).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped Säwla, wife of Giyorgis (the new martyr) when she wanted to bury the remain of her husband's body (incomplete at the end, folios including the end missing).</p><p>The original owner's name, Kəflä Mika'e, is mentioned in this text at the beginning of most of the miracles. The later owner has erased the original owner's name in the first few folios. But the name of Säga Mika'el, the father of Kəflä Mika'e, which also appears at the beginning of some miracles has escaped the eraser because his name is in black ink not red. Some other names sometimes appear at the beginning of the miracles, but those mentioned above are the most common.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary accepted the book of her miracles compiled by Saint Hildefonsus [Däqsəyos], Bishop of Toledo (Budge, Mary 1; Strelcyn 15.1.1, 32.16.1).</p><p>How Jesus Christ asked the Virgin Mary about her five lamentations.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain adulterous person from his temptation in Alexandria (incomplete at the end, folios including the end missing from manuscript).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped a young impoverished man and how the church keeper gave his daughter to him (incomplete at the beginning, which is at 72rv).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain wealthy woman who was the patron of a monastery.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to the Färäsawi when he denied Christ but kept his devotion to the Virgin Mary.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved from the hand of a demon a monk who fell in love with a certain woman and drowned while going to visit her (Budge, Mary, 69).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain nun who died before she finished her penitence and how she appeared to the Abbess and told her how the Virgin Mary saved her (similar to Romances, Cleopatra 13?).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped a certain nun by encouraging her to pray Hail Mary everywhere.</p><p>How the icon of the Virgin Mary bled when a certain Jew cast it to the ground (Budge, Mary, 68).</p><p>Excerpt, unclear, probably how the Virgin Mary appeared at Däbrä Metmaq.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to the ascetic woman Arsema to reassure her about the purity of her friends, also at the monastery (incomplete at the beginning, which is at 75r).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved a noble man named Armatəyas in Ephesus from hanging when he was falsely accused.</p><p>How the icon of the Virgin Mary at the Däbrä Qälmon monastery healed an Arab woman with hemorrhage.</p><p>How a certain nun fled with a certain monk and how the Virgin Mary fulfilled the duties of the nun during her absence (Budge, Mary, 106).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved a young man whose mother had promised him to the Devil (Budge, Mary, 49).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary delivered a certain Jew from a fiery furnace into which his father had cast him (Budge, Mary, 59).</p><p>How Sybil the prophetess saw the Virgin Mary with Christ the Child inside the sun disk and revealed it to a king who did not want to be worshipped.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary obtained forgiveness for a monk named Hərnay who had mutilated himself and died under the influence of Satan in disguise as a saint Mar Ya'əqob [Jacob] (Budge, Mary 101).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary spoke from her picture to a devout worshipper (Budge, Mary 2; Strelcyn 15.1.3, 32.16.2).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary healed the elderly Jew of Akəmim when he fell and broke his back during the church service because of his old age (Budge, Mary, 3).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to the dying scribe Damianus of Philippi (Budge, Mary, 4).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Isaac, the monk, and promised to take him to herself after three days (Budge, Mary, 6).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared out of her picture to Mary, the daughter of a certain God-fearing man, and promised to take her to Paradise after three days (Budge, Mary, 7).</p><p>How a painter was saved by the Virgin Mary when he fell from a scaffold (Budge, Mary, 8).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary carried a sick person from the Monastery of the Pilgrims to Jerusalem and showed him where Jesus was crucified and buried and baptized him in the waters of the Jordan (Budge, Mary, 9).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary recovered the stolen property of two women called Juliana and Barbara, when they were on pilgrimage to Jerusalem (Budge, Mary, 11; Strelcyn 32.16. 11).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary moved the Monastery in Greece to Jericho road (Budge, Mary, 13; Strelcyn 32.16. 13).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary healed the merchant from Colossae after being shot in the eye with an arrow by pirates (Budge, Mary, 15; Strelcyn 32.16. 15).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary arranged marriages for two poor girls called Martha and Yäwahit (Budge, Mary, 17; Strelcyn 32.16. 17).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary delivered the soul of the scribe who was writing the book of her miracles when the demons took him by mistake to hell (Budge, Mary, 18; Strelcyn 32.16.18).</p><p>How the icon of the Virgin Mary spoke to a certain woman whose mother-in-law was opposed to her devotion to the icon of the Virgin and how the icon disappeared because of the mother-in-law's objection.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary delivered from prison a certain man called Giyorgis the New Martyr (Budge, Mary, 19; Strelcyn 32.16. 19).</p><p>How a certain rich man called Paqlima hurled a loaf at the head of a beggar and wounded him, and how the Virgin Mary delivered his soul from demons (Budge, Mary, 86).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped a certain wealthy women from Caesarea to give birth to a child when her relatives brought her to the Icon of the Virgin Mary.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary healed the foot of a widow from Harətärom (incomplete at the end) (Budge, Mary, 24).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain shepherd and promised to take him to herself in paradise and how she lead him to a certain monastery to die there (incomplete at the end, folio flipped, continues on 60v).</p><p>How the Icon of the Virgin Mary spoke to a certain woman who swallowed scorpion when she was depressed and how the voice from the icon led her to a certain wise man for her healing (incomplete at the beginning).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved the people on a certain ship on the sea when they were caught in a powerful storm.</p><p>How a certain young man placed a ring on the finger of a icon of the Virgin Mary and how the virgin regarded it as an engagement ring) (incomplete at the end, which appears on 61rv (Budge, Mary, 67).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary sent the shepherd to the monastery and how he died after he blessed the monks in the monastery (incomplete at the beginning, a continuation of fol. 56v).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped a certain church whose leader had died very recently (excerpt).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain evil wealthy man's soul from demons and how she took him in to paradise.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of a wicked monastic leader after he died because he was devoted to her and how he appeared to his disciple and told him how she saved him from hell (incomplete at the end, which is at 64rv).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary healed a man with a stone foot (Budge, Mary, 22; Strelcyn 32.16.22) (incomplete at the end).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of certain monk after he died (incomplete at the beginning, which is at 61v).</p><p>Four-line fragment, does not continue on 65r.</p><p>Fragment, does not continue from 64v.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved the thief from hanging.</p><p>(How the Virgin Mary appeared in the monastery of Asqetəs with the church fathers.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary brought water to the well of Däbrä Mətmaq.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Deacon Yohannəs in the Pillar of Light.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to Yohannəs Käma and how she commanded him to build a church.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary punished the son of the king of the Egypt when he challenged the Virgin Mary and Jesus Christ .</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped a young impoverished man and how the church keeper gave his daughter to him (incomplete, the end of the story is at 25r).</p><p>How the icon of the Virgin Mary exuded oil and milk (incomplete at the beginning) (Budge, Mary, 59).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary raised a dead martyred knight to fight against an enemy of the church called Goliath (Goləyəd) (Budge, Mary, 60).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary left her handprint in the icon of the Virgin Mary when a certain priest burned incense and bowed to her icon and how she brought holy water inside the church and how Elarəya, daughter of King Zänun, left for the monastic life at Asqetəs (fragment).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to an ascetic woman named Arsema to reassure her about the purity of her friends, also at the monastery (incomplete at the end, the end is at 31r) (repeated).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary raised from the dead a certain man's son (incomplete at the beginning).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped a wicked prince who was devoted to the Virgin Mary but became mad (incomplete at the end, see 79rv for end).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of a young man who denied God and the angels but kept his faith in the Virgin Mary (excerpt).</p><p>How a certain Jew of Constantinople threw to the ground a picture of the Virgin Mary and when it was restored it exuded oil that healed many (Budge, Mary, 45).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary wicked prince who was devoted to the Virgin Mary but became mad (incomplete at the beginning, see 76r for beginning).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary gave children to a certain woman whose nine children had died when the woman promised that they would become priests and deacons.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Barok, a dissolute man (Budge, Mary, 26).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Anəsətasəyos of Rome (Budge, Mary, 27).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped a monk to escape the monastery of Qäləmon when persecuted by other monks when he breached the wall of the church by hitting it with his skull cap (Budge, Mary, 28; Strelcyn 32.16.28).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved a thief from his persecutors.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved the woman in childbirth from drowning (Budge, Mary, 32; Strelcyn 32.16. 31; Bland 2, also Vincent de Beauvais).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary gave water to a thirsty dog (Budge, Mary, 33; Strelcyn 32.16. 32).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary gave a garment to a monk (Budge, Mary, 93).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary begged her son to forgive the sins of a wealthy evil man.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared before a certain woman in the monastery during church service.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary anointed the animal's feet while she was at Däbrä Qusəqam, according to Saint Anthony.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared at Däbrä Qusəqam, according to Saint Anthony.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved Timothy, a drunken monk, from a lion) (Budge, Mary, 48).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary performed a miracle on her feast day at Wäme[?] (excerpt).</p><p>How the Church of the Virgin Mary in Getheseman will be an ark at the time of Christ's coming (incomplete at the beginning).</p><p>How a certain priest left his handprint in the icon of the Virgin Mary when he bowed to her and how the Virgin Mary brought holy water inside the church and how Elarəya, daughter of King Zänun, left for the monastic life at Asqetəs (incomplete, the end is at 75v?).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped a sick monk to receive the holy communion)(incomplete at the beginning.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary helped a young impoverished man by appearing as a wealthy woman to the father of a young woman and giving him the money needed for the young man to marry her (excerpt).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary persuaded her son to forgive the Ishamalite by telling him that he could no longer sit on her lap unless he forgave the man (incomplete at the end).</p><p>How during her festival the Virgin Mary took a certain woman into paradise (incomplete at the beginning).</p><p>How the wealthy farmer forgot to prepare a banquet for the feast day of Saint Michael the Archangel and how Saint Michael the Archangel forgave the farmer and protected his farm when it was invaded by worms.</p><p>How Jesus healed the deaf, dumb, and blind (Strelcyn 16, ?).</p><!--BIBLIOGRAPHY--><p>References: Regarding Miracles of Mary, see manuscript no. 8. Regarding Book of Baptism, see Sylvain Grébaut, "Ordre du Baptême et de la Confirmation dans l'Église Éthiopienne," ROC, vol. 26 (1927-8), pp. 105-89; Ernst Trumpp, "Das Taufebuch der aethiopischen Kircher: Aethiopisch und Deutsch," Abhandlungen der philosophisch.- philologischen Classe der Königlichen Bayerischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, vol.14, no. 111 (1878), pp. 147-83; Enclyopedia Aethiopica, vol. 1, pp. 468-470.</p></summary><msItem xml:id="ms_i1"><locus>Located on folio 1r-21r.</locus><title>Miracles of Mary 1-10</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i2"><locus>Located on folio 22r-91v.</locus><title>Miracles of Mary 11-94</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i3"><locus>Located on folio 7r-8v, 10r-16v.</locus><title>Book of Baptism, (Mäsəhafä Təmqät)</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i4"><locus>Located on folio 19v-20r.</locus><title>Miracle of Saint Michael the Archangel</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i5"><locus>Located on folio 20v-21r.</locus><title>Miracle of Jesus</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i6"><locus>Located on folio 1rv.</locus><title>First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i7"><locus>Located on folio 1v-2r.</locus><title>Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i8"><locus>Located on folio 2rv.</locus><title>Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i9"><locus>Located on folio 2v-3r.</locus><title>Homily of King Zärə'a Ya'əqob on the Honor of Virgin Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i10"><locus>Located on folio 3v-4r.</locus><title>Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i11"><locus>Located on folio 4rv.</locus><title>Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i12"><locus>Located on folio 5rv.</locus><title>Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i13"><locus>Located on folio 5v-6r.</locus><title>Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i14"><locus>Located on folio 6rv.</locus><title>Eighth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i15"><locus>Located on folio 9rv.</locus><title>Ninth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i16"><locus>Located on folio 9v.</locus><title>Tenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i17"><locus>Located on folio 17r-19v.</locus><title>Prayer to Mary About the Reading of the Miracles</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i18"><locus>Located on folio 22r-23v.</locus><title>Eleventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i19"><locus>Located on folio 23v-24r.</locus><title>Twelfth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i20"><locus>Located on folio 24v.</locus><title>Thirteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i21"><locus>Located on folio 25r.</locus><title>Fourteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i22"><locus>Located on folio 25v-26v.</locus><title>Fifteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i23"><locus>Located on folio 26r-27v.</locus><title>Sixteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i24"><locus>Located on folio 27r-28v.</locus><title>Seventeenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i25"><locus>Located on folio 28r-29v.</locus><title>Eighteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i26"><locus>Located on folio 29rv.</locus><title>Nineteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i27"><locus>Located on folio 29v-30v.</locus><title>Twentieth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i28"><locus>Located on folio 30v.</locus><title>Twenty-First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i29"><locus>Located on folio 31r.</locus><title>Twenty-Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i30"><locus>Located on folio 31r-32r.</locus><title>Twenty-Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i31"><locus>Located on folio 32r-33v.</locus><title>Twenty-Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i32"><locus>Located on folio 33v-35v.</locus><title>Twenty-Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i33"><locus>Located on folio 35v-37r.</locus><title>Twenty-Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i34"><locus>Located on folio 37r-39r.</locus><title>Twenty-Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i35"><locus>Located on folio 39r-40r.</locus><title>Twenty-Eighth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i36"><locus>Located on folio 40r-41v.</locus><title>Twenty-Ninth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i37"><locus>Located on folio 41v-42r.</locus><title>Thirtieth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i38"><locus>Located on folio 42r-43r.</locus><title>Thirty-First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i39"><locus>Located on folio 43r-44r.</locus><title>Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i40"><locus>Located on folio 44r-45r.</locus><title>Thirty-Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i41"><locus>Located on folio 45r-46r.</locus><title>Thirty-Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i42"><locus>Located on folio 46r-47r.</locus><title>Thirty-Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i43"><locus>Located on folio 47r-48r.</locus><title>Thirty-Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i44"><locus>Located on folio 48rv.</locus><title>Thirty-Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i45"><locus>Located on folio 48v-49v.</locus><title>Thirty-Eighth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i46"><locus>Located on folio 49v-50v.</locus><title>Thirty-Ninth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i47"><locus>Located on folio 50v-51v.</locus><title>Fortieth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i48"><locus>Located on folio 51v-52v.</locus><title>Forty-First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i49"><locus>Located on folio 52v-53r.</locus><title>Forty-Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i50"><locus>Located on folio 53rv.</locus><title>Forty-Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i51"><locus>Located on folio 53v.</locus><title>Fragment of a Miracle About a Certain Priest</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i52"><locus>Located on folio 54r-55r.</locus><title>Forty-Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i53"><locus>Located on folio 55rv.</locus><title>Forty-Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i54"><locus>Located on folio 55v.</locus><title>Forty-Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i55"><locus>Located on folio 56rv.</locus><title>Forty-Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i56"><locus>Located on folio 57rv.</locus><title>Forty-Eighth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i57"><locus>Located on folio 57v-58vr.</locus><title>Forty-Ninth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i58"><locus>Located on folio 58v-59v and 61rv.</locus><title>Fiftieth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i59"><locus>Located on folio 60rv.</locus><title>Fifty-First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i60"><locus>Located on folio 61v.</locus><title>Fifty-Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i61"><locus>Located on folio 62rv.</locus><title>Fifty-Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i62"><locus>Located on folio 62v.</locus><title>Fifty-Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i63"><locus>Located on folio 63rv.</locus><title>Fifty-Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i64"><locus>Located on folio 64rv.</locus><title>Fifty-Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i65"><locus>Located on folio 64v.</locus><title>Fifty-Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i66"><locus>Located on folio 65r.</locus><title>Fifty-Eighth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i67"><locus>Located on folio 65r-66r.</locus><title>Fifty-Ninth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i68"><locus>Located on folio 66rv.</locus><title>Sixtieth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i69"><locus>Located on folio 66r-68r.</locus><title>Sixty-First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i70"><locus>Located on folio 68r-69v.</locus><title>Sixty-Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i71"><locus>Located on folio 70r-71r.</locus><title>Sixty-Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i72"><locus>Located on folio 71r-72r.</locus><title>Sixty-Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i73"><locus>Located on folio 72rv.</locus><title>Sixty-Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i74"><locus>Located on folio 73rv.</locus><title>Sixty-Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i75"><locus>Located on folio 73v-74v.</locus><title>Sixty-Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i76"><locus>Located on folio 75r.</locus><title>Sixty-Eighth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i77"><locus>Located on folio 75rv.</locus><title>Sixty-Ninth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i78"><locus>Located on folio 76rv.</locus><title>Seventieth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i79"><locus>Located on folio 76v.</locus><title>Seventy-First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i80"><locus>Located on folio 77rv.</locus><title>Seventy-Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i81"><locus>Located on folio 78rv.</locus><title>Seventy-Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i82"><locus>Located on folio 79rv.</locus><title>Seventy-Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i83"><locus>Located on folio 79v-80r.</locus><title>Seventy-Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i84"><locus>Located on folio 80r-81r.</locus><title>Seventy-Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i85"><locus>Located on folio 81rv.</locus><title>Seventy-Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i86"><locus>Located on folio 81v-82r.</locus><title>Seventy-Eighth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i87"><locus>Located on folio 82rv.</locus><title>Seventy-Ninth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i88"><locus>Located on folio 82v-83r.</locus><title>Eightieth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i89"><locus>Located on folio 83r-84r.</locus><title>Eighty-First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i90"><locus>Located on folio 84r.</locus><title>Eighty-Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i91"><locus>Located on folio 84r-85r.</locus><title>Eighty-Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i92"><locus>Located on folio 85rv.</locus><title>Eighty-Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i93"><locus>Located on folio 85v-86v.</locus><title>Eighty-Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i94"><locus>Located on folio 86v-87r.</locus><title>Eighty-Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i95"><locus>Located on folio 87rv.</locus><title>Eighty-Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i96"><locus>Located on folio 87v.</locus><title>Eighty-Eighth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i97"><locus>Located on folio 88r.</locus><title>Eighty-Ninth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i98"><locus>Located on folio 88rv.</locus><title>Nintieth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i99"><locus>Located on folio 89r.</locus><title>Ninety-First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i100"><locus>Located on folio 90r.</locus><title>Ninety-Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i101"><locus>Located on folio 90rv.</locus><title>Ninety-Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i102"><locus>Located on folio 91rv.</locus><title>Ninety-Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1700" notAfter="1709">1700s</date></msItem></msContents><physDesc><objectDesc form="Codex"><supportDesc><support><p/></support></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc><history><origin><origDate>1700s</origDate></origin></history></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml"><xi:fallback><p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p></xi:fallback></xi:include></encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language><language ident="gez"/></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="PL" when="2016-11-17">Created XML record from https://findingaids.princeton.edu/collections/C0776/cPRet00164.xml . See https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/1181.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/"><body><ab/></body></text></TEI>