<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="mss" xml:lang="en" xml:id="PRet00076"><teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/"><fileDesc><titleStmt><title xml:id="t1">Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 8: Miracles of Mary (Tä'amrä Maryam)</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority><publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher><pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace><availability><licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"><p>This file is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p><p>Transformed with permission to create a stub record from https://findingaids.princeton.edu/collections/C0776/cPRet00076.xml . See https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/1181.</p></licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc xml:id="ms"><msIdentifier><repository ref="INS0486Princeton_University_Library"/><idno>Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 8: Miracles of Mary (Tä'amrä Maryam)</idno></msIdentifier><msContents><summary><p>Fols. 10v, 12v, 25r, 27r: Owner's named erased at the beginning of every miracle, but appears faintly on these folios as "Zä'ra Krəstos." </p><p>  Fol. 47: Previous cataloger says this folio loose, but no folio 47 is in the box. </p><p>  Manuscript is in different hands, one hand for 1r-22v (miracles 1-12), another for fols. 22r-46v (miracles 13-27). The two parts were commissioned at the same time, however, as the same owner's name appears throughout and the numbering of the miracles is continuous. </p><p> No scribe listed.</p><p> No miniatures.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary accepted the book of her miracles compiled by Saint Hildefonsus [Däqsəyos], Bishop of Toledo and how she punished a bishop who usurped the garment and chair of Hildefonsus (Budge, Mary 1; Strelcyn 15.1.1, 32.16.1; Bland 1). Incomplete at the beginning.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary healed the sick deacon who recited her sälam song by anointing him with her breast milk (not in Budge).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved a certain bandit from hanging because he always recited her sälam song and how he became a pious monk (not in Budge).</p><p>How Sybil the prophetess saw a vision of the Virgin Mary holding her child within a circle around the sun and revealed this vision to a king who refused to be worshipped (not in Budge).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary commanded a deacon to dig up and rebury in consecrated ground the body of an adulterous deacon from the island of Jericho in the city of Gärisat who was killed by the people (Budge, Mary, 103).</p><p>How a certain sinful knight from Afəras (France) named Niqodimos recited the Hail Mary (Sälamä Gäbrə'el) his whole life and when he died a tree with Hail Mary written on its leaves in gold sprang from his grave (Budge, Mary, 38).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary kept alive a certain wicked man who had been beaten by his enemies until he repented from his sins.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary gave a garment to a certain bishop and how she commanded him to receive a person who wanted to repent before him (Budge, Mary, 40).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain deacon who loved to sing her praises and how she received his soul into paradise.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a bishop to restore a priest called Enədrəyas who knew how to conduct only one of the fourteen anaphoras, the Anaphora of the Virgin Mary (Budge, Mary, 102).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to reassure an ascetic woman about the purity of her friends, other ascetic women in the monastery.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared as a shining woman and saved the drunk monk, who was devoted to the Virgin Mary, from the lion (Budge, Mary, 48).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary confronted robbers who went to steal property from a church devoted to her in Sam and how she locked the door so they couldn't get out and killed one and sent the governor to kill the rest.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to various people, including Europeans (Afərəng), Romans, Syrians, and Marionites, in the church of Däbrä Mətməq in Egypt, and how she gave a vision of hell to a Jacobite (non-Chalcedonian) and how she saved the Christians when they were called before the Asraf, the Sultan of Egypt when asked to describe this vision.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved kidnapped Christians from the Muslim Cyprian, especially one rich man imprisoned by a Muslim in a box and how she transported the box, the prisoner, and the jailer to her church and how the Muslim converted.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to the Syrian potter (Ephrəm) and how she caused him to compose the Wədasse Maryam for the seven days of the week (Budge, Mary, 35).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary told Dänasəyos the Archbishop of Rome that King Marqos had entered a monastery.</p><p>How King Marqos became the king of Rome and was pressed to marry, how he left his palace and went to church to pray before the Icon of Mary and how he entered the monastery of Tormaq.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary and Jesus and angels appeared to a pure man named Bifämon of Awəsem before his martyrdom and received him into paradise.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary saved from demons the soul of a wicked wealthy man who oppressed his servants but was devoted to her.</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a Roman youth called Zacharias who crowned her icon with roses and how she saved him from bandits because they saw roses flowing from his mouth when he recited her sälam and how they converted and became monks (Budge, Mary, 10).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary recovered the stolen food of two women when they were on pilgrimage to Jerusalem and how the thief's teeth fell out as he ate their food and how the thieves converted (Budge, Mary, 11; Strelcyn 32.16. 11).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary sent Christ in the form of a child to an elderly woman who prayed to the Virgin Mary asking how she raised her son and how the woman refused to pick up the child and how the child said that she was praying to his mother and how she wept upon realizing that she had not recognized her Lord (Budge, Mary, 46).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary caused a stream to reverse (Budge, Mary, 36).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to reassure an ascetic woman about the purity of her friends, other ascetic women in the monastery (same as eleventh miracle above).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared as a shining woman and saved the drunk monk, who was devoted to the Virgin Mary, from the lion (Budge, Mary, 48; same as twelfth miracle above).</p><p>How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain wealthy woman who was the patron of a certain monastery (upper folio broken so some words missing).</p><!--BIBLIOGRAPHY--><p>References: The main work addressing the Ethiopic Miracles of Mary is Enrico Cerulli, Il libro etiopico dei Miracoli di Maria (Rome, 1943). Regarding information on Marian literature, see the entry in Encyclopedia Aethiopica , vol. 3, pp. 814-817. For other cataloguing, see S. Strelcyn, Catalogue of Ethiopian Manuscripts in the British Library Acquired Since the year 1877 (London: British Library, 1978), mss. 14, 15, 32, 35, 39. For translations into English, see Wallis Budge, The Miracles of the Blessed Virgin Mary and the Life of Hanna (London 1900); Wallis Budge, One Hundred and Ten Miracles of Our Lady Mary (London 1923); Wallis Budge, Legends of Our Lady Mary, the Perpetual Virgin and Her Mother Hanna (London 1922). For comparison, see one hundred miracles of Mary written down by Johannes Herolt in Latin in the 1430s, the most popular European print version of the tales. For a translation, see C. C. Swinton Bland, Miracles of the Blessed Virgin Mary by Johannes Herolt called Discipulus (1435-1440) (London, George Routledge and Sons, 1928). See also Mussafia, Studien zu den mitteralterlichen Marienlegenden , an examination of collections of Mary legends in European libraries.</p></summary><msItem xml:id="ms_i1"><locus>Located on folio 1r-2r.</locus><title>First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i2"><locus>Located on folio 2r-4r.</locus><title>Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i3"><locus>Located on folio 4r-6r.</locus><title>Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i4"><locus>Located on folio 6r-8v.</locus><title>Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i5"><locus>Located on folio 9r-10v.</locus><title>Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i6"><locus>Located on folio 10v-12v.</locus><title>Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i7"><locus>Located on folio 12v-13v.</locus><title>Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i8"><locus>Located on folio 13v-15v.</locus><title>Eighth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i9"><locus>Located on folio 14v-17v.</locus><title>Ninth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i10"><locus>Located on folio 117v-19v.</locus><title>Tenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i11"><locus>Located on folio 19v-21r.</locus><title>Eleventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i12"><locus>Located on folio 21r-22r.</locus><title>Twelfth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i13"><locus>Located on folio 23r-25r.</locus><title>Thirteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i14"><locus>Located on folio 25r-27r.</locus><title>Fourteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i15"><locus>Located on folio 27r-30r.</locus><title>Fifteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i16"><locus>Located on folio 30r-33v.</locus><title>Sixteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i17"><locus>Located on folio 33v-34r.</locus><title>Seventeenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i18"><locus>Located on folio 34r-35v.</locus><title>Eighteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i19"><locus>Located on folio 35v-37r.</locus><title>Nineteenth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i20"><locus>Located on folio 37r-38r.</locus><title>Twentieth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i21"><locus>Located on folio 39r-41r.</locus><title>Twenty-First Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i22"><locus>Located on folio 41rv.</locus><title>Twenty-Second Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i23"><locus>Located on folio 41v-43r.</locus><title>Twenty-Third Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i24"><locus>Located on folio 43rv.</locus><title>Twenty-Fourth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i25"><locus>Located on folio 43v-44v.</locus><title>Twenty-Fifth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i26"><locus>Located on folio 44v-45v.</locus><title>Twenty-Sixth Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem><msItem xml:id="ms_i27"><locus>Located on folio 45v-46v.</locus><title>Twenty-Seventh Miracle of Mary</title><date cert="low" notBefore="1870" notAfter="1899">late 19th century</date></msItem></msContents><physDesc><objectDesc form="Codex"><supportDesc><support><p/></support></supportDesc></objectDesc></physDesc><history><origin><origDate>late 19th century</origDate></origin></history></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml"><xi:fallback><p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p></xi:fallback></xi:include></encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">English</language><language ident="gez"/></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="PL" when="2016-11-17">Created XML record from https://findingaids.princeton.edu/collections/C0776/cPRet00076.xml . See https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/issues/1181.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/"><body><ab/></body></text></TEI>