<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="ESaqg005"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="mss">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gadla Samāʿtāt, Vitae of Saints and Martyrs (for the months from Tāḫśāś to Naḥāse)</title>
            <editor key="DN"/>
            <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob Ludolf Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens: Eine
                                multimediale Forschungsumgebung / beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p>
                                    This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                    Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-06-07T17:37:12.519+02:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0097AQG"/>
                  <collection>Ethio-SPaRe</collection>
                  <idno>AQG-005</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>I) Gadla Samāʿtāt, Vitae of Saints and Martyrs (for the months from Tāḫśāś to Naḥāse) (fols. 2ra-270vb), incomplete, fols. misplaced&#xD;
I-1) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-ʾAnqiṭos “Vita and Martyrdom of ʾAnqiṭos” (for 12th Tāḫśāś) (fols. 2ra-13rb)&#xD;
I-2) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Märbǝhnam wa-za-ʾǝḫǝtu Sara “Vita and Martyrdom of Märbǝhnam and his sister Sara” (for 14th Tāḫśāś) (fols. 13vb-23rb), including 13 miracles (fols. 19ra-23rb)&#xD;
I-3) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Gorgorewos  liqa ṗāṗāsāt za-ʾArmanya “Vita and Martyrdom of Gregory, Bishop of Armenia” (for 15th Tāḫśāś) (fols. 23va-31vb)&#xD;
I-4) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Ṣādǝqānä Kädiḥ “Vita and Martyrdom of the Righteous Ones of Kädiḥ” (for 18th Tāḫśāś) (fols. 32ra-35vb), including 2 miracles (fols. 32vb-35vb)&#xD;
I-5) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Yoḥannǝs qasis  “Vita and martyrdom of John the Priest” (for 25th Tāḫśāś) (fols. 36ra-41vb)&#xD;
I-6) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Fiqṭor za-ʾAnṣokiya “Vita and Martyrdom of Victor of Antioch” (for 27th Miyāzyā) (fols. 42ra-49vb, 162ra-167vb)&#xD;
I-7) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-ʾabba ʾAbsadi wa-ʿAllaniqos ʾeṗis qoṗosat za-Gǝbǝṣ “Vita and Martyrdom of ʾAbsadi and Hellanicus, Bishops of Egypt” (for 27th Tāḫśāś) (fols. 50ra-53vb)&#xD;
I-8) “How the relies of St Stephen were found”, written by the priest Lucian (Luqyanos) (fols. 54ra-57vb)&#xD;
I-9) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Tewodros za-ʾAnṣokiya “Vita and Martyrdom of Theodore of Antioch” (for 12th Ṭǝrr) (fols. 58ra-65vb, 74ra-82rb)&#xD;
I-10) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Qirqos wa-ʾǝmmu ʾIyäluṭa “Vita and Martyrdom of Cyricus and his Mother Julitta” (for 15th Ṭǝrr) (fols. 91va-96vb, 269ra-vb, 66ra-72rb)&#xD;
I-11) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Ṭeqäla wa-4-dänagǝl ʾellä mǝsleha “Vita and Martyrdom of Thecla and 4 Virgins who were with her” (30th of Ṭǝrr) (fols. 72va-73vb, 97ra-98rb)&#xD;
I-12) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-7-däqiq [za-ʾEfeson] “Vita and Martyrdom of the 7 Youths (of ʾEfeson)” (for 13th of Ṭǝrr) (fols. 82va-89rb)&#xD;
I-13) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-ʾƎmrayǝs “Vita and Martyrdom of ʾƎmrayǝs” (for 14th Ṭǝrr) (fols. 89va-91ra)&#xD;
I-14) Gadl wa-sǝmʾ za-ʾOrni “Vita and martyrdom of ʾOrni” (for 30th Ṭǝrr) (fols. 98va-105vb, 114ra-rb)&#xD;
I-15) Gadl wa-sǝmʾ za-Ṗilaṭos “Vita and Martyrdom of Pilate” (for ?) (fols. 107ra-107vb (?), 106ra-106vb, 108ra-113rb, incomplete, fols. missing before fol. 107ra)&#xD;
I-16) Gadl wa-sǝmʾ za-ʾAtnasewos “Vita and Martyrdom of Athanasius”(for 18th Ḥamle) (fols. 113va-vb, 194ra-196vb)&#xD;
I-17) Gadl wa-sǝmʾ za-ʾAbuqir wa-Yoḥannǝs ʾǝḫuhu wa-śalastu dänagǝl “Vita and Martyrdom of ʾAbuqir, his brother John and three virgins” (for 6th Yakkātit) (fols. 114va-120rb), including a miracle (fols. 117va-120rb)&#xD;
I-18) Gadl wa-sǝmʾ za-Filmon “Vita and Martyrdom of Philemon” (for 20th? Yakkātit) (fols. 121ra-127rb)&#xD;
I-19) Gadl wa-sǝmʾ za-Tewodoṭos “Vita and Martyrdom of Theodotus” (for 7th Maggābit) (fols. 127va-133va)&#xD;
I-20) Gadl wa-sǝmʾ za-40 ḥara za-Qäṗädoqya “Vita and Martyrdom of 40 soldiers of Cappadocia” (፵፡ ሐራ፡ እለ፡ ተኰነኑ፡ በቀጰዶቅያ: …) (for 13th Maggābit) (fols. 133vb-139vb)&#xD;
I-21) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Tewoqriṭos ʾAnagnosṭis “Vita and Martyrdom of Theocritus the Reader” (for 17th Maggābit) (fols. 140ra-150va)&#xD;
I-22) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Giyorgis “Vita and Martyrdom of George” (for 23th Miyāzyā) (fols. 150vb-161vb, 208ra), followed by an appendix on the Jews (በፍቅሩ፡ ለጊዮርጊስ፡ ዘአምነት፡ አይሁዳዊት፡ ወእምአዋልደ፡ እስራኤል፡…) (cp. also Orient. 686, fol. 178ra) (fols. 208ra-208vb)&#xD;
I-23) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Yoḥannǝs za-Sǝnhut “Vita and Martyrdom of John from Sǝnhut” (for 8th Gǝnbot)” (fols. 168ra-176rb)&#xD;
I-24) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-ʾAfǝmya “Vita and Martyrdom of Euphemia” (for 11th Gǝnbot) (fols. 176va-182ra)&#xD;
I-25) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-[ḥara] ʾArǝrinosofis wa-Ṗeṭros wa-ʾƎskǝryon (“Vita and Martyrdom of the soldiers ʾArsenofis, Peter and ʾƎskǝryon” (cp. Orient. 686, fol. 233vc) (for 19th Sane) (fols. 182rb-187va)&#xD;
I-26) Homily on the martyrdom of the prefect Pilate (“Ṗilaṭos mäsfǝn”) from “Rome”, by St Cyriacus of Behnesa (for 25 Sane) (ድርሳን፡ ዘደረሰ፡ አቡነ፡ ቅዱስ፡ ወብፁዕ፡ አባ፡ ህርያቆስ፡ ዘሀገረ፡ ብህነሴ፡ በእንተ፡ ዘኮነ፡ ስምዐ፡ ጲላጦስ፡ መስፍን፡ በብሔረ፡ ሮሜ፡...) (fols. 188ra-193vb, incomplete [text missing after fol. 193vb])&#xD;
I-27) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-ʾabba Nob za-Nǝhisa “Vita and Martyrdom of <roleName type="title">ʾabbā</roleName> Nob from Nǝhisa” (for 24th Ḥamle) (fols. 197ra-201vb, 212ra-222rb)&#xD;
I-28) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Yoḥannǝs walda Ḍärabi “Vita and Martyrdom of John, the son of Serapion" (fols. 202ra-207vb, 209ra-rb) (cp. Orient. 686, fol. 215r)&#xD;
I-29) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Ṗisṭis, ʾAlaṗis wa-ʾAgaṗis wa-ʾǝmmon Sofya “Vita and Martyrdom of Pistis, Elpis and Agape and their Mother Sophia” (for the 1st Naḥāse) (fols. 223ra-228vb)&#xD;
I-30) Gadl wa- sǝmʿ za-Mäkǝbyu wa-[7]-däqiqa (ba-hagärä ʾAnṣokiya)” Vita and Martyrdom of Maccabees and her 7 sons (at Antioch)” (for 8th of Naḥāse) (fols. 229ra-236ra)&#xD;
I-31) Gadl wa- sǝmʿ za-Ḥarusṭǝfurus wa-2-ʾanǝst “Vita and Martyrdom of Christopher and Two Women” (for 10th Naḥāse) (fols. 236rb-239vb, 257ra-257vb)&#xD;
I-32) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Krǝsṭina walatta Rǝbänos “Vita and Martyrdom of Chistina, Daughter of Rǝbänos” [for 15th Naḥāse] (fols. 262va-vb, 246ra-vb, 256ra-vb, 239ra-245vb, 263ra-va)&#xD;
I-33) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-ʾƎnṭawos “Vita and Martyrdom of ʾƎnṭawos” [for 17th Naḥāse] (fols. 263vb, 247ra-252vb, 254ra-rb l.10)&#xD;
I-34) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-ʾƎndryanos wa-bǝʾǝsitu ʾƎnṭilya wa-kalǝʾan 24 “Vita and Martyrdom of Adrian, his wife Anatolia, and 24 others” (for 25th Naḥāse) (fols. 254ra-255vb, 264ra-266vb, 268ra-268vb, 267ra-267vb, incomplete [text missing between fol. 255vb and fol. 264ra = Orient. 686, fols. 282ra l.31-283ra l.32])&#xD;
I-35) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Basǝliqos “Vita and Martyrdom of Basǝliqos” (for the 14th Naḥāse) (fols. 258ra-262rb)&#xD;
I-36) Gadl wa-sǝmʿ za-Hernewos ṗāṗās za-Sorǝm “Vita and Martyrdom of Irenaeus of Sirmium” (for 29th Naḥāse) (fols. 270ra-va)&#xD;
&#xD;
Additiones 1-2.</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     
                     <incipit>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en"/>
                     </incipit>
                     <explicit>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en"/>
                     </explicit>
                     <note/>
                  </msItem>
                  <!--The data in the items below refers to other items. please remove this items and move the information to the appropriate place.-->
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2">
                     <note>- Some folios are missing and many are misplaced.</note>
                     <note>For the reconstruction of the texts, the following Mss., containing almost the same texts or some of them, have been consulted and compared with<ref type="mss" corresp="ESaqg005">AQG-005</ref>: Orient. 686 (cp. WrBriMus 167, no. 257), Orient.<ref type="mss" corresp="ES687688">687-688</ref>(cp. WrBriMus 167, no. 257). The Catalague of Wright (WrBriMus) has been used as reference for some of the saints names and the commemoration dates.</note>
                     <note>- On fol. 270va-vb, after Text I-36, a long Subscriptio concludes the entire work:</note>
                     <note>[fol. 270va] ተፈጸመ፡ በዝየ፡ ገድሎሙ፡ ለቅዱሳን፡ ሰማዕት፡ እለ፡ ተሣየጡ፡ በሞት፡ ሕይወት፨ ... ወአጽሐፊሁሰ፡ ለዝንቱ፡ መጽሓፍ፡ አቡነ፡ &lt;…&gt; ረባን፡ አበ፡ መነኮሳት፡ ... [fol. 270vb] ምስለ፡ ጸሓፊሁ፡ ሳሙኤል፡ … ወምስለ፡ አኃው፡ ዘደብረ፡&lt;…&gt; ….</note>
                     <note>The note mentions the commissioner, whose name here is erased. He must be the afore mentioned <roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName> Ṗeṭros who is mentioned in the exhortations throughout the Ms. In the subscriptio, after the erasure there are the titles räban (“master”; s. also on fol. 262rb) and ʾabä mänäkosat (“the head of the monks”). They are probably referred to Filǝṗṗos (s. above), the <roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName> Ṗeṭros' "father". At the end of the note, there is the mention of the scribe Sāmuʾel, to whom some of the exhortations are dedicated, and of the "brothers of the däbr" from where most probably also the commissioner and the scribe come.</note>
                     <note/>
                     <note>- Some of the gädl (i.e. I-1, I-2, I-10, I-13, I-14, I-15, I-17, I-21, I-22, I-23, I-27, I-28 ) end with a final note with the concluding formula “ተፈጸመ፡ (or ተፈጸመ፡ ብዝየ፡) ገድሉ፡…” of the text, followed sometimes by the commemoration dates of the saints to whom the text is dedicated, or also by supplication formulas.</note>
                     <note>These final notes are alone or are followed by exhortation notes, short or extended, (ጸልዩ፡ ለዘ…) for the commissioner (sometimes also for his children, or for the children of his place), for the scribe, the reader, the translator of the gädl, and for the ones who believe and make the “tazkār” of the saints to whom the gädl is dedicated. These exhortations are after the majority of the texts (i.e. I-1, I-2 I-3 I-4 I-5, I-6 I-8, I-9, I-10 I-11, I-12, I-13, I-16, I-17, I-18, I-19, I-20, I-21, I-23, I-24, I-25, I-27, I-29, I-30, I-31, I-32, I-33, I-34, I-35).</note>
                     <note/>
                     <note>- About the scribe and the mention of his name in the above mentioned exhortation notes, s. above in “short content”. On fol. 23rb, in the exhortation at the end of Text I-2, the name of the scribe has been erased.</note>
                     <note>- In the exhortation notes on fols. 89rb, 91ra, 98rb, 114rb, 120ra, 127rb, respectively at the end of Texts I-12, I-13, I-11, I-14, I-17, I-18, the commissioner, <roleName type="title">ʾAbuna</roleName> Ṗeṭros, is said to be “lover of the Gadla sämaˤtat” (መፍቀሬ፡ ገድሎሙ፡ ለሰማዕታት).</note>
                     <note>On fol. 127rb, it is also written that he is the “master of the ‘temple’” (መምህረ፡ አላዳስ).</note>
                     <note>On fols. 41vb,150va, he is mentioned as: <roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName> Ṗeṭros za-Dabra Mämhǝr.</note>
                     <note>About the mention of the commissioner on the other folios, s. above in “short content”.</note>
                     <note/>
                     <note>Details on some texts:</note>
                     <note>- Text I-4. The miracles are not numbered.</note>
                     <note>- Text I-25. On fol. 187va, at the end of the text, as the month of the commemoration date for the martyrs ʾArǝrinosofis, Peter and ʾƎskǝryon, is written Ṗäsini (ጰሲኒ), instead of the Ethiopian name ሰኔ.</note>
                     <note>Comparing the same text in, e.g., Orient. 686, the month at the same passage is written as Ṗahin/Ṗaḥin (ጳሂን/ጳሒን). Ṗaḥin (c. Dillmann Lexicon, p. 1251) is the Ethiopian name for Paōni, the 10th month of the Coptic Calendar, which corresponds to the Ethiopian month Sane.</note>
                     <note>In the text of<ref type="mss" corresp="ESaqg005">AQG-005</ref>, Ṗäsini might appear phonetically more similar to the 9th month (in Sahidic) of the Coptic calendar, i.e. Pašons (s. CE II, 439). It also look as if it is an assimilation (scribe mistake?) of ጰ (from the Coptic month) and ሲኒ (from ሰኔ).</note>
                     <note>At the left margin of the Coptic month, probably as cue for the rubricator, is annotated the letter ግ.</note>
                     <note>- Text I-27. On fol. 222rb, the text ends with the colophon of the work with the mention of Metropolitan <roleName type="title">ʾAbbā</roleName> salāma (Metropolitan from 1350 or 1348; cp. EAE IV, 488-89) and its work of translation from Arabic into Gǝˤǝz.</note>
                     <note>At the end of the colophon, the date “1079 from the ‘Years of the Martyrs’ (እመዋዕለ፡ ሰማዕት)” is indicated. It is not clear if it refers to the year when <roleName type="title">ʾAbbā</roleName> salāma translated the text. According to the “Chronologie” of Chaine, this date, 1079 E.M.D., should corresponds to 1363 A.D. (cp. ChChron, 161).</note>
                     <note>- Text I-16. On fol. 196va, at the end of text, as month of the commemoration date of the martyr ʾAtnasewos, it is given the month ʾIyolyu (ኢዮልዩ) and after it Ḥamle, mentioned as the correspondent month in Gǝˤǝz. ʾIyolyu appears phonetically very similar to “Iulius”, the Latin name for the month July.</note>
                     <note>- Text I-30. On fol. 236ra, at the end of text, as month of the commemoration date of the martyr Maccabees and her 7 sons, it is written ʾAwgusṭos (አውግስጦስ). This name is mentioned as month in the byzantine calendar (በአውራኅ፡ ሮሜ); the same is on fol. 273rb in Orient. 686.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <material key="parchment"/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>Made of <measure unit="leaf">270.0</measure> folios, of which
                                                  <measure unit="leaf" type="blank"/> blank
                                                  1r, 91rb, 222v, 253r, in
                                                  <measure unit="quire"/> quires . 
                                                <dimensions type="outer">
                              <height unit="cm">40.5</height>
                              <width unit="cm">26.5</width>
                              <depth unit="cm">16.5</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <foliation><!--2016-10-18+02:00 Updated AQG-005 from DomLib--></foliation>
                        <collation>
                           <signatures>
                              <note>- Quire marks (recent?) are written (in black) in the upper left margin of a few fols.: &#xD;
fol. 74r: ፰; fol. 82r: ፱; fol. 122r: ፲፬; fol. 130r: ፲፭; fol. 146r: ፲፯.</note>
                           </signatures>
                           <list>
                              <item xml:id="q1">The structure of quires cannot be determined due to the poor condition of the Ms.</item>
                           </list>
                        </collation>
                        <condition key="deficient">The front board is broken and the back is missing; the original sewing is for the most part missing. The Ms. has been wrongly rearranged and resewn.&#xD;
Many fols. are missing and some are misplaced. &#xD;
Many fols. are affected by humidity and stained with dirt; some parts of text are illegible (e.g., fols. 177rb, 177ra, 267va, 268rb).&#xD;
The bottom part of fols. 242-268 seems damaged by rodents.&#xD;
f. 1 is damaged.&#xD;
Cuts repaired, e.g., on fols. 67, 149, 174, 221.&#xD;
Some fols. seem to have been cut at the bottom: e.g., fols. 123, 128, 133, 134.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" writtenLines="36">
                           <dimensions unit="mm">
                              <height>310</height>
                              <width>210</width>
                              <dim type="intercolumn">20</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="margin">
                              <dim type="top">32</dim>
                              <dim type="bottom">66</dim>
                              <dim type="right">48</dim>
                              <dim type="left">16</dim>
                              <dim type="intercolumn">20</dim>
                           </dimensions>
                           <note>All data are for fol. 3r</note>
                           <ab type="ruling">the number of the lines is very irregular</ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">Pricking and ruling are visible.</ab>
                           <ab type="ruling" subtype="pattern">
Ruling pattern: 1A-1A-1A1A/0-0/0-0/C.</ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">
Primary pricks are visible.</ab>
                           <ab type="pricking">
Ruling pricks are visible.</ab>
                           <ab type="ruling">
The upper line is written below the ruling (above on many fols., e.g. 1-59, 65, 74-81, 107-112, 115r-119r, 201-208).</ab>
                           <ab type="ruling">
The bottom line is written above the ruling.</ab>
                           <ab>
One or two upper ruled lines were not used by the scribe on fols. 98r, 114r, 227r, 234v, 235r.</ab>
                        </layout>
                        <layout>
                           <ab type="CruxAnsata">
                              <locus target=""/>
                           </ab>
                           <ab type="coronis">
                              <locus target="#23r #57v #120r"/>
                           </ab>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><!--ACHTUNG! first HandNote comes from writing system in Ethiospare. the others are one for each CHANGE OF HAND-->
                     <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                        <seg type="script">Irregular</seg>
                        <seg type="ink">Black; red (vivid vermillion).</seg>
                        <persName role="scribe" ref="PRS00000">Sāmuʾel</persName>Sāmuʾel is mentioned as the scribe in the exhortation after Texts I-27 (fol. 222rb), I-33 (fol. 254rb), I-34 (fol. 267vb) and in the subscriptio at the end of Text I-36 (fol. 271vb).&#xD;
In the exhortation on fol. 176rb, the name of Sāmuʾel has been written over erasure (not sure if later).<date>Second half of 15th century (?)</date>
                     </handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h2" script="Ethiopic">The handwriting is characterized by thick strokes and right-sloping letters. It is possible that several hands were involved in writing (cp. fols. 25v-26r).<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h3" script="Ethiopic">
Some peculiar features:<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h4" script="Ethiopic">
Letters:<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h5" script="Ethiopic">
- ጵ has the 6th order marker set up on the vertical stroke at the top, oriented to the left (e.g., fols. 67vb l.18, 152rb l.1)<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h6" script="Ethiopic">
- ሎ has the 7th order marker attached directly at the body of the letter, without linking line (e.g., fol. 13rb l.4)<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h7" script="Ethiopic">
- the upper horizontal strokes of መ and ሠ, in the 1st order, are slanted to the left<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h8" script="Ethiopic">
- the 6th order marker of the letter የ has a very short and downwards oriented left part, going down below the ruling (e.g., fols. 209ra l.4, 225va l.14); in the 4th order, the marker is short as well and diagonal (e.g., fols. 229va l.11, l.16, 98rb l.11)<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h9" script="Ethiopic">
- ኴ has the loop marking the 5th order open (fol. 225ra l.1, l.8).<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h10" script="Ethiopic">
Numbers:<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h11" script="Ethiopic">
- the numbers are mostly written without dashes <!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h12" script="Ethiopic">
- ፬ is triangular and downwards oriented (e.g., fol. 23ra)<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h13" script="Ethiopic">
- ፮ is with the loop open, looking like “compressed” ፯ (e.g., fol. 35vb)<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h14" script="Ethiopic">
- ፪ has the loops closed, not separated<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h15" script="Ethiopic">
- ፼ has the ligature (e.g., fol. 18rb).<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h16" script="Ethiopic">
Punctuation:<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h17" script="Ethiopic">
- Crux ansata and coronis (together or separated) are in the margins of some texts: on fol. 182r, the crux ansata with coronis marking the beginning; on fols. 23r, 57v, 120r, 139v, the coronis used as caesura<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h18" script="Ethiopic">
- sentence dividers are accompanied by the paragraph signs (throughout the Ms.).<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h19" script="Ethiopic">
Other:<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h20" script="Ethiopic">
- The word እግዚአብሔር is usually written እግዚኣብሐር (the second አ in the 4th order). The same word sometimes is written with the ligature (e.g., fol. 113rb l.28)<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="h21" script="Ethiopic">
- the size of the letters and columns (s., e.g., fols. 25v-26r).<!--The names of this hands need to be replaced by appropriate refs.--></handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote type="rubrication" xml:id="d0">Name of St Mary; name of the commissioner; a few lines, or groups of lines, alternating with black lines, on the incipit (or incipit page) of the texts; the numbers and title of the miracles in Text I-2; the initial words of some subsections; the word haleluya on fol. 163vb; Ethiopic numerals and sometimes their elements; elements of punctuation signs and of coronis; crux ansata with coronis on fol. 182r.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="frame" xml:id="d1">f. 2r (incipit page of Text I-1): elaborate, coloured (red, blue, yellow, white), ornamental frame, with an horizontal band reaching the top of the page, and three vertical extensions reaching a second horizontal band at the bottom of the page; interlaces.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="frame" xml:id="d2">ff. 13v, 23v, 32r, 36r, 50r, 54r, 58r, 72v, 82v, 89v, 91v, 98v, 113v, 114va, 127v, 133vb, 140ra, 150vb, 168r, 176v, 188r, 197r, 202r, 223r, 229r, 258r, 262v (incipit or incipit pages of Texts I-2, I-3, I-4, I-5, I-7, I-8, I-9, I-11, I-12, I-13, I-10, I-14, I-16 I-17, I-19, I-20, I-21, I-22, I-23, I-24, I-26, I-27; I-28, I-29, I-30, I-35, I-32): coloured (red, green, blue, yellow, white), ornamental band, with three vertical extensions reaching the middle of the page; the horizontal band reaches the top of the page; interlaces, crosses.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="frame" xml:id="d3">f. 42r (incipit page of Text I-6): elaborate, coloured (red, green, yellow, white), ornamental band with three vertical extensions reaching the bottom of the page; the horizontal band extends to the top of the page; interlaces, crosses, geometric motifs.</decoNote>
                     <decoNote type="frame" xml:id="d4">ff. 121ra, 182rb, 236rb, 263vb, 270r (incipits or incipit page of Texts I-18, I-25, I-31, I-33, I-36): simple, coloured (red, blue, yellow, white) ornamental band; interlaces.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions><!--THIS element in domlib CONTAINS ESCAPED HTML, thus it is not possible to reliably extract the information about pages. Please watch out.-->
                     <list>
                        <item xml:id="a1">
                           <locus target="#120va">f. 120va</locus>-vb: Exhortation to pray for priest Thomas.<quote xml:lang="gez">f. 120va: ጸልዩ፡ ሎቱ፡ አንትሙ፡ ውሉደ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ ዓቢይ፡ ወንኡስ፡ በኅብረተ፡ መንፈስ፡ ቅዱስ፡ ለአቡክሙ፡ ቶማስ፡ ቀሲስ።…</quote>
                           <quote xml:lang="en"/>
                           The note is written in a more recent secondary hand.
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a2">
                           <locus target="#253v&lt;">f. 253v</locus>: Ownership note. <quote xml:lang="gez">f. 253v: ዝመጽሐፍ፡ ዘአድ፡ ቋልቋል፡ ዘቅዱስ፡ ጊዮርጊስ፡ ዘተሳየጦ፡ በወርቁ፡ ክፍ[sic] ዘአቡነ፡ [ገብረ፡ክር]ስቶስ፡</quote>
                           <quote xml:lang="en"/>
                           The note, partly unclear and possibly unfinished, has been written within the frame of the ornamental cross (above left side).
The note states that the book is property of the church of ʿAddi Qolqwal Giyorgis (ʾAd Qwalqwal), purchased  by <roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName> Gabra Krǝstos. Additio 2 of AQG-003 is written in the same hand.
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e1">- The note ገድለ፡ ሰማዕታት፡ ብርእየ፡ ሥመሪ፡ is written in the bottom margin of fol. 51r, probably in a secondary hand.&#xD;
- The title ገድለ፡ ሰማዕ[sic] is written, in a secondary hand, at the edge of the bottom margin on fol. 73r.&#xD;
- f. 120vb:  crude and recent note, after Text I-17, repeating the incipit of Text I-18 on fol. 121ra. &#xD;
- Cues for the rubricator (numerals) throughout the Ms.&#xD;
- Corrections (words or letters) written interlineally: fols. 58rb, 60va, 74ra, 135va.&#xD;
- Correction written over erasure: fol. 38ra.&#xD;
- Compressed script: fols. 35vb, 41va, 53vb, 89rb, 113rb, 263va.&#xD;
- Pen trial: fol. 222v.&#xD;
- Crude notes and drawings in pen or pencil in the margins and on the inner front board: e.g., fols. 12r, 18r, 31r, 32r, 57r, 75r, 137r, 143r, 202r.</item>
                     </list>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding contemporary="partly">
                        <decoNote xml:id="b1">Two wooden boards (the front bord is broken; the back is missing)&#xD;
Two pairs of sewing stations.</decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b2" type="bindingMaterial">
                           <material key="wood"/>
                        </decoNote>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b3" type="Endbands"/>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b4" type="Other">Some of the quires are reinforced by parchment guards.&#xD;
On the front board possibly traces of leather cover.&#xD;
Recent threads for the sewing are visible on some fols. (e.g., between fols. 55v-56r and on fols. 122v, 123v, 125v, 144v).</decoNote>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <placeName ref="INS0097AQG">ʿAddi Qolqwal Giyorgis / AQG</placeName>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate notBefore="1450" notAfter="1500">If we suppose that the Ms. was commissioned by <roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName> Ṗeṭros from Dabra Bizän (s. above), the date of its production may be collocated in the second half of the 15th century.</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <listBibl type="catalogue">                               
                              <bibl>
                                 <ptr target="bm:EthioSpare"/>
                              </bibl>                            
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <custodialHist>
                        <custEvent type="restorations" subtype="modern"/>
                     </custodialHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  
                  
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Encoded according to TEI P5 Guidelines.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person>
                  <persName role="owner" ref="PRS0000">
                     <roleName type="title">ʾAbuna</roleName> Ṗeṭros is mentioned as the commissioner in the subscriptio at the end of Text I-36 and in the exhortations at the end of the most texts. In many of them, his name is mentioned together with the name of his monastery (i.e. <roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName> Ṗeṭros za-Dabra &lt;…&gt;), which is however always partly erased. On fol. 13rb (Text I-1) the last letter of the name is readable(ደብረ፡ &lt;…&gt;ን).&#xD;
On fols. 228vb, 254ra, 262rb, it is said that he is the son (disciple) of <roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName> Filǝṗos, named the “righteous” (“ṣadǝq”, fol. 254rb) and the “teacher” (“räban”, fols. 262rb, 270va). Considering this date and the small clue on fol. 13rb, it might be possible suppose that the monastery of <roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName> Ṗeṭros and where this Ms. was originated is Dabra Bizän (in Eritrea). The founder of this monastery was the monk Filǝṗos (1322/23-1406; cp. EAE II, 15-17). &#xD;
On fol. 57vb, <roleName type="title">ʾabuna</roleName> Ṗeṭros is mentioned as the abbot (ʾabä mǝnet) of his monastery.&#xD;
According to an additional note in a Bible Ms. from Dabra Bizän, Ṗeṭros is mentioned as the 4th “mamhǝr” of the monastery, third successor of the founder Filǝṗos. His death is to be collocated between 1488/89 and   1491/92. His predecessor was Säräqä Bǝrhān (d. 1460/61 or 1457/58) (cp. Schneider, in AÉ 1978, 138-39).</persName>
                  <!--ACHTUNG! This is actually paragraphic information identifying the donor. 
                                        Person/persName should only contain the person name, not all the paragraph.-->
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName role="scribe" ref="PRS00000">Sāmuʾel</persName>
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName role="owner" ref="PRS0000">As mentioned in Additio 2, the owner of the book is the church of ʿAddi Qolqwal Giyorgis.</persName>
                  <!--ACHTUNG! This is actually paragraphic information identifying the donor. 
                                        Person/persName should only contain the person name, not all the paragraph.-->
               </person>
               <person>
                  <persName ref="PRS00000"/>
                  <!--other-->
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#ethioauthlist">
               <term key="Hagiography"/>
               <term key="Homily"/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Inglese</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez" xml:id="Lan05">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="DN" when="2010-11-18">registered</change>
         <change who="VP" when="2014-09-23">created</change>
         <change who="DN" when="2015-11-07">last edited</change>
         <change who="PL" when="2016-05-10">transformed from mycore to TEI
                            P5</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
