<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="ESum050"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="mss">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fragments of ten various manuscripts</title>
            <editor key="DN"/>
            <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p>
                                    This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                    Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2016-06-07T17:47:46.601+02:00</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0017UM"/>
                  <collection>Ethio-SPaRe</collection>
                  <idno>UM-050</idno>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <idno>C3-IV-81 (on the front board)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>I-1) Homily by the Orthodox on St John the Baptist (fols. 43r-44v, possibly fragments of two different texts from the same Ms.), hand a (28 lines)&#xD;
II) Homilies (fols. 45r-122v), hand b (identical to hand e of UM-045) (25 lines)&#xD;
II-1) Possibly the Homily by Jacob for the third Sunday in Lent (fols. 45r-59ra) (cp. Orient. 8192, 5.)&#xD;
II-2) Homily on Lent, for the third Sunday in Lent (fols. 59rb-66vb) (cp. Orient. 8192, 6.)&#xD;
II-3) Homily by John Chrysostom for the fourth Sunday in Lent (fols. 66vb-69ra) (cp. Orient. 8192, 7.)&#xD;
II-4) Homily by the Orthodox on Lent, for the fourth Sunday in Lent (69ra-73ra) (cp. Orient. 8192, 8.)&#xD;
II-5) Homily by Gregory of Antioch for the fifth Sunday in Lent (fols. 73ra-79ra) (cp. Orient. 8192, 9.)&#xD;
II-6) Homily for the Friday of the sixth week in Lent (fols. 79ra-84vb) (Orient. 8192, 10.; beginning in the same way, without title) &#xD;
II-7) Homily for the Saturday of the sixth week in Lent (fols. 73ra-85vb) (cp. Orient. 8192, 11.)&#xD;
II-8) Homily by Jacob (ʾabba Yāʿqob) for the Sunday of the sixth week in Lent (fols. 85vb-91ra) (Orient. 8192, 12.)&#xD;
II-9) Homily by the Orthodox for Palm Sunday (fols. 91ra-97ra) (cp. Orient. 8192, 13.)&#xD;
II-10) Homily by ʾabbā ʾEfrem for reading at the service on Holy Thursday (fols. 97ra-103vb) (cp. Orient. 8192, 14.)&#xD;
III) Martyrdom of St George of Lydda (fols. 98rv, 142r-148v), hand c (27-28 lines) (identical to hand d of UM-045) (cp. E.A.W. BUDGE, The History of George of Lydda, the patron Saint of England, London 1930, respectively pp. 89 l.17-91 l. 4 and pp. 96 l. 12-108 l. 18)&#xD;
II-11) Homily by ʾabbā ʾEfrem for reading at the service on Holy Thursday (fols. 97ra-103vb) (cp. Orient. 8192, 14)&#xD;
II-12) Homily by ʾabbā ʾEfrem for Easter Eve (fols. 103vb-107vb) (cp. Orient. 8192, 15., beginning in the same way), in full&#xD;
II-13) Homily by the Orthodox for Easter Sunday (fols. 107vb-118va) (cp. Orient. 8192, 16.), in full&#xD;
II-14) Homily on the Suffering of Jesus Christ for Monday in Easter-week (fols. 118vb-122va, fol. 122 is loose), incomplete (cp. Orient. 8192, 17.)&#xD;
I-2) Text containing God’s promises to Israel (fol. 123rv, a loose leaf), hand a (27 lines in a column)&#xD;
IV-1) Homily by Cyril (Gerlos) Patriarch of Jerusalem on the Resurrection of Jesus Christ (fol. 124r-131v, after the incipit page, the biggest part possibly missing), hand d (25 lines)&#xD;
IV-2) Discourse by John Chrysostom on the life and decollation of John the Baptist (fols. 126r-132v), possibly almost complete, hand d&#xD;
V-1) A homily for Easter (fol. 133rv), ancient hand e &#xD;
VI-1) 2 Kings (fol. 134rv), ancient hand f (similar but not identical with hand a of UM-045)&#xD;
IV-3) Maṣḥafa lәdäta la-Māryām “Book of the Nativity of Mary” (fols. 135, 136va-141v), end missing, hand d (Cp. M. CHAINE, Apocrypha de Beata Maria Virgine, Romae 1909 [CSCO 39, 40 (SAe 22, 23)], “Liber nativitatis Mariae”; the correct sequence is fols. 136va-141v, 135)&#xD;
IV-4) Martyrdom of Theocritus the Reader, commemorated on 17 Maggābit (fol. 136r-va), end part and explicit, hand d&#xD;
VII-1) Text concerning ʾabbā Yoḥannǝs (?) (fol. 149rv): &#xD;
hand g (28 lines)&#xD;
VIII-1) The Finding of the Holy Cross by St Helena (?) (fols. 150r-152r, explicit), hand h (35 lines)&#xD;
V-2) Unidentified homily (fol. 152rv), ancient hand e &#xD;
(31 lines)&#xD;
IX-1) 2 Kings 18:32-19:15 (fol. 153rv), ancient hand j (35 lines) (identical to the hand of UM-058, the text follows on UM-058 fol. 66rv)&#xD;
I-3) Text concerning the Nativity of John the Baptist (fol. 154rv), hand a (28 lines)&#xD;
I-4) Prayer concerning Yoḥannǝs (Maṭmǝq) (?) (fol. 155rv): hand a (?) (27 lines)&#xD;
V-3) Homily by John Chrysostom on Easter Sunday (fols. 156ra-161ra), in full (?), ancient hand e (32 lines) (cp. BerPrKult orient. fol. 3075 no. 17, HamSixBerl 1, 298-99)&#xD;
V-4) Homily by an anonymous author on Easter (fols. 161ra-161vb), 16th-cent. hand k; the text is written in empty space after Text V-3, and may be the beginning of the following text (which had been acephalous, originally or though the loss of leaves)&#xD;
V-5) Unidentified homily (fols. 162r-167v), acephalos (but cp. above), ancient hand e (31 lines)&#xD;
X) Text concerning Archangel Michael, the Vision of Daniel and the Three Holy Children (fol. 168r-169v), hand l (28 lines)&#xD;
V-6) Unidentified homily (fols. 171r-177v), end part and explicit, ancient hand e (31 lines)&#xD;
V-7) A homily of Jacob (of Sarug?) (fol. 177vb), heading only, ancient hand e&#xD;
V-8) Unidentified homily (fols. 172ra-173ra), explicit, ancient hand e&#xD;
V-8) Homily by John Chrysostom on penance (fols. 173ra-185v), ancient hand e (cp. BerPrKult orient. fol. 3075 no. 25, HamSixBerl 1, 300) &#xD;
I-2) Text concerning John the Baptist (fols. 186r-187v): hand a (28 lines)&#xD;
V-9) Unidentified homily (fols. 188ra-189rb), end part and explicit, ancient hand e (31 lines)&#xD;
V-10) Homily by Jacob of Serug on the Apostle Thomas (fols. 189r-194v), in full (?), ancient hand e (cp. EAE III, 262b)&#xD;
V-11) Homily by John Chrysostom on Lazarus (fols. 194va-197rb), in full (?), ancient hand e (cp. BerPrKult orient. fol. 3075 no. 20, HamSixBerl 1, 299; cp. EAE III, 293b)&#xD;
V-12) Homily by John Chrysostom on the Samaritan woman (cp. BerPrKult orient. fol. 3075 no. 21, HamSixBerl 1, 299; Orient. 774 fols. 126r-131r, EAE III, 293b), in full (?), ancient hand e&#xD;
V-13) Homily by John Theologus (Tewologos) on Easter Sunday (fols. 205vb-211vb), end and some fols. missing, ancient hand e (cp. Orient. 774, no. 22).</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     
                     <incipit>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en"/>
                     </incipit>
                     <explicit>
                        <foreign xml:lang="en"/>
                     </explicit>
                     <note/>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <material key=""/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>Made of <measure unit="leaf"/> folios, in
                                                  <measure unit="quire"/> quires . 
                                                
                        </extent>
                        <foliation><!--2016-10-18+02:00 Updated UM-050 from DomLib--></foliation>
                        <condition key="deficient">ff. 1-42 (fragment of a Four Gospels manuscript) are described as Ms. UM-50a. The fragment of ten manuscripts (<locus from="43" to="203">43-203</locus>) are loosely placed into the binding of UM-050a.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout/>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc><!--ACHTUNG! first HandNote comes from writing system in Ethiospare. the others are one for each CHANGE OF HAND-->
                     <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                        <seg type="script"/>
                        <seg type="ink"/>
                        <date/>
                     </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <binding>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b1"/>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b2" type="bindingMaterial"/>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b3" type="Endbands"/>
                        <decoNote xml:id="b4" type="Other"/>
                     </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>
                        <placeName ref="INS0017UM">ʿUra Qirqos / UQ</placeName>
                     </origPlace>
                     <origDate notBefore="1350" notAfter="1600"/>
                  </origin>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>
                           <listBibl type="catalogue">                               
                              <bibl>
                                 <ptr target="bm:EthioSpare"/>
                              </bibl>                            
                           </listBibl>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <custodialHist>
                        <custEvent type="restorations" subtype="none"/>
                     </custodialHist>
                  </adminInfo>
                  
                  <listBibl type="secondary">
                     <bibl/>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Encoded according to TEI P5 Guidelines.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person>
                  <persName ref="PRS00000"/>
                  <!--other-->
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#ethioauthlist">
               <term key="NewTestament"/>
               <term key="Hagiography"/>
               <term key="Homily"/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">Inglese</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez" xml:id="Lan05">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="DN" when="2010-04-30">registered</change>
         <change who="DN" when="2013-12-28">created</change>
         <change who="MV" when="2015-04-23">last edited</change>
         <change who="PL" when="2016-05-10">transformed from mycore to TEI
                            P5</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
