<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="EthWindsor3" xml:lang="en" type="mss">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> Discourses of the Archangels Michael, Gabriel, and Raphael</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                <editor key="ES"/>
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                            Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                                licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:id="ms">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="INS0976Windsor"/>
                        <idno facs="https://rct.resourcespace.com/iiif/1005081/">MS Eth. Windsor III</idno><!--  facs="EMIP/Codices/3488/" n="139" -->
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno>RCIN 1005081</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <altIdentifier><repository ref="INS0447EMIP"/><collection>EMIP</collection>
                            <idno>EMIP 3488</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents><summary>An Ethiopian manuscript of the Discourse of John Chrysostom in praise of the Archangels Michael, Gabriel and Raphael written in Geez, the ancient liturgical language of the Ethiopian church.
                        
                        St. John Chrysostom (347–407) was a Patriarchate (Archbishop) of Constantinople and one of the most important writers of the early Christian Church. His writings are thought to have been translated into Geez from the Greek by Syrian monks who founded monasteries in Ethiopia.
                        
                        The text was written by a single scribe and begins with a Discourse of John Chrysostom on the Four Beasts (ff. 2v-10v) and a painting of the Trinity (ff. 11r) followed by a Discourse for the festivals of the Archangel Michael by Demetrius, the second-third century Patriarch (Archbishop) of Alexandria (ff. 11v-62v); Miracles of the Archangel Michael (ff. 63r-81r); Discourses for the festivals of the Archangel Gabriel (ff. 82v-83r); Miracles of the Archangel Gabriel (ff. 83v-84r); the Discourse of John Chrysostom in praise of the Archangel Gabriel (ff. 84v-96v); the Discourse of Jacob of Serug (the fourth-fifth century Syriac theologian) in praise of the Archangel Gabriel (ff. 97r-101r); further discourses of the Archangel Gabriel followed by a double page illustration of the Annunciation and birth of Christ (ff.101v-117v); the Discourse of John Chrysostom in praise the Archangel Raphael (ff. 118r-131r); and Miracles of the Archangel of Raphael (ff. 131v-138v).
                        
                        52 paintings illustrate the volume which is bound in brown calf with blind stamped decoration over wooden boards with textile inlays on the inside covers. It was rebound and re-backed by the India Office in the late 19th century.
                    </summary></msContents>
                    <physDesc></physDesc>
                    <history><provenance>Previously owned by Walatta Iyasus, Walatta Negest and Walda Maryam.  Taken by
                        <persName ref="PRS9430Tewodros"/> and brought to <placeName ref="INS0101MadhaneAlam"/>. It was then bought by Richard Holmes during the British <persName ref="PRS7484Napier">Napier</persName> expedition in <date>1868</date> and later presented to Queen Victoria.</provenance></history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source>
                                    <listBibl type="catalogue">
                                        <bibl>
                                            <ptr target="bm:Ullendorff1953Windsor"/>
                                            <citedRange unit="page">75</citedRange>
                                        </bibl>
                                    </listBibl>
                                </source>
                            </recordHist>
                        </adminInfo>                        
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2022-04-25">Created entity</change>
            <change when="2022-01-10" who="ES">added EMIP ID and facs</change>
            <change when="2022-11-04" who="ES">added info and facs from https://www.rct.uk/collection/search#/4/collection/1005081/discourse-of-saint-john-chrysostom-in-praise-of-the-archangels-michael-gabriel</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography"/><!---->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>