<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="EthWindsor2" xml:lang="en" type="mss">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Discourse of John Chrisostom</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                <editor key="ES"/>
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                            Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                                licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:id="ms">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="INS0976Windsor"/>
                        <idno facs="https://rct.resourcespace.com/iiif/1005080/">MS Eth. Windsor II</idno><!-- facs="EMIP/Codices/3487/" n="104" -->
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno>RCIN 1005080</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <altIdentifier><repository ref="INS0447EMIP"/><collection>EMIP</collection>
                            <idno>EMIP 3487</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary>An Ethiopian manuscript of the Discourse of John Chrysostom in praise of St. John the Baptist written in Geez, the ancient liturgical language of the Ethiopian church.
                            
                            St. John Chrysostom (347–407) was a Patriarchate (Archbishop) of Constantinople and one of the most important writers of the early Christian Church. His writings are thought to have been translated into Geez from the Greek by Syrian monks who founded monasteries in Ethiopia.
                            
                            The main text (ff. 3v-33v) is a detailed memoir of St John the Baptist drawn from the canonical Gospels. The second part of the text (ff. 33v-57) is the ‘Retua Haymanot’ (The True Orthodoxy), also attributed to John Chrysostom, followed by a prayer of St John the Baptist (ff. 51r-56v). The remainder of the manuscript is another unknown text (ff. 56r-103r) followed by a colophon (ff. 104r-106v) which gives the name of the patron as Nabiya Leul. The whole manuscript is written in a fine, large hand without column divisions; 11 lines to a page.
                            
                            The volume is bound in brown calf with blind stamped decoration over wooden boards with textile inlays on the inside covers. Tooled decoration comprises two under-over box patterns with crosses at the centre. The manuscript was rebound and re-backed by the India Office in the late 19th century.
                            
                            This manuscript was among a group of an estimated 1000 manuscripts acquired from churches across Ethiopia by Emperor Tewodros II (d. 1868) intended for the church and library he planned to build at Maqdala, his fortress in Northern Ethiopia. In April 1868 British forces led by Lieutenant General Sir Robert Napier laid siege to the fortress to secure the release of British hostages held there (see RCIN 2500869) and Tewodros took his own life. Tewodros’s manuscripts, then stored in huts near his temporary church at Maqdala, were among the items subsequently auctioned as spoils of war. Many of these (approximately 400) were bought by Richard Holmes (see RCINs 917350-2 and 922419) who had been sent by the British Museum as part of the Abyssinian Expedition specifically to acquire antiquities and manuscripts in Ethiopia. Richard Holmes presented sixteen of the manuscripts to Queen Victoria who retained six for the Royal Library (RCINs 1005079-1005084) and in 1869 offered ten back to the Trustees of the British Museum. In 1973 those manuscripts were transferred to the British Library.
                        </summary>
                        <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                            <title>Discourse of John Chrysostom in praise of St. John the Baptist</title>
                            <textLang xml:lang="gez"></textLang>
                            <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.1">
                                <title>memoir of St John the Baptist drawn from the canonical Gospels</title>
                                <textLang xml:lang="gez"></textLang>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.2">
                                <title>Retua Haymanot</title>
                                <textLang xml:lang="gez"></textLang>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.3">
                                <title>prayer of St John the Baptist</title>
                                <textLang xml:lang="gez"></textLang>
                            </msItem>
                            <msItem xml:id="ms_i1.4">
                                <title>unknown</title>
                                <textLang xml:lang="gez"></textLang>
                            </msItem>
                            <colophon xml:id="coloph1">The colophon gives the name of the patron as Nabiya Leul</colophon>
                        </msItem>
                        
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc></physDesc>
                    <history><provenance>Commissioned by Nabiya Leul. Acquired  by
                        <persName ref="PRS9430Tewodros"/> and brought to <placeName ref="INS0101MadhaneAlam"/>. Bought by Richard Holmes during the British <persName ref="PRS7484Napier">Napier</persName> expedition in <date>1868</date> and later presented to Queen Victoria.</provenance></history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source>
                                    <listBibl type="catalogue">
                                        <bibl>
                                            <ptr target="bm:Ullendorff1953Windsor"/>
                                            <citedRange unit="page">74</citedRange>
                                        </bibl>
                                    </listBibl>
                                </source>
                            </recordHist>
                        </adminInfo>                        
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Homily"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2022-04-25">Created entity</change>
            <change when="2022-01-10" who="ES">added EMIP facs</change>
            <change when="2022-11-04" who="ES">added info and facs from https://www.rct.uk/collection/search#/1/collection/1005080/discourse-of-saint-john-chrysostom-in-praise-of-john-the-baptist-geez</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography"/><!---->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>