<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="EthWindsor4" xml:lang="en" type="mss">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Nagara Māryām</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB"/>
                <editor key="ES"/>
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                            Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                                licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:id="ms">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository ref="INS0976Windsor"/>
                        <idno facs="https://rct.resourcespace.com/iiif/1005082/">MS Eth. Windsor IV</idno><!-- facs="EMIP/Codices/3489/" n="323" -->
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno>RCIN 1005082</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <altIdentifier><repository ref="INS0447EMIP"/><collection>EMIP</collection>
                            <idno>EMIP 3489</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents><summary>The cult of Mary, Mother of Jesus, has been a focal point in Ethiopian Christian worship since the 15th century. This text of the stories of her life is divided into readings for the twelve months of the Ethiopian calendar year, beginning on folio 3r, with the month of Maskaram (መስከረም). The manuscript was written by an anonymous single scribe, 27 lines in 3 columns per page, with floral scroll headings (harag) on ff. 1r, 64r, 129r and 151r.
                        
                        More than 250 paintings illustrate the volume which opens (f. 2r) with an image of the Virgin and child flanked by the archangels Michael and Gabriel, with portraits of the manuscript’s patrons, a husband and wife, prostrated at their feet. A sixteenth century engraving of The Virgin and child icon from the church of Santa Maria Maggiore in Rome is stitched onto the first page of the manuscript (f. 1v). For centuries the icon, dating from the 6th century, was considered the ‘true likeness’ of Mary and Jesus painted by St Luke from life. Prints of this image reached Ethiopia via Jesuit priests based in Goa in the late sixteenth century and influenced subsequent depictions of the Madonna in Ethiopian painting, as evident throughout the illustrations to this manuscript. This is the only known print associated with the Jesuit mission in Ethiopia to survive. Impressions on its surface may indicate that it was traced and used as a template for other images. Remains of adhesive on its reverse suggest that it was adhered to something else before being sewn into this book.
                        
                        The volume is bound in brown calf with blind stamped decoration over wooden boards with textile inlays on the inside covers. It was rebound and re-backed by the India Office in the late 19th century.
                        
                        See also Kristen Windmuller-Luna, 'Building Faith: Ethiopian Art and Architecture during the Jesuit Interlude, 1557–1632' (2016)
                    </summary></msContents>
                    <physDesc></physDesc>
                    <history><provenance>Originally owned by Yonakendis and his wife Yodit. Taken by
                        <persName ref="PRS9430Tewodros"/> and brought to <placeName ref="INS0101MadhaneAlam"/>. It was then bought by Richard Holmes during the British <persName ref="PRS7484Napier">Napier</persName> expedition in <date>1868</date> and later presented to Queen Victoria.</provenance></history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source>
                                    <listBibl type="catalogue">
                                        <bibl>
                                            <ptr target="bm:Ullendorff1953Windsor"/>
                                            <citedRange unit="page">76</citedRange>
                                        </bibl>
                                    </listBibl>
                                </source>
                            </recordHist>
                        </adminInfo>                        
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <abstract>
                <p/>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature"/>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="ES" when="2022-04-25">Created entity</change>
            <change when="2022-01-10" who="ES">added EMIP ID and facs</change>
            <change when="2022-11-04" who="ES">added info and facs from https://www.rct.uk/collection/search#/5/collection/1005082/nagara-maryam-nagare-maareyaame-the-life-of-mary</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="https://www.rct.uk/collection/search#/5/collection/1005082/nagara-maryam-nagare-maareyaame-the-life-of-mary"/>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography"/><!---->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>