<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP03133">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Yale Collection, Ethiopic 05</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Yale Collection</repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/3133/">Yale Collection, Ethiopic 05</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Miracles of Mary, ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡; F<locus target="#1r"/>-8v: Introduction to the Miracles of Mary, መቅድመ: ተአምረ: ማርያም: ዘሙዓልቃ:. <locus target="#9r"/> First Miracle of Mary. How the Virgin Mary accepted the Book of Miracles compiled by Saint Däqsǝyos and how she punished a bishop who usurped the garment and chair of Däqsǝyos (Budge, I; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, f<locus target="#30r"/>–32r; EMDL 681, f<locus target="#76rv"/>:). <locus target="#12r"/>: Second Miracle of Mary: : How the Virgin Mary spoke from her picture to a devout worshipper and said to him, “Blessed art thou among men” (Budge, II; Princeton 20, f<locus target="#41v"/>–42r; Princeton 23, f<locus target="#28v"/>–29v; Princeton 41, f<locus target="#54v"/>; Princeton 43, f<locus target="#8rv"/>; Princeton 46, f<locus target="#10v"/>–11r; EMDL 681, <locus target="#107v"/>). <locus target="#13v"/>-19v: Third Miracles of Mary: How the Virgin Mary received the covenant of mercy from her son; and how the Virgin Mary saved the soul of the cannibal of Kemer, who had killed and eaten his wife and two children and a large number of men and women (Budge, XXIX; TM, pp. 43–52). F<locus target="#19v"/>-21r: Fourth Miracle of Mary: How the Virgin Mary saved the robber’s soul from judgment because he drank from water that sprang from her feet (Princeton 20, f<locus target="#5rv"/>). F<locus target="#21r"/>-23r: Fifth Miracle of Mary: How the Virgin Mary removed the Monastery of Si‘ǝqona  from the site on which it had been built in the desert to the side of a running stream; and how the removal was effected by night whilst the monks were sleeping (Budge, XIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, f<locus target="#62rv"/>). F<locus target="#23r"/>-25v: Sixth Miracle of Mary: How the Virgin Mary anointed the eyes of John Bakansi, a blind priest of the Church of Saint Mercurius in Cairo, with milk from her breasts and restored his sight when he was one hundred years old (Budge, XIV; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, f<locus target="#62v"/>–63v; EMDL 681, f<locus target="#79v"/>–80v). F<locus target="#25v"/>-28r: Seventh Miracle of Mary: How a merchant from the Island of Colossae  was shot in the eye by the arrow of a pirate in the Mediterranean; how his friends made an image in wax of the wounded man with an arrow fixed in one eye and took it to a church of the Virgin Mary; and how she withdrew the arrow from the eye of the figure, whereupon the eye of the Greek was healed (Budge, XV; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, f<locus target="#63v"/>–64r; EMDL 681, f<locus target="#80v"/>–81r). F<locus target="#28r"/>-29v: Eighth Miracle of Mary. How the Virgin delivered from devils the soul of a scribe who was engaged in writing a copy of the Book of her Miracles. This scribe had a brother who had sinned, but not knowing him they seized the innocent man and tried to carry him off to hell (Budge, XVIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, f<locus target="#66v"/>–67v; EMDL 681, f<locus target="#83rv"/>).. FF. Miracles of Jesus,  <locus target="#12r"/> and passim mention the owner, ገብራ ገላወዴዎስ.</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <textLang/>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf">ii + 97</measure>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height/>
                              <width/>
                              <depth/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate>twentieth century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
