<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<listRelation xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sdcRels">
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p1" name="sdc:constituteUnit"  passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniMat1">
        <desc>The small quire at the beginning of the text block, bound together, is a material unit due to the size of the 
            leaves in comparison to the rest of the manuscript.</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p1" name="sdc:constituteUnit"  passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCah1">
        <desc>The small quire at the beginning bound together is a quire unit, being bound together. </desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p2" name="sdc:constituteUnit"  passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniMat2">
        <desc>The eight leaves within the small quire are of a different parchment and are thus a separate material unit.
            There is no sign that these four bifolia where once separated and thus there is no sign that this was a quire or 
            a production unit separate from <ref type="mspart" corresp="p1">the rest of the small quire</ref>. 
            It is only part of it, or rather the two outer bifolia where, in the same act of production, used to surround the inner leaves, which share in 
            layout, ruling and writing.
        </desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation name="sdc:constituteUnit" active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p1" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd1">
        <desc>The small quire constitutes one production unit being bound into a single quire.</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation name="sdc:constituteUnit" active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p3" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniMat3">
        <desc>All other leaves are of the same size, the one of the Gospel and constitute thus a unit</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniMat3" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation"  passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr1">
        <desc>the small quire was added to the Manuscript.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr1" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:A1">
        <desc>This a transformation A1 Addition of material support and content
            </desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr1" name="sdc:produces" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#ms">
        <desc>There are therefore a UniCirc before the transformation and one after.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr1" name="sdc:resultsIn" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc1">
        <desc>The Manuscript as we know it in terms of material correspond to this circulation unit.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniMat3" name="sdc:constitueUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc2">
        <desc>The Manuscript before that addition is another circulation unit we can be sure about.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc2" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2">
        <desc>For the latest additions, which were presumably not seen by Carlo Conti Rossini, we can assume they where made to the circulation unit
        which already had the small quire. This is however hypothetical, as it may also be for other reasons that Conti Rossini did not list these texts.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:A2">
        <desc>This a transformation A2 Addition of material support and content.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a23" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd2">
        <desc>Each of these additions is a production unit, involved into the one group transformation 
            which groups different acts which we cannot further distinguish at the moment.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd2" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a26" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd3"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd3" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a27" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd4"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd4" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a1" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd5"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd5" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a2" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd6"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd6" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a8" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd7"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd7" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a9" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd8"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd8" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a12" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd9"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd9" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a13" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd10"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd10" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a14" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd11"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd11" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a18" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd12"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd12" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2"/>
    
        <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2" name="sdc:resultsIn" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc3">
        <desc>The unit before and after the transformation are UniCirc, but because we cannot order them one by one we can only group additions into one transformation.
    The issue is determining to which UniCirc the additions where made and this also can be done only for some additions.
        </desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr1" name="sdc:isPartOfTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr3"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr2" name="sdc:isPartOfTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr3"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr3" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:UA1">
    <desc>What we have now having been subject to additions as a whole is a unit which 
        has been subject to a transformation UA1, that is, a union followed by additions.</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc2" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr4">
        <desc>
    The leaves of the same size of the Gospel after the small quire have detached from one another and we cannot say how they fit together.
    This occurred probably before the small quire was added, if this was the result of a copy from the contents of some of these leaves, so the
    subject of the transformation is the circulation unit before the transformation which added the small quire.
        </desc>
    </relation>
    <relation  active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr4" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:D3"
        ><desc>This transformation is a simple
            division  (D3).
        </desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr4" name="sdc:produces" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd13" >
        <desc>This detachment however did not produce different units of circulation, 
            as the leaves continued to circulate together.</desc>
    </relation>
    
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#layout1" name="sdc:constituteUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd14">
        <desc> The two leaves with the end of the Gadla Qirqos, 
            distinguished from the rest because of the ruling pattern and material, were probably taken from another, 
            unknown, manuscript to produce the small quire at a point which we cannot say. We need to define this as a production unit separate from the one
        of the small quire which is now inside it.</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#layout2" name="sdc:constituteUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd15">
        <desc>Also the small quire, whose content stability allows to think of a single production intention is also a production unit, however independent.</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd13" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr5">
        <desc>The unit from the other manuscript was then subject to a transformation.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation  active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr5" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:D2"
        ><desc>This transformation is a simple division  (D2).</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation  active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd14" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr6">
        <desc>And was followed by the addition to a another unit.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation  active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd15" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr6">
        <desc>We thus have to say that also the unit with the other ruling pattern now inside this one was part of the same transformation</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation  active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr6" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:A1"
        ><desc>This transformation is a an addition of support and contents (A1).</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr5" name="sdc:isPartOfTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr7"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr6" name="sdc:isPartOfTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr7"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr7" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:MA1">
        <desc>Also in this case we can group the transformation into a single complex one. 
            This is probably a transformation MA1, where a codex has been somehow deprived of two 
            bifolia to make our quire which contains the homogeneous one.
            The additions on folios 11 and 12 use the ruling in some way, but this does not tell us
            if these where there already or not. If we had organized a table by quire, which was not suitable for this example, it would become clear
            that a convergent discontinuity was present here. In our table this turns out into two convergent discontinuities.
        </desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr7" name="sdc:produces" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd16">
    <desc>The result of this is thus the observable production unit.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr7" name="sdc:resultsIn" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc4">
        <desc>The transformation also consequently results in a new circulation unit.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd16" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr8">
        <desc>If the texts (UniCont) on p1 f.11v and 12v where already there 
    when the leaves where used to produce uniprod1, we do not know. 
    CCR dates them later than the text of the Gadla 
    Qirqos, which however does not help in this respect. 
    They where added to that material in any case.</desc></relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a24" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd17"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd17" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr8"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#a25" name="sdc:constitutesUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd18"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniProd18" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr8"/>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr8" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:A2">
        <desc>This a transformation A2, an addition of content.</desc>
    </relation>
   
   
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p4" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr9">
      <desc>  
    The following are permutations of type P1, changes in the order of the folios, which produce a new UniCirc, but not a new UniProd.
    After cross checking convergent discontinuities in the table view, we can  safely say that the folio numbered by Schneider 17/18, the same as Bausi II 15, 
    is the leaf which CCR had before the one with the cross in his description, the ancient leaf. If we follow Conti Rossini description, the two leaves after the small 
    quire are not there. In facts photo 001 by Schneider shows that the sequence sees the end of the small quire and then the folio which has the coptic cross 
    on the verso. Of all folios available the one which carries the texts which Conti Rossini dates the earliest is the one which we now numbered 27, 
    which is delimited by convergent discontinuities, and was referenced as said above
    previously. We can thus say that there was at least one permutation of the order of the leaves, before they were photographed in 1975 and that this one moved to its current position.
      </desc>
  </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr9" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:P1">
        <desc>This is a permutation of folios. 
            For the msPart containing the Eusebian letter and the canons, identified by decoration and content unity, the
            sequence at CCR time was, with reference to the current pagination 27  (the leaf with old texts), 13 (cross on verso), 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19 (tempio on recto).</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr9" name="sdc:resultsIn" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc5">
        <desc>The permutation results in a unit of circulation only.</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p4" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr10">
        <desc>  
            The continuity between 19 and 26 may be based on the convergence of discontinuities of 
           <list>
               <item>content (CCR7)</item>
            <item>material</item>
            <item>decoration</item>
           <item>layout (1 col)</item>
            <item>eventually the two lines text on top of 19r and 26r.</item>
           </list>
            We can thus say that another permutation occurred with respect to the latest photos. This is easily confirmed and dated after 1975, since 
            in the photos of Schneider the current folio 26 does follow directly on 19 and is paginated with 3 for the recto and 4 for the verso. 
        </desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr10" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:P1">
        <desc>This is a another permutation of folios.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr10" name="sdc:resultsIn" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc6">
        <desc>The further permutation results in a further unit of circulation only.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p4" name="sdc:undergoesTransformation" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr11">
        <desc>  
           There is another observable permutation which affects the group of leaves of the same size of the once containing the Gospel. 
           The leaves which Schneider paginated as 7/8 and 9/10 moved by the time Bausi took his photographs of these folia in 1993 to their current placement
           at 24 and 25 (Bausi II 12 and II 13). It may have appeared obvious to someone that in their position at that time they interrupted the continuity of a content Unit (CCR 20).
        </desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr11" name="sdc:hasTransformationModel" passive="sdc:P1">
        <desc>This is a another permutation of folios.</desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#tr11" name="sdc:resultsIn" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc7">
        <desc>The further permutation results in a further unit of circulation only.</desc>
    </relation>
    
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc7" name="skos:exactMatch" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1">
        <desc>This unit, which contains what was last seen corresponds to the described object.</desc>
    </relation>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p4" name="sdc:constituteUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc8">
        <desc>
            We can then define a reconstructed production unit which represents the state of the leaves sorrounding the decorated leaves and is possibly closer to the
            state observed by Conti Rossini. To this unit other texts which are discontinuous with the rest and are not those added later
            may have been added, e.g.<ref type="item" corresp="p10_i2"> CCR 8</ref>.
        </desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc8" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p11"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc8" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p5"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc8" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p10"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p4" name="sdc:constituteUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc9">
        <desc>
     A unit, corresponding roughly to a fascicule circulated until Schneider took photos as 20, 24, 25, 21, 22, 23.    
     It is impossible to say more on this unit, whose unity at some point may be attested by a univocal deletion intervention.
        </desc>
    </relation>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc9" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p7"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc9" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p8"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc9" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p9"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#layout6" name="sdc:constituteUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc10"/>
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#layout7" name="sdc:constituteUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc10">
        <desc>
    However the layout of 24 and 25 stands out as a separate unit, 
    characterized by the two columns layout and the blank first column on the verso of both leaves, and thus to define a further unit of the remaining leaves
    sharing the one column layout and the dotted line separators.
        </desc>
    </relation>
        <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc10" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p8"/>
        <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc10" name="dcterms:hasPart" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p9"/>
    
    <relation active="DabraLibanosHamGG1#p7" name="sdc:constituteUnit" passive="DabraLibanosHamGG1#UniCirc11"/>
   
</listRelation>
