<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP02184">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Mandeville Collection Codex 1</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Mandeville Collection</repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/2184/">Mandeville Collection Codex 1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Varia. F. i v: A miracle of Jesus Christ as a child: how he rode on a beam of the sun. F. ii v: Miracle of Saint Mika'el when a ship at sea was threatened by a storm. Miracles of Mary.  F<locus target="#1r"/>-6v: The Prayer of Mary for sinners which she prayed at Jesus' grave on Yakatit 16 (based on the prayer of Our Lady Mary at Golgotha). F<locus target="#7rv"/>: Hymn to Mary, “I Prostrate Before You,” እሰግድ፡ ለኪ፡. Répertoire 336/338. F<locus target="#8r"/>-10r: Angels Praise Her, Yǝwedǝssǝwa Mäla’ǝkt, ይዌድስዋ፡ መላእክት፡ ለማርያም፡. Répertoire 388; MD 519ff. ; EMML 1593, <locus target="#92a"/>. F<locus target="#10r"/>-13r: Greeting to Mary, the ark of Noah, ሰላም፡ ለኪ፡ ማርያም፡ ለኅ፡ ሐመሩ፡. F<locus target="#13r"/>-15r: Hymn to Mary, “Rejoice, Mary, Virgin in Body and Mind,” ተፈሥሒ፡ ማርያም፡ ድንግልተ፡ ሥጋ፡ ወሕሊና፡. Répertoire 303; IES 71. F<locus target="#15r"/>-16r: Continuation of the hymn, I Prostrate Before You. F<locus target="#17r"/>-108r: Thirty-Two Miracles of Mary. F<locus target="#111r"/>-122v: The Homiliary of the Mother of Mercy, ድርሳን ዘእመ ምሕረት. F<locus target="#123r"/>-130v: Image of the Covenant of Mercy, መልክአ፡ ኪዳነ፡ ምሕረት፡, incipit: እግዚአብሔር: ወሃቤ: ብርሃን: ዘይሤለስ በአካሉ።, Répertoire 362. Dillmann, Chrestomathia 136–46; MG 681–700. EMIP 499; 2073/Tweed 124. F<locus target="#131r"/>-143v: Prayer of Our Lady Mary at Golgotha, Säne Golǝgota, ጸሎተ፡ እግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ዘሰኔ፡ ጎልጎታ፡. Copied and printed several times in its Gə‘əz and Amharic versions, e.g., ጸሎተ፡ እግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ዘሰኔ፡ ጎልጎታ፡ በመቃብረ፡ እግዚእነ፡ ኢየሱስ፡ ክርስቶስ፡  (Addis Ababa: Täsfa, 1949 E.C.); ጸሎተ፡ እግዝእትነ፡ ማርያም፡ ዘሰኔ፡ ጎልጎታ፡ (Addis Ababa: Täsfa, 1963 E.C.); see also Grébaut, “La prière de Marie au Golgotha,” and Basset, Apocryphes 5 30 –47; StrLin 47, <locus target="#73r"/>; EMML 1213, <locus target="#1a"/>. F<locus target="#144r"/>-148r: Introduction to the Miracles of Mary, መቅድመ: ተአምረ: ማርያም: ዘሙዓልቃ:. F<locus target="#148rv"/>: Image of Mary, Répertoire 93, incipit: ሰላም ለኪ ኦማርያም ድንግል አሙ ለ እግዚአነ ኢየሱስ ክርስቶስ ከሃሊ. Varia. F<locus target="#16r"/>, col 2-16v: Asmat prayer against the evil eye with the story of Jesus and the disciples at the Sea of Tiberias, Ṣälota Nǝdra, ጸሎተ፡ ንድራ፡. EMIP Magic Scroll 3:1; Or. 4865 (StrBL 121). Cf. AbbCat 143, <locus target="#49r"/>; Notice 109.  <locus target="#108r"/>, col. 2: Prayer of supplication for six individuals. Notes. F. ii r, bottom:  Primary note of ownership: This book belongs to አጻዳ ማርያም and his father, አዳራ ጊዮርጊስ, and his mother, ቢሩታዊት, who bought it with his own means. Condemned by the authority of Peter and Paul is the one who steals or erases it." A secondary owner has written their names above the original owners: ዘርቤታ ድንግል, whose father is ኪዳነ ማርያም, and whose mother is ወላተ ተክለ ሃይማኖት. F. ii r, column 2: Note of later ownership by church: This book is the property of ደብረ ኢየሱስ church and was given by ወለተ ተክላ ሃይማኖት, her father was ዘዉገ ሚካኤል, and her brothers were ገብረ መድኀን and ገብረ ሥላሴ, and her mother was ሐመረ ኪዳን. F. iiir: Introdution to the Miracles of Mary, daily reading.</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <textLang/>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf"/>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height/>
                              <width/>
                              <depth/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate when="1650">17th century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
