<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP02623">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Kaleab Addis Project 335</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Kaleab Addis Project </repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/2623/">Kaleab Addis Project 335</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>F<locus target="#1r"/>-165v: Psalter, ዳዊት፡. Hiob Ludolf, Psalterium Davidis Aethiopice et Latine, 1701. Printed several times in Ethiopia, e. g. MD.  F<locus target="#1r"/>-129r: 151 Psalms of David. The word for God is rubricated throughout. Marginal numbers indicate Qalu reckoning by 10's. The midpoint of the Psalms (<locus target="#62v"/>) is marked with the line written in alternating red and black ink. Psalm 151 is written in columetric layout with red letters in the first, third, and fifth positions. Psalm 151 is the long version. F<locus target="#129r"/>-141v: Fifteen Biblical Canticles. The fourth canticle is Song of Hana, mother of Samuel, prophet. <locus target="#142r"/>-149v: Song of Songs, in the Hebraic or Scholars' Edition. F<locus target="#150r"/>-160v: Praises of Mary, arranged for the days of the week, beginning with prayers for Monday. F<locus target="#160v"/>-165v: Gate of Light. F<locus target="#166r"/>-xx: Angels Praise Her, written in a different and later hand. Notes: F. i v(erso), top: Excerpt from the Pslams, written in an untrained hand. F. i v(erso), bottom: Asmat prayer against colic, ሕማመ፡ ቁርፀት፡. F. ii r(ecto) and v(erso): excerpt from Absolution of the Son, written in a different hand. F. iii r(ecto): excerpt from Psalm 140, written in the same hand as the base hand of the book. F. iii v(erso): Record: Note of ownership, This book belongs to Abuna ወልደ ሥላሴ who bought it with his own money to save his soul and body. Other members of his family are mentioned. <locus target="#165v"/>: Record: A record of the ownership of a plot of land, in Old Amharic. Illuminations: i v(erso):  crude drawing of horse and rider with spear.  F. ii r(ecto): Crude drawing in purple ink of horse and rider. F. ii v(erso): Angel with sword and scabbard.  Both the front and back inside covers appear to have mirror niches with a residue of glue. Sheguala Maryam</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <textLang/>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf"/>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height/>
                              <width/>
                              <depth/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate when="1750">18th century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
