<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP02259">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Weiner Codex 260</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Weiner</repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/2259/">Weiner Codex 260</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>F<locus target="#1r"/>-xxx: Miracles of Mary, Tä’ammǝrä Maryam, ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡, for Monday through Saturday, written in Ge'ez (left column) and Amharic (right columns). The standard works on the miracles of Mary are Cerulli, Maria, and Budge, Mary. An exhaustive collection has been published in Ethiopia, Tä’ammǝrä Maryam (Addis Ababa: Tǝnśa’e zä-guba’e, 1989 E.C.) EMML 2058, 2059, and 2060. See Delamarter, et al, MYS 1 for a description of 371 miracles. F<locus target="#5v"/>-8r: Hymn to Mary, “I Prostrate Before You,” እሰግድ፡ ለኪ፡. Répertoire 336/338. F<locus target="#8v"/>-18v: the Introductory Rite from Mu‘älläqa, in Ge'ez (left) and Amharic (right). F<locus target="#19r"/>-20v: How the Virgin Mary saved a harlot from stoning by the people of a certain city (TM, p. 121), in Ge'ez (left) and Amharic (right). Further Miracles (f<locus target="#21r"/>, 23r,  25r,  27r, ), in Ge'ez (left) and Amharic (right). F<locus target="#32r"/>-xxx: Vision of John, Son of Thunder, on the Agreement of the Eighty-One Canonical Scriptures. For a critical edition and English translation, see Getatchew Haile, The Mariology of Emperor Zär’a Ya‘ǝqob of Ethiopia, OCA 242 (Rome: Pontificium Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1992), esp. 94–117. F<locus target="#33r"/>-xxx: Collection of Biblical Confessions gathered by two monks from Dabra Bizan. On the religious controversy. F. i v-iii r: Magabit 7, 1941. Record, a Will by ቄስ ፍሰሀ በለጡ, in which he specifies who should receive which properties.  At the end are five finger prints with signatures of each witness. Written in Amharic. F<locus target="#19r"/> and passim mention the owner, መምሕር ፍሥሐ ጽዮን. <locus target="#81r"/> has a colophon: This book was written in Dabra Bizan, the monastery named by Philipos and John. . .in 1900 EC. . .in the year of John the Evangelist,on Monday, on the 5th day of Miyazia, at 3 in the afternoon. . . by scribe ወልደ ጻድቅ.</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <textLang/>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf"/>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height/>
                              <width/>
                              <depth/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate>1930-1974 (f. 1v)</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
