<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng"
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="mss" xml:lang="en" xml:id="EMIP02046">
   <teiHeader xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Tweed Codex 097</title>
            <editor key="RL"/>
            <editor key="ABe"/>
            <editor key="JS"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter</p>
                                        <p>Dedicated to Cane Hope Felder</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0880WHU">Tweed</repository>
                  <collection>Tweed Collection</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/2046/" n="156">Tweed Codex 097</idno>
                  <altIdentifier>
                     <collection>EMIP</collection>
                     <idno>EMIP 2046</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Thirty-Four Miracles of Mary, ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡; Ten Miracles of Jesus, ተአምረ፡ ኢየሱስ፡ </summary>
                  <textLang mainLang="gez">Gǝʿǝz</textLang>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <locus from="1r" to="10r" facs="009"/>
                     <title>Vision of John, Son of Thunder, on the Dual Virginity of Mary, <foreign xml:lang="gez">ራዕየ፡ ተአምር፡ ዘዮሐንስ፡ ወልደ፡ ነጐድጓድ፡</foreign></title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i2">
                     <locus from="14r" to="68v"/>
                     <title type="complete" ref="LIT2384Taamme"/>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.1">
                        <locus from="14r" to="19r" facs="022"/>
                        <title>Introduction to the Miracles of Mary, <foreign xml:lang="gez">መቅድመ፡ ተአምረ፡ ማርያም፡ ዘሙዓልቃ፡</foreign>
                        </title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.2">
                        <locus from="19r" to="20v" facs="027"/>
                        <title>Second, shorter Introduction to the Miracles of Mary, <foreign xml:lang="gez">ስምዑ፡ እነግረክሙ፡</foreign>
                        </title>
                        <incipit xml:lang="gez">በስመ፡ አብ፡ ወወልድ፡ <gap reason="omitted"/> ስምዑ፡ እነግረክሙ፡ አኃውየ፡ ፍቁራን፡ ውሉደ፡ ዛቲ፡ ቤተ፡ ክርስቲያን፡ እግዚአብሔር፡ ይባርክሙ፡ ወያብርህ፡ አዕይንተ፡ አልባቢክሙ፡ <gap reason="omitted"/>
                        </incipit>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.3">
                        <locus from="20v" to="21v" facs="029"/>
                        <title>
                           <title type="complete" ref="LIT3056RepCh336"/>
                        </title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.4">
                        <locus from="22r" to="25r" facs="030"/>
                        <title>[First Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary accepted the Book of Miracles compiled by Saint Däqsǝyos and how she punished a bishop who usurped the garment and chair of Däqsǝyos (Budge, I; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 30r" to="32r; MYS 1, ff. 5r" to="6r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.5">
                        <locus from="25r" to="26v" facs="033"/>
                        <title>[Second Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary received the soul of Anastasius, a deacon of Rome, who addressed the “Five Gaudes” to her at all times, and took it to Paradise (Budge, XXVII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 84r" to="85r; MYS 1, ff. 19v" to="20r), with a concluding hymn</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.6">
                        <locus from="26v" to="27r" facs="035"/>
                        <title>[Third Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary spoke from her picture to a devout worshipper and said to him, “Blessed art thou among men” (Budge, II; Princeton 20, ff. 41v" to="42r; Princeton 23, ff. 28v" to="29v; Princeton 41, ff. 54v; Princeton 43, ff. 8rv; Princeton 46, ff. 10v" to="11r; MYS 1, f. 171v), with a concluding hymn</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.7">
                        <locus from="27r" to="28v" facs="035"/>
                        <title>[Fourth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary saved Qiras, the bandit who was devoted to Mary, when the people caught him and led him to the gallows; and how he later became a monk (Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 80rv; MYS 1, ff. 25rv; cf. Budge, XXXI), with a concluding hymn</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.8">
                        <locus from="28v" to="30r" facs="037"/>
                        <title>[Fifth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary commanded a deacon to dig up and rebury in consecrated ground the body of an adulterous deacon from the island of Jericho in the city of Gärisat who was killed by the people;” Budge, CIII; Princeton 8, ff. 9r" to="10v; Princeton 40, ff. 80v" to="81v; Princeton 43, ff. 25r" to="26r; Princeton 46, ff. 128rv; MYS 1, f. 126v)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.9">
                        <locus from="30r" to="31r" facs="038"/>
                        <title>[Sixth Miracle of Mary:] How an aged Jew of Akhmim, who had spent his whole life in ministering in a church of the Virgin Mary, fell down one day during the service and broke his back, and how the Virgin Mary touched his backbone and made it whole, and made him to stand by her on the right-hand side of the altar (Budge, III; MYS 1, f.)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.10">
                        <locus from="31r" to="33r" facs="039"/>
                        <title>[Seventh Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary appeared to a man from France (Afǝras) when he denied Christ but kept devotion to the Virgin Mary (cf. Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 100v" to="101v; MYS 1, ff. 33v" to="34r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.11">
                        <locus from="33r" to="34r" facs="041"/>
                        <title>[Eighth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain nun and commanded her to continue reciting the Hail Mary (Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 96rv; MYS 1, f. 31v)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.12">
                        <locus from="34r" to="35r" facs="042"/>
                        <title>[Ninth Miracle of Mary:] How Nicodemus, an evil-living [Persian] knight, became a Christian, but was unable to learn the Lord’s Prayer, and could only master the Salutation to Mary; and how these words were found written on every leaf of a tree which grew on his grave (Budge, XXXVIII, Princeton Ethiopic 8, ff. 10v" to="12v; MYS 1, f. 86v)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.13">
                        <locus from="35r" to="36r" facs="043"/>
                        <title>[Tenth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary saved a certain man from drowning when the ship was sinking (Princeton 41, ff. 99v" to="100v; MYS 1, ff. 174v" to="175r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.14">
                        <locus from="36v" to="38r" facs="045"/>
                        <title>[Eleventh Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary commanded the bishop to bury in the believers’ burial the body of a hanged thief who had been devoted to Mary; and how a tree with healing powers grew up from his grave (MYS 1, ff. 30v" to="31r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.15">
                        <locus from="38r" to="39v" facs="046"/>
                        <title>[Twelfth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary saved a certain governor and deacon when he became mentally distressed by anointing his lips with her breast milk (Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 75r" to="76v; MYS 1, ff. 24rv; cf. Princeton Ethiopic 8, ff. 2r" to="4r; Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 75r" to="76v; MYS 1, f. 85v; and MYS 1, f. 170r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.16">
                        <locus from="39v" to="42r" facs="048"/>
                        <title>[Thirteenth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary anointed the eyes of John Bakansi, a blind priest of the Church of Saint Mercurius in Cairo, with milk from her breasts and restored his sight when he was one hundred years old (Budge, XIV; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 62v" to="63v; MYS 1, ff. 12v" to="13r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.17">
                        <locus from="42r" to="43r" facs="050"/>
                        <title>[Fourteenth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary appeared to a monk from the Island Ṭegǝros (Tigres?) when he couldn’t walk and his friends carried him to church (Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 107v" to="108r; MYS 1, ff. 34v" to="35r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.18">
                        <locus from="43r" to="44v" facs="051"/>
                        <title>[Fifteenth Miracle of Mary:] How the icon of the Virgin Mary helped a young impoverished man and how the church keeper saw this miracle and how he gave his daughter to the young man in marriage (Princeton 20, f. 25r; Princeton 20, ff. 72rv; Princeton 41, ff. 93r" to="94r; MYS 1, ff. 172rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.19">
                        <locus from="44v" to="46r" facs="053"/>
                        <title>[Sixteenth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary took a shepherd into paradise in seven days (Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 108r" to="109r; MYS 1, ff. 35rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.20">
                        <locus from="46r" to="47v" facs="054"/>
                        <title>[Seventeenth Miracle of Mary:] How a certain painter was decorating a church in Afrǝng with pictures of the Blessed Virgin and Paradise with the righteous souls and with pictures of the devils in Gehenna; how the Devil overturned the scaffolding, and how the painter was caught by the arm by the Virgin Mary as he fell, and how she lowered him little by little uninjured to the ground (Budge, VIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 57v" to="58v; MYS 1, ff. 9r" to="10r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.21">
                        <locus from="47v" to="49r" facs="056"/>
                        <title>[Eighteenth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary rescued from the clutches of the Devil the soul of a libertine monk who was crossing a stream one night to visit a paramour (Budge, LXIX; Princeton 20, ff. 27r" to="28v; MYS 1, f. 149r; cf. MYS 1, ff. 136rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.22">
                        <locus from="49r" to="51r" facs="057"/>
                        <title>[Nineteenth Miracle of Mary:] How a certain Muslim was converted when he saw oil and milk flowing from the breasts of a picture of the Virgin Mary (Budge, LXI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 92r" to="93r; MYS 1, ff. 29rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.23">
                        <locus from="51r" to="52r" facs="059"/>
                        <title>[Twentieth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary received the soul of  a sick and devout monk who was unable to go to church and how she took his soul to Paradise (cf. Budge, XXVII; Princeton 20, ff. 81rv; Princeton 41, ff. 84r" to="85r; Princeton 43, ff. 6v" to="8r; Princeton 43, ff. 50v" to="51v; Princeton 46, ff. 27v" to="28r; Princeton 47, ff. 80v" to="81r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.24">
                        <locus from="52v" to="54r" facs="061"/>
                        <title>[Twenty-First Miracle of Mary:] How Isaac, monk and verger, heaped ascetic labors upon himself, and for seven years devoted his nights to prayers to the Virgin whilst the brethren were asleep, and how the Virgin Mary appeared to him and promised to take him to herself after three days (Budge, VI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 56r" to="57r; MYS 1, ff. 8rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.25">
                        <locus from="54r" to="55r" facs="062"/>
                        <title>[Twenty-Second Miracle of Mary:] How a certain God-fearing man took his two elder daughters and went to church, leaving in his house Mary, his youngest daughter, in spite of her protests and wish to go in order to receive the Sacrament; and how the Virgin Mary appeared from out of her picture to the child, and told her that she would take her to herself in Paradise after three days; and how a godly man saw the child three days later, clad in purple and following the Virgin up into heaven (Budge, VII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 57rv; MYS 1, ff. 8v" to="9r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.26">
                        <locus from="55r" to="56r" facs="063"/>
                        <title>[Twenty-Third Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary carried a sick monk from the Monastery of the Pilgrims[2] to Palestine, and showed him Jerusalem and Bethlehem, and bathed him in the waters of Jordan (Budge, IX; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 58v" to="59r; MYS 1, f. 10r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.27">
                        <locus from="56r" to="57v" facs="064"/>
                        <title>[Twenty-Fourth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary arranged marriages for three poor girls,[3] called Mary, Martha and Yawahita, with the sons of Tewog, the blacksmith of Makmas (Budge, XVII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 65v" to="66v; MYS 1, ff. 13v" to="14v)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.28">
                        <locus from="57v" to="58r" facs="066"/>
                        <title>[Twenty-Fifth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary cleansed Bishop Mercurius of his leprosy by touching his body with her hand (Budge, XXIII; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 70v" to="71r; MYS 1, ff. 17rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.29">
                        <locus from="58v" to="59v" facs="067"/>
                        <title>[Twenty-Sixth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary healed a certain man with a foot of stone (Budge, XXII (has lame foot); Princeton 20, ff. 63rv; Princeton 41, ff. 70rv; Princeton 46, ff. 24rv; Princeton 47, ff. 67v" to="69v; MYS 1, ff. 147rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.30">
                        <locus from="60r" to="60v"/>
                        <title>[Twenty-Seventh Miracle of Mary:] How a certain woman, living with her mother-in-law, was devoted to an icon of Mary in her house; how her mother-in-law criticized her for her devotion to the icon; how Mary appeared in a dream and told her that she could not stay in the home because of the criticisms of the mother-in-law; and how, when she awoke, the icon was gone (Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 75rv; Princeton 20, ff. 52v" to="53r; MYS 1, ff. 24r and 161rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.31">
                        <locus from="60v" to="62r" facs="069"/>
                        <title>[Twenty-Eighth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary used to appear in person in the church at Ḥärtälo[mä], and how she healed the broken foot of a woman therein (Budge, XXIV; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 73v" to="74v; MYS 1, ff. 17v" to="18r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.32">
                        <locus from="62r" to="63r" facs="070"/>
                        <title>[Twenty-Ninth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary raised the dead son of a wealthy man from Cappadocia who refused to bury the son and who took the body to the church and prayed to Mary for his son (Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 74v" to="75r; MYS 1, ff. 23v" to="24r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.33">
                        <locus from="63r" to="64v" facs="071"/>
                        <title>[Thirtieth Miracle of Mary:] How a generous, wealthy woman attended prayers with the monks at a monastery and saw the Virgin Mary descending from heaven with a multitude of angels (Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 91r" to="92r; Princeton Ethiopic MS 8, ff. 45v" to="46v; MYS 1, f. 29r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.34">
                        <locus from="64v" to="66r" facs="073"/>
                        <title>[Thirty-First Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary kept the lamp of oil in front of her icon suspended in the air after its attachments had broken (Princeton 41, ff. 135r" to="136v; MYS 1, 180rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.35">
                        <locus from="66r" to="68r" facs="074"/>
                        <title>[Thirty-Second Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary appeared to a bishop to restore a priest called Enǝdrǝyas who knew how to conduct only one of the fourteen anaphoras, the Anaphora of the Virgin Mary (cf. Budge, CII; TM, pp. 104–6; MYS 1, ff. 93rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.36">
                        <locus from="68r" to="68v" facs="076"/>
                        <title>[Thirty-Third Miracle of Mary:] How two women [elsewhere identified as Juliana and Barbara] went on a pilgrimage to Jerusalem, were attacked by robbers who stole their provisions; and how, when the thieves tried to eat them, the Virgin Mary turned the bread into stones upon which the thieves broke their teeth; and how the thieves repented (Budge, XI; Princeton Ethiopic MS 41, ff. 60v" to="61r; MYS 1, ff. 11rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i2.37">
                        <locus from="68v" facs="077"/>
                        <title>[Thirty-Fourth Miracle of Mary:] How the Virgin Mary appeared to a monk [elsewhere identified as from the Island Ṭegǝros] when he couldn’t walk and his friends carried him to church (Princeton Ethiopic 41, ff. 107v-108r; MYS 1, ff. 34v" to="35r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i3">
                     <locus from="69r" to="86v" facs="077"/>
                     <title type="complete" ref="LIT2382Taamme"/>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.1">
                        <locus from="69r" to="71v" facs="077"/>
                        <title>[First Miracle of Jesus:] 1) The birth of Jesus; 2) how the hand of the midwife Salome was completely withered; 3) how Mary cured the hand of Salome by putting the hand of Jesus on Solome’s hand, 4) how Jesus declared that his mother was the Virgin predicted by Isaiah (Grébaut, Miracles of Jesus, I:583–589; EMML 2180, f. 26a; EMIP 347, ff. 9v" to="11r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.2">
                        <locus from="71v" to="72v" facs="080"/>
                        <title>[Second Miracle of Jesus:] How the midwife Salome praised Jesus (Grébaut, Miracles of Jesus, I:589–592; EMML 2180, f. 28b; EMIP 347, ff. 11rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.3">
                        <locus from="72v" to="74r" facs="081"/>
                        <title>[Third Miracle of Jesus:] Presentation of the Child Jesus to the Temple: 1) how Mary and Joseph presented Jesus in the temple and made the offering prescribed by the Mosaic law; 2) how the aged Simeon took in his arms the infant Jesus, gave thanks to God and prophesied; 3) how Satan was appalled when he heard Simeon’s words (Grébaut, Miracles of Jesus, I:605–609; EMML 2180, f. 34a; EMIP 347, ff. 14v" to="15r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.4">
                        <locus from="74r" to="75r" facs="082"/>
                        <title>[Fourth Miracle of Jesus:] The righteous man, Ṭǝṭmǝna, from Nazareth whose cattle were stolen: 1) how Ṭǝṭmǝna, learning of the theft of his cattle, returned thanks to God like Job; 2) how Joseph brought Ṭǝṭmǝna to Jesus who located the stolen cattle behind Mount Tabor; 3) how Jesus, Joseph and Ṭǝṭmǝna go to the thieves, who give the cattle to their owner and believe in Jesus (Grébaut, Miracles of Jesus, I:642–646; EMML 2180, f. 40b; EMIP 347, ff. 18rv)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.5">
                        <locus from="75r" to="76v" facs="083"/>
                        <title>[Fifth Miracle of Jesus:] The fisherman of Galilee whose fish were stolen by his companions: 1) how a fisherman accused his companions for having stolen the fish he had caught; 2) how Jesus was brought in as arbiter of the dispute; 3) how Jesus went down into the boat of the accused fishermen and ordered the stolen fish to return to the boat which had caught them (Grébaut, Miracles of Jesus, I:646–649; EMML 2180, f. 48a; EMIP 347, ff. 18v" to="19r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.6">
                        <locus from="76v" to="78r" facs="085"/>
                        <title>[Sixth Miracle of Jesus:] The stolen calf: 1) how a calf was stolen, and how Jesus was selected as a judge by both the owner and the thief, 2) how he directed the calf to speak, how it declared that it belonged to the old Kemämur son of Nazǝr, and was fleeing to Caesarea, 3) how he forgave the repentant thief, 4) how the thief asked to become a disciple of Jesus (Grébaut, Miracles of Jesus, II:775–779; EMML 2180, f. 49a; EMIP 347, ff. 19r" to="20r)</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.7">
                        <locus from="78r" to="81r" facs="086"/>
                        <title>[Seventh Miracle of Jesus:] How the spears in the hands of the guards at the palace of Pilate bowed down and worshipped Jesus; how the Jews accused the guards of making the spears bow down; how Pilate instructed them to select other guards whom they trusted; how they brought Jesus into the room and the spears bowed down to him; how Pilate wanted to release Jesus when he saw this; how the Jews put forth witnesses who claimed that Jesus had violated the Sabbath; how Pilate responded that he found no guilt in Jesus; how Pilate offered to release a prisoner and how the Jews called for Barabas and demanded that he crucify Jesus. </title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.8">
                        <locus from="81r" to="83v" facs="089"/>
                        <title>[Eighth Miracle of Jesus:] (continued) How Pilate’s wife sent a message to him about her dream; how Pilate washed his hands of the matter; how he declared the innocence of Jesus; how Pilate asked Jesus to respond to the accusations; how Jesus did not respond; how Pilate claimed authority to judge Jesus; how Jesus responded that he had no authority except that given from heaven; how the arch priests asked Jesus if he is the Christ; how Jesus affirmed it; how the arch priests said that they needed no further witnesses; how they took his garments and scourged Jesus; how Peter denied Jesus; how Pilate inscribed King of the Jews on a board; how the Jews objected; and how Pilate refused to change it and wrote his account in Greek, Hebrew, and Latin. </title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.9">
                        <locus from="83v" to="85r" facs="092"/>
                        <title>[Ninth Miracle of Jesus:] (continued) How they crucified Jesus Christ with the two thieves; how the thief on the left insulted Jesus Christ; how the thief on the right rebuked the other and how his eyes were opened to see the glory of Jesus Christ; how he asked Jesus to remember him and how Jesus promised that he would be in paradise on that day; how Jesus reminded him that this was the fulfillment of what he had told to him on the road in Egypt when the Holy Family was fleeing; how they gave Jesus vinegar to drink; how Jesus cried out, “My God, My God, why have you forsaken me;” how the sun was darkened and the moon became as blood from the sixth to the ninth hour; how the curtain in the temple was torn in pieces; how graves were opened and many of the dead came forth; how Jesus commended his spirit in the hands of his father; how a soldier pierced the side of Jesus and blood and water came forth from the side</title>
                     </msItem>
                    <msItem xml:id="ms_i3.10">
                        <locus from="85v" to="86v" facs="094"/>
                        <title>[Tenth Miracle of Jesus:] (continued) How the soldiers broke the bones of the two thieves; how they came to Jesus and found that he was dead; how one of the commanders saw the miracles and said, “Truly this man is the son of God;” how the arch priest came to Pilate and asked him to burn the body of Jesus; how Pilate refused to burn his body but posted guards at the tomb of Jesus; how Joseph of Arimathea and asked for the body of Jesus; how Joseph and Nicodemus prepared his body and placed it in the tomb; how the Jews gave gold to Pilate to place guards at the tomb. Incomplete at the end</title>
                     </msItem>
                  </msItem>
                </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf">viii + 87</measure>
                           <measure unit="quire">Protection quire + 11</measure>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height>180</height>
                              <width>127</width>
                              <depth>58</depth>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation>
                          <note>Quire descriptions: protection quire and quires 1, 3, and 8–10 balanced; quire 5 adjusted balanced; quires 2, 4, 6–7, and 11 unbalanced.</note>
                          <list>
                            <item xml:id="q1" n="a">
                              <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                              <locus from="i" to="viii" facs="001"/>
                              Protection Quire
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q2" n="1">
                              <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                              <locus from="1" to="8" facs="009"/>
                              Quire 1
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q3" n="2">
                              <dim unit="leaf">5</dim>
                              <locus from="9" to="13" facs="017"/>
                              <note>A folio stub is visible between <locus target="#9 #10" facs="018"/>.</note>
                              Quire 2:
                              4, stub after 1
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q4" n="3">
                              <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                              <locus from="14" to="21" facs="022"/>
                              Quire 3
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q5" n="4">
                              <dim unit="leaf">9</dim>
                              <locus from="22" to="30" facs="030"/>
                              <note>A folio stub is visible between <locus target="#28 #29" facs="037"/>.</note>
                              Quire 4:
                              3, stub after 7
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q6" n="5">
                              <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                              <locus from="31" to="40" facs="-39"/>
                              <note>Folio stubs are visible between <locus target="#34 #35" facs="043"/> and <locus target="#37 #38" facs="046"/>.</note>
                              Quire 5:
                              4, stub after 7
                              7, stub after 4
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q7" n="6">
                              <dim unit="leaf">9</dim>
                              <locus from="41" to="49" facs="049"/>
                              <note>A folio stub is visible between <locus target="#49 #50" facs="058"/>.</note>
                              Quire 6:
                              1, stub after 9
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q8" n="7">
                              <dim unit="leaf">9</dim>
                              <locus from="50" to="58" facs="058"/>
                              <note>A folio stub is visible between <locus target="#55 #56" facs="064"/>.</note>
                              Quire 7:
                              4, stub after 6
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q9" n="8">
                              <dim unit="leaf">10</dim>
                              <locus from="59" to="68" facs="067"/>
                              Quire 8
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q10" n="9">
                              <dim unit="leaf">8</dim>
                              <locus from="69" to="76" facs="077"/>
                              Quire 9
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q11" n="10">
                              <dim unit="leaf">6</dim>
                              <locus from="77" to="82" facs="085"/>
                              Quire 10
                            </item>
                            <item xml:id="q12" n="11">
                              <dim unit="leaf">5</dim>
                              <locus from="83" to="87" facs="091"/>
                              <note>A folio stub is visible between <locus target="#82 #83" facs="091"/>.</note>
                              Quire 11:
                              5, stub before 1
                            </item>
                          </list>
                        </collation>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                       <layout>
                         <dimensions type="margin" unit="mm">
                           <dim type="top">18</dim>
                           <dim type="bottom">28</dim>
                           <dim type="right">10</dim>
                           <dim type="left">8</dim>
                         </dimensions>
                       </layout>
                       <layout columns="2" writtenLines="17"/>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote xml:id="h1" script="Ethiopic">
                        <seg type="rubrication">
                           <foreign xml:lang="gez">ማርያም፡</foreign>
                        </seg>
                     </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d1">
                        <locus target="#iiv(erso)" facs="003"/>
                        <desc>
                           <ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1035HolyMan"/>,<persName ref="PRS4585Georgeo"/> and the <term key="dragon"/> with caption <q>“Saint George,” “Berutawit.”</q>
                        </desc>
                     </decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d2">
                        <locus target="#12r" facs="020"/>
                        <desc>
                           <ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1005Crucifixion"/> with caption <q>“Our Lady Mary,” “Saint John.”</q>
                        </desc>
                     </decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d3">
                        <locus target="#41r" facs="049"/>
                        <desc>
                           <ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1041HolyMen"/>
                           <persName ref="PRS9162TaklaHa"/> and <persName ref="PRS3934Ewostate"/>
                        </desc>
                     </decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d4">
                        <locus target="#87r" facs="095"/>
                        <desc>
                           <ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1031VirginAndChild"/> with caption <q>“Our Lady Saint Mary,” “Saint Mika’el,” “Saint Gabri’el.”</q>
                        </desc>
                     </decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="miniature" xml:id="d5">
                        <locus target="#87v" facs="096"/>
                        <desc>
                           <ref type="authFile" corresp="AT1008Descent"/> with caption <q>“Adam,” “Eve,” “Resurrection.”</q>
                        </desc>
                     </decoNote>
                    <decoNote type="frame" xml:id="d6">
                      Decorative designs:
                      <locus target="#14r #22r" facs="022 030"/> (haräg);
                      multiple full stops are used as section dividers throughout;
                      <locus target="#10r #36r #38r #54r #55r #57v #59v #68r" facs="018 044 046 062 063 066 068 076"/>, etc. (line of black dots);
                      <locus target="#25r #31r #33r #34r #35r #63r #64v" facs="033 039 041 042 043 071 073"/>, etc. (line of alternating red and black dots)
                    </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <list>
                        <item xml:id="a1">
                          <locus target="#iv(erso)" facs="002"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT3522Epistle#Chp4:13–5:1"/>
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a2">
                          <locus target="#iiir(ecto) #iiiv(erso)" facs="003 004"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT3522Epistle#Chp5:2–10"/> , continued
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a3">
                          <locus target="#iiiv(erso)" facs="004"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT3507Epistle#Chp5:5–11"/>
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a4">
                          <locus target="#ivr(ecto) #ivv(erso)" facs="004 005"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT3507Epistle#Chp14:66–72"/>  mixed with the apocryphal Lamentation of Peter, incomplete at the beginning.
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a5">
                          <locus target="#vr(ecto)" facs="005"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: A passage on the sealing of the tomb with Pilate’s seal
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a6">
                          <locus target="#vir(ecto) #viv(erso)" facs="006 007"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: excerpt from a Pauline Epistle and the concluding hymn for the hour, <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT1019Actsof#Chp16:25–34"/> , and a passage from <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT1793Leviti"/> 23
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a7">
                          <locus target="#viiir(ecto)" facs="008"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: continuation of <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT1793Leviti"/> 23, and <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT1685Bookof#Chp17:26–7"/>
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a8">
                          <locus target="#viiiv(erso)" facs="009"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT1019Actsof#Chp17:2–5"/>
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a9">
                          <locus target="#10r #10v" facs="018 019"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT3516Epistle#Chp15:51–58"/>
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a10">
                          <locus target="#10v #11r" facs="019"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT3509Epistle#1:1–5"/>
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a11">
                          <locus target="#11r #11v" facs="019 020"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              Biblical readings for the hours: <title type="incomplete" ref="LIT1019Actsof#20:5–12"/>
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a12">
                          <locus target="#41v" facs="050"/>
                           <desc type="GuestText">
                              an excerpt from an unidentified text, written in a seventeenth or eighteenth-century hand, and crossed out
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e1">
                          <locus target="#ir(eco) #iir(eco) #vv(erso) #viir(ecto) #viiv(erso) #12v #13r #13v" facs="001 002 006 007 008 021 022"/>
                           <desc>
                              blank
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="a13">
                          <locus target="#vr(ecto)" facs="005"/>
                           <desc type="OwnershipNote">
                              mentions the owner, Gäbrä Sänbät, and the scribe, Wäldä Maryam
                            </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e2">
                           <desc>
                             It is unclear what manuscript this is in the insurance hand list
                           </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e3">
                          <locus target="#10 #52" facs="018 060"/>
                           <desc>
                             red string is sewn into the fore edge as navigation system
                           </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e4">
                        <locus target="#14r #14v #15r #15v #21v" facs="022 023 024 030"/>
                         <desc>
                          (etc.) words of text are written interlinearly
                        </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e5">
                        <locus target="#18r #20v" facs="026 029"/>
                        <desc>
                          lines of text are written interlinearly
                        </desc>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="e6">
                        <locus target="#15r #84r" facs="023 092"/>
                        <desc>
                          text has been removed
                        </desc>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                    <binding xml:id="binding" contemporary="true">
                      <decoNote xml:id="b1">Parchment, four Coptic chain stitches attached with bridle attachments to rough-hewn boards of the traditional wood with a cloth strap wrapped around the edge of the folios.</decoNote>
                      <decoNote xml:id="b2" type="bindingMaterial">
                        <material key="parchment"/>
                        <material key="wood"/>
                        <material key="textile"/>
                      </decoNote>
                    </binding>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate notBefore="1850" notAfter="1950">Late-nineteenth/Early-twentieth century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/Documentation/master/prefixDef.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>Definitions of prefixes used</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage><language ident="en">English</language><language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language></langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
         <change when="2019-10-31" who="RL">Added ms items, miniatures, varia and notes</change>
         <change who="PL" when="2019-11-13">updated msIdentifier for Tweed collection.</change>
         <change when="2019-12-18" who="ABe">Added facs</change>
         <change when="2020-01-06" who="JS">Added quire maps, margin dims, columns/lines, binding desc, dating info.</change>
         <change when="2020-02-27" who="RL">Added quire image links, corrected chapter and verse references in additions</change>
         <change when="2020-04-17" who="RL">corrected ǝ character</change>
         <change when="2020-11-18" who="ABe">Minor edits</change>
  </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:base="https://betamasaheft.eu/">
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
