<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP02281">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Mandeville Codex 8</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Mandeville</repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/2281/">Mandeville Codex 8</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Psalter, copied in or around the Government Scriptorium, arranged by a secondary hand for the days of the week: Monday (8r), Monday (15v), Tuesday (23v), Tuesday (34r), Tuesday (42r), Wednesday (48v), Wedneday (58r), Thursday (70r), Thursday (79r), Thursday (85r), Friday (112r), Saturday (115v), Saturday (122r), Sunday (129r), Sunday (142v). The Psalms begin with a poem from the Mazmura Dengel. The midpoint of the Psalms (64r) is marked with a cryptic text in alternating red and black ink; the word half is written in black letters, the word David in red letters: መዳንዊፈትቀ. Psalm 151 is a long version, with an extra line, additional beyond the norm. The fourth biblical canticle is "Song of Hana, mother of Samuel, prophetess." The Song of Songs is the Hebraic Edition.  The Praises of Mary begin on Monday and culminate on Sunday. Illuminations: i r: "Abraham blessing his sons" (all captions written in Amharic), i v(erso): Righteous Job, Moses Chief of Prophets; ii r(ecto), Aaron priest, and Joshua governer. ii v(erso): The birth of Christ, Joseph. iii r(ecto): donkey and cow, and wisemen. iii v(erso): Jesus is baptized by John in the Jordan River. iv r(eto): Joseph and Mary, taking the son. iv v(erso): How Jesus saved the leper and how he told him to carry his bed and go home, and how he did that. v r(ecto): Jesus preaching the gospel. v v(erso): Jesus blessed fish and bread and gave them and the left overs. vi r(ecto): Jesus healing the man who was born blind. vi v(erso): King David. 170v: When Jesus was praying on Mount Olives (the disciples) slept. 171r: Saint Peter being beheaded. 171v: Jesus entered into Jerusalm and people welcomed him with palm leaves. 172r: At Jerusalem they put their garments (on the ground). 172v: Abuna Garima and Abuna Ewostatwos. 173r: Saint Mary with her Son. 173v: Jesus observing the Last Supper on Thursday night. 174r: The disciples. 174v: Jesus carrying his cross to be crucified. 175r: The crucifixion. 175v: Jesus raised from the Dead (raising) Adam and Eve. </summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <textLang/>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf"/>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height/>
                              <width/>
                              <depth/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate when="1925">early-twentieth century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
