<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/schema/master/tei-betamesaheft.rng" 
type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     type="mss"
     xml:lang="en"
     xml:id="EMIP02172">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="t1">Weiner Codex 232</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>The initial version of this file was created from data kindly
                                        provided by the Ethiopic Manuscript Imaging Project directed
                                        by Steve Delamarter.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
            <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">
                  <p> This file is licensed under the Creative Commons
                                                Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="ms">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="INS0447EMIP">Weiner</repository>
                  <collection>EMIP</collection>
                  <idno facs="EMIP/Codices/2172/">Weiner Codex 232</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>F<locus target="#1r"/>-212v: Psalter of the Virgin. <locus target="#1r"/>: Extensive Opening prayer. <locus target="#79r"/>: The midpoint is unmarked. Psalm 151 is the short version. <locus target="#167r"/>: The fourth Biblical Canticle is the Prayer of Hana, mother of Samuel, prophetess. Song of Songs is the common version. Praises of Mary begins with a note about Ephrem, the Syrian, how Our Lady Mary appeared to him on a Monday, and summoned him to praise her, how he protested his inability, how she blessed him and how he opened his mouth and praised her. The Praise of Mary begin on Monday and culminate on Saturday. <locus target="#212v"/>: Prayer for healing of the eyes, based on Jesus' five words from the cross.  Not in Repertoire. Incipit:  ሰለም ለአዕይንቲከ ለማርያም በኵራ, written in a different hand. F<locus target="#213r"/>-213v: Christological teachings (here called መሠረተ ሃይማኖት) from Abuna Marqos, bishop of Ethiopia, to the community of Walatta Petros, about the incarnation and trinity, etc., and from bishop ሰዊሮስ ዘእ[ስ]ሙናይ; and from ገብረ እግዚአብሔር to ክርስቶ[ስ] ጳጳስ ዘብሔረ ኢትዮጵያ on the divinity and humanity of Jesus. F<locus target="#214r"/>-215r: Hymn to Mary, commonly called “Image of Edom,” መልክዐ፡ ኤዶም፡. Répertoire 221; MG 651ff. F. i v: Three notes, in different hands. Upper: Calendar of the fasting times of the year. Middle: Family geneology. Lower: Asmat prayer for protection from thieves, and the enemy, etc, in a trained hand. F. iii r: Asmat prayer for protection against snow. Illuminations added recently over text. <locus target="#88l"/>: upper margin, prayer to the memory of the departed, ወልደ ተክለ ሃይማኖት. <locus target="#161v"/>: Note of ownership: ዘወልደ ተክለ ሃይማኖት, and his wife, ወለተ ገብርኤል, his father, ወልደ ሚካኤል, his mother, ወለተ ንግሥት, his brothers, ወልደ እግዚ'እ, እልደ ጊዮርጊስ, and ወልደ ዘራዓ ቡሩክ. A plea to those who will pray with this Psalter, to remember ወልደ ተክለ ሃይማኖት in prayer. A curse on those who would steal or erase parts of the book. <locus target="#178r"/>: a pray to "give rest to the soul of Abuna ገብረ ማርያም. </summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="ms_i1">
                     <textLang/>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="Codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <watermark/>
                        </support>
                        <extent>
                           <measure unit="leaf"/>
                           <dimensions type="outer" unit="mm">
                              <height/>
                              <width/>
                              <depth/>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate when="1750">late-17th / early 18th century</origDate>
                  </origin>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
            <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
            <language ident="it">Italiano</language>
            <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="PL" when="2018-01-18">Created
                                    XML record from EMIP Collection Metadata.xsls</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab/>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
